<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Protestant peace-maker, or, A seasonable persuasive to all serious Christians who call themselves Protestants that laying aside calumnies, and all exasperating disputes, they would pursue charity, peace, and union, as the only means (now left us) of safety and reformation of the publick manners : with a postscript, or notes on Mr. Baxter's and some others late writings for peace / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross in Ireland.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17243145</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17243145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65556)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1162:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Protestant peace-maker, or, A seasonable persuasive to all serious Christians who call themselves Protestants that laying aside calumnies, and all exasperating disputes, they would pursue charity, peace, and union, as the only means (now left us) of safety and reformation of the publick manners : with a postscript, or notes on Mr. Baxter's and some others late writings for peace / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross in Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes The cry of holiness for peace: p. [35]-65.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term>Christian union.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106283:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Proteſtant Peace-Maker:</hi> OR, A SEASONABLE PERSUASIVE To all Serious CHRISTIANS, Who call themſelves PROTESTANTS, That laying aſide Calumnies, and all exaſperating Diſputes, they would purſue Charity, Peace, and Union, As the only Means (now left us) of <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Publick Manners.</p>
            <p>With a <hi>POSTSCRIPT,</hi> or <hi>NOTES</hi> on Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s, and ſome Others late Writings for <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDWARD</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Roſs,</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:106283:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106283:2"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Papers</hi> following came lately to my <hi>Hands,</hi> and finding them contain many things very <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and highly <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> at this Juncture, and writ with exceeding good and <hi>peaceable Deſign,</hi> and with great <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and no leſs ſenſe of <hi>Piety;</hi> I thought fit to make 'em Publick.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. W.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 14. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 24. line 22. for lighteſt, read <hi>higheſt.</hi> p. 98. l. r. r. all <hi>he.</hi> &amp; l. 13. r. <hi>methodos.</hi> p. 99. l. ult. r. his <hi>Prayer.</hi> p. 100. l. 22. dele <hi>it.</hi> p. 107. l. 22. r. <hi>my</hi> conſent. &amp; l. 31. r have <hi>refuſed</hi> to do. p. 110. l. 25. r. <hi>my</hi> Miniſtry. &amp; l. 28. r. <hi>as</hi> theſe. p. 111. l. 5 &amp; 9. r. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuſma. &amp; l. 27. r. <hi>wildly</hi> out.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:106283:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106283:3"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>The Text. II SAM. XV. 11.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <hi>And with</hi> Abſalom <hi>went Two hundred men out of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>that were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and they went in their ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and they knew not any thing.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the preſent ſtate of things, he that would deſign the greateſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service, will perhaps upon due conſideration ſcarce find any thing more worthy his fixing on, than to endeavour to ſweeten the Minds of men of <hi>one</hi> Faction towards thoſe of <hi>another;</hi> to take off and abate thoſe bitter apprehenſions and conceits, thoſe Heats and Furies, with which they mutually ſtand enraged.</p>
                  <p>My purpoſe is at preſent to do, what in an hours time I can, thereto: And that I may ſucceed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the better, I will deſire, that while I open my Text, you will be pleaſed to ſuſpend your Cenſures of any other deſign which you may imagine I have; not to think I had, in the choice thereof, any Eye at the preſent <hi>Plot,</hi> or any <hi>Great ones</hi> ſuppoſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106283:4"/> to be concerned therein: for by the ſequel of my Diſcourſe it will appear, I had not. I only intend to make ſuch Obſervations upon the Text, as ſhall moſt naturally conduce to the End I propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>The Words are a ſmall paſſage in the Hiſtory of <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s <hi>Conſpiracy.</hi> In Chap. 14 33. we find <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> reſtored to the Kings favour: and the firſt uſe he makes of it is, with more ſecurity and facility to lay a wicked deſign againſt his Crown and Life. Firſt, he endeavours to make himſelf conſiderable: he Attracts the Peoples <hi>Eyes</hi> by a Princely Grandure and Retinue; <hi>(He prepared himſelf Chariots and Horſes, and Fifty men to run before him,</hi> ver. 1.) and then their <hi>Hearts</hi> by crafty Inſinuations. He calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niates (but with a ſeeming tenderneſs and modeſty) his Fathers Government, condoles the Peoples Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, ſhews a Zeal for their redreſs; and all this with the moſt obliging Condeſcenſions and the faireſt Speeches imaginable: <hi>He riſes up early and ſtands by the way of the Gate,</hi> where People paſt to the Court for Juſtice: <hi>and if any came nigh him, to do him obeyſanee, he put forth his hand and took him and kiſſed him. And when any man that had a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie came to the King for Judgment; ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thy matters are good and right, but there is no man deputed of the King to hear thee. Oh! that I were Judge in the Land, I would do you Juſtice.</hi> From v. 2, to 6. In a word no Art, by which he might fix Negligence or Male-adminiſtration on his Father, or recommend himſelf as a ſweet, diligent and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince, is omitted: And by this means <hi>had he ſtole the Hearts of the men of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106283:4"/>
                  <p> After <hi>Forty years</hi> the Buſineſs is ripe, and an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procritical pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> gives it Birth. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom <hi>ſaid unto the King, I pray thee, let me go and pay my Vow which I have vowed unto the Lord in</hi> Hebron; <hi>for thy Servant vowed a Vow while I abode at</hi> Geſhur <hi>in</hi> Syria, <hi>ſaying, If the Lord ſhall bring me again indeed to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>then will I ſerve the Lord,</hi> ver. 7, 8. And having obtained and taken his leave at Court, away he goes for <hi>Hebron.</hi> But now not a word more of <hi>Religion;</hi> (for what have men of aſpiring and Treaſonable deſigns to do with it, any further than the Pretence of it ſerves their Intereſt?) no <hi>Vow</hi> ſhall you hear of perform'd, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept perhaps by a Mental reſervation his Vow were to do all that might be to take off the King. The Crown was the <hi>God he ſerved,</hi> and to make his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs thereto, the King was to be the Sacrifice. He therefore ſtrengthens his Party all he can, <hi>ſends Spies throughout all the Tribes of</hi> Iſrael, that they might be ready upon the firſt Voice of his being <hi>Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and at the ſame time ſets forward himſelf. <hi>And with</hi> Abſalom <hi>went Two hundred Men out of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>that were called; and they went in, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now upon this laſt Verſe it is that I am to make my <hi>Obſervations,</hi> having nothing to do with, nor any applications to make of any thing elſe in the ſtory. And they ſhall be only two, of thoſe upon the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of theſe <hi>Two hundred of</hi> Abſalom's <hi>Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and upon their <hi>Cauſe;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> of which (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their <hi>Character)</hi> ſeems really <hi>good,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> was ſtark <hi>naught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I obſerve then, Firſt, <hi>Men of a right honeſt Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be eaſily drawn into the Society of the vileſt Cauſe. They went in their ſimplicity.</hi> The Original
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106283:5"/> is a little more emphatical <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>They went in their Integrity. Integrity</hi> is more than <hi>Simplicity.</hi> They went only to bring the Heir apparent, and the Kings Darling, out of the Town, or to accompany him to his Devotions, and <hi>knew no more</hi> of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; though in the mean while their Company gives encouragement and furtherance to one of the vileſt Cauſes in the World, the moſt ungrateful and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Treaſon the Sun ever ſaw.</p>
                  <p>I add, Secondly, <hi>Such mens honeſt Intentions will not juſtifie their Engagements and Practices in the Society of a Wicked party.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe two Propoſitions I ſhall apply meerely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the pacifying or allaying <hi>Religious Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> at leaſt towards the uniting honeſt mens hearts and affections; nor ſhall I meddle one word with the croſs intereſts or fewds of <hi>State,</hi> from which <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt then, <hi>Men of honeſt Intentions may be drawn into fellowſhip of very wicked Factions,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more eaſily perhaps than others. To aſſert this, I ſhall only deſire you to reflect on the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Methods</hi> of inveigling or drawing in men of Religion into Parties, and together upon the <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Infelicities</hi> of ſuch mens <hi>Tempers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The great Art of Religious bewitching men into Parties, lies in the dextrous applicat on of fine <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> and <hi>Pretences. By good words and fair</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. xvi. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Speeches</hi> theſe Artiſans <hi>deceive the hearts of the ſimple,</hi> or of the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Men that walk in their Integrity,</hi> as in the Text.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106283:5"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Promiſes</hi> in matter of Religion (to which again I admoniſh my Diſcourſe confines it ſelf) are uſually,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Of greater Purity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Of more Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And though it be very true, that the ſober, plain, ſtrict Chriſtianity, which we know conſiſts in an holy heart and li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, poſſeſſes men really of the moſt of theſe ſo great promiſed goods; yet is there not the wildeſt, vileſt Religion in the World, the Profeſſors whereof are not ſtill cracking of theſe Golden Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, whereſoever they have any hopes of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes. They will <hi>promiſe you liberty,</hi> though at the ſame time <hi>themſelves are the Servants of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19. Their <hi>Mouth</hi> ſhall <hi>ſpeak great ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling words</hi> (of perfection, perhaps) and they ſhall <hi>ſeparate themſelves,</hi> though all the while they are <hi>ſenſual, not having the Spirit,</hi> Jude <hi>v.</hi> 16 19. In all probability the language I uſe was meant of the old <hi>Gnoſticks;</hi> and impurer ſlaves of Villany cannot well be conceived than they were, notwithſtanding theſe ſo contrary Promiſes.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Pretences</hi> commonly are of the greateſt Zeal and Love for their Souls, whom they would gain to themſelves. Thus the falſe Apoſtles in <hi>Galat.</hi> iv 17. <hi>They zealouſly affect you—yea they would exclude us, that you might affect them.</hi> (ſo with ſome good Copies I read thoſe words.)</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Liberty</hi> is a tempting bait to all men; and what more proper to draw in men of honeſt hearts, than <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Purity?</hi> Eſpecially when all is ſet off with the greateſt Love to mens better parts, when 'tis pleaded by thoſe that would win them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106283:6"/> that it is the Perſons thus to be brought in that will be the great gainers, that themſelves have no intereſt of their own, at leaſt none ſecular, or of this World.</p>
                  <p>Such plauſible <hi>Topicks</hi> as theſe can ſcarce fail of being effectual, if we conſider what was the ſecond member deſired to be reflected on, ſome <hi>Infelicities</hi> naturally attending the <hi>temper</hi> of good and honeſt-hearted men.</p>
                  <p>As 1. <hi>Eaſineſs, Sweetneſs</hi> and <hi>Ductility.</hi> They are not, nor haply ever have been, conſcious to themſelves of ſuch Falſeneſs as rules and actuates others; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they ſcarce imagine it incident unto Chriſtian men; they being the properties of <hi>Charity</hi> (of which Grace ſuch mens hearts are full) <hi>to bear all things, believe all things, hope all things</hi> (1 Cor. 13. 7.) and eſpecially, where yet nothing appears evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the contrary, to believe and hope the beſt, theſe kind of men too readily ſwallow the bait. For it is plain, this their Chriſtian temper renders them at once <hi>leſs Suſpicious</hi> and <hi>more Credulous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor is it to be denied (2.) That in many men of very honeſt hearts there is more <hi>ſhort-ſightedneſs,</hi> and <hi>want of judgment,</hi> than is commonly found in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of much worſe Morals. The uprighteſt men are not ever the profoundeſt: It is not given to all to ſmell Conſequences at a great diſtance. Even in the beginning of Chriſtianity, when the Evidences of it were more freſh, and the Power more miraculous, <hi>Not many of the wiſe men after the fleſh were called,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27. And be ſure <hi>Artis eſt celare artem</hi> in this caſe alſo; the Perſons, who practiſe, remove at firſt as far as may be out of reach, not only the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right miſchievous and wicked part of their deſign,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106283:6"/> but whatever might give jealouſie or ſuſpicion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Theſe poor men in the Text heard of a <hi>Vow,</hi> but not a word of a <hi>Conſpiracy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To be brief, (3.) <hi>Inconſideration, Half-conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or perhaps <hi>Prejudicate conſideration,</hi> may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray men of very ſincere Minds into very unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cauſes and Practices. The firſt and ſecond of theſe, namely <hi>Inconſideracy,</hi> or <hi>Half-conſidering,</hi> muſt needs be admitted in theſe men here following <hi>Abſalom;</hi> and the laſt of theſe, <hi>viz. Prejudice,</hi> and the force of it, no mans Honeſty forthwith exempts him from, though by degrees it may work it out. Education, Cuſtom, Affection to their own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Laws, fear of diſpleaſing, &amp;c. ſo clouded the Judgments (at leaſt ſwayed the Practice) even of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> that they went aſide to ſome acts of <hi>Judaiſm (Gal.</hi> 2. 11, 12, 13, 14.) <hi>They walked not uprightly,</hi> but were <hi>to be blamed,</hi> and even <hi>others</hi> were <hi>carried away with their diſſimulation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the whole now, ſuppoſing thoſe who ſtudy to make or maintain Parties, have the Art (which few of them want) to apply ſuch <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> as above-mentioned, to honeſt men (of <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>Charitable tempers</hi> indeed, but not of the <hi>deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Judgments,</hi> and beſides a little <hi>inconſiderate</hi> (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally perhaps) and by an unlucky Age or juncture of Circumſtances prejudiced too) it will move no reaſonable perſons wonder, though it may do his pity, that ſuch men ſhould be thus led aſide.</p>
                  <p>I have now proved my <hi>first Obſervation</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently <note place="margin">Application.</note> for my deſign, and give me leave briefly to <hi>apply</hi> it thereto.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106283:7"/>
                  <p> I therefore humbly and paſſionately Expoſtulate with perſons of all ſorts, who will be juſt to their own Reaſon, whether this Conſideration, <hi>That men of upright and ſincere intention may be,</hi> many times, <hi>drawn in into a bad Cauſe or Party,</hi> deſerve ſo much their <hi>Indignation,</hi> as Affections contrary, namely <hi>Commiſeration</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion.</hi> Even the <hi>Laws</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">L. Perſpicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum D. de Poenis.</note> themſelves (I mean the <hi>Civil Laws)</hi> diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt mens <hi>Crimes</hi> and their <hi>Misfortunes.</hi> The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher is yet more accurate, and puts a difference betwixt <hi>Misfortunes, Faults,</hi> and <hi>Injuries. Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes,</hi> ſaith he, are ſuch which are neither done with ill intent, nor could be foreſeen. <hi>Faults,</hi> which might have been foreſeen, but were done with no ill intent. <hi>Injuries</hi> (or downright vicious acts) are ſuch <note place="margin">Rhetoric. l. 1. c. 13.</note> which are deſigned, and done with evil intent. When therefore we ſee men engaged in a Profeſſion and way which to us ſeems groſs, let it ſuffice us at firſt to judge of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> they are in, and that according to evidence; and becauſe all is not yet clear as to their <hi>Perſons,</hi> to ſuſpend as to them any ſevere and mercileſs Sentence, let us be content to think the men no more guilty than their circumſtances, (which too may be to us much unknown) do make them. We underſtand not <hi>(firſt)</hi> what <hi>intentions</hi> they carry, perhaps as honeſt as they are capable of. Nor <hi>ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> what <hi>Temptations</hi> were upon them, how far they have been practiced on. Nor yet again, what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or Morally unavoidable, <hi>Infelicities</hi> they are or have been under. For theſe and many other Reaſons we are not, we cannot be their Judges. Eſpecially, we want Authority, we have not yet our Commiſſion, the ſeaſon is not yet come. <hi>Judge nothing before the time,</hi> 1 Cor. iv. 5. Admit the Saints are to <hi>judge</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106283:7"/> 
                     <hi>the World;</hi> 'tis only as <hi>Aſſeſſors of Chriſt:</hi> Let us ſtay then till <hi>the Lord come,</hi> and wait our time. Things are not yet ripe, nor come to light: We may adjudge that to be mens <hi>Crime</hi> which is not ſo much as their <hi>fault,</hi> if all could be duly opened. Much more Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitous will it be after ſuch immature, unwarrantable and hard Sentence paſt, to purſue them, whom we have thus cenſured with ſuch irreconcileable heats and keeneſs; which, if all were true that we have too raſhly judged, would be more than perhaps, even in ſuch caſe, Chriſtianity would allow.</p>
                  <p>But admit there were <hi>ſome</hi> particular Perſons, of the Factions we diſlike, every whit as bad as their cauſe, <hi>incorrigibly guilty</hi> and uncurable; yet can we perſwade our ſelves <hi>All</hi> are ſo? 'Tis a bad Religion indeed, of which there are none good: And perhaps amongſt all thoſe ſeveral Profeſſions which lay a claim to the ſtyle of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> there is none ſo bad in which ſome excellenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is not to be ſound; If we ſurvey all impartially and with Candour, haply in each we may diſcover <hi>Peculiar Commendables:</hi> In <hi>Nonconformiſts, Fervour in Prayer, Indefatigable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Holy duties, Care in inſtructing and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Families, ſtrict obſervation of the Lords day, &amp;c.</hi> beſides a great deal of <hi>Negative Sanctity</hi> at the leaſt: No Profaneneſs, no common Swearing, Curſing, or the like. In <hi>Quakers, Plaineſs of habit,</hi> general <hi>ſimplicity, modeſty,</hi> and <hi>frugality</hi> of living, <hi>Reverence of Oaths</hi> (even to exceſs) <hi>Faithfulneſs in their words,</hi> and perhaps divers other, good qualities, which occur not to me now. Even in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, amongſt the very Common People, at ſome ſeaſons, what <hi>Mortification, Faſting, Absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, Obedience to Superiours</hi> (though blind?)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106283:8"/> And in a multitude of thoſe of their <hi>Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> what frequent, what <hi>Zealous devotions,</hi> what <hi>strictneſs perpetually,</hi> what <hi>Self-denial, Obſervance of Vows</hi> (though thoſe perhaps in many raſh and highly inſnaring, and generally of things beyond what the Chriſtian Law ever intended to enjoyn) what <hi>ſtrange abandoning of their own wills,</hi> though too often to the conduct of thoſe, who are much worſe than themſelves? But in theſe ſeveral ſorts mentioned, can any ſay, <hi>All</hi> are <hi>Hypocritical</hi> in theſe Obſervances? The <hi>Phariſees</hi> in our Lords time were a vile Sect, inſomuch that, from them then, <hi>Phariſaiſm</hi> is become a name for Pride, Vain-glory, Hypocriſie, and many ſuch qualities concurring in one curſed mixture: But even amongſt them in thoſe very daies was there a <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> a <hi>Zacheus,</hi> a <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathea,</hi> nay a <hi>Paul</hi> too, and perhaps divers more, whoſe Names the Holy Ghoſt did not think fit to honour in Sacred Records. Let us not therefore with ſuch unlimited <hi>Zeal</hi> (which for want of <hi>Omniſciency</hi> muſt needs be ſometimes <hi>without knowledge)</hi> run againſt whole Parties; but only againſt Crimes and Criminals. Let us temper our Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Chriſtian pity, Gentleneſs, Charity, and the conſequents hereof, hoping and believing the beſt; <hi>Of ſome have compaſſion, making a difference</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jude verſ. 22.</note> betwixt the Abuſed and the Abuſers, being readier to ſave as many as we can by <hi>pulling them out of the fire,</hi> than to give any up for loſt, and call for <hi>Fire</hi> down <hi>from Heaven</hi> upon them. As amongſt the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> of old, ſo amongſt thoſe of the vileſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions amongſt us, there may be <hi>many who have not known the depths of Satan,</hi> or at leaſt who would be <note place="margin">Revel. 2. 24.</note> glad fairly to be drawn out of them.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106283:8"/>
                  <p> But I have too long I fear inſiſted on this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. From moving <hi>Pity</hi> therefore unto others, let us proceed to take <hi>Caution</hi> as to our ſelves. For the ſecond thing we obſerv'd upon the matter related in the Text was, that <hi>Honeſt intentions</hi> will <hi>not juſtifie</hi> mens <hi>engaging</hi> or <hi>proceeding</hi> in an <hi>ill Cauſe.</hi> They do undoubtedly before God, in ſome conſiderable meaſure, <hi>extenuate</hi> the <hi>guilt;</hi> and 'tis fit that before humane Juſtice, when they really appear, they ſhould prevail for <hi>alleviating puniſhment.</hi> But that, which is in its own nature evil, will be evil ſtill; though a man of upright heart was ſurprized or betray'd thereinto.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, If the Matter be more properly againſt <hi>God,</hi> although the mans Intentions were right, it will be an Act of Impiety, and ſo, though a <hi>ſin of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> yet a <hi>ſin</hi> ſtill: No man will maintain Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance warrants an Act; nay it does not fully excuſe it: <hi>He that knew not and did commit things worthy of ſtripes, was</hi> to be <hi>beaten,</hi> though but <hi>with few ſtripes,</hi> Luke xii. 48. And it will be difficult to aſſign a good reaſon why that paſſage ſhould not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted of <hi>Invincible Ignorance:</hi> though (God knows) the Ignorance of this Age and Nation muſt be imputed generally to Idleneſs, Heedleſsneſs, Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſs, or Affectation: And theſe are ſuch Excuſes and Pleas as no wiſe man would be fond of, or can hope will mend his caſe. In the Old Law, <hi>The Soul which committed a Treſpaſs and ſinned, even through Ignorance, in the Holy things of the Lord, was to bring his Treſpaſs Offering to the Sanctuary:</hi> And beſides that, to make amends alſo for the harm that he had done in the Holy thing, and <hi>add the fifth part thereto and give it to the Prieſt;</hi> Not till this was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106283:9"/> done was the Prieſt to make Attonement for him, nor without Attonement thus made would it be forgiven him. <hi>Levit.</hi> V. 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>Again, If the matter more directly be againſt my <hi>Neighbour,</hi> 'tis truly and really <hi>Treſpaſs</hi> or <hi>Hurt,</hi> though I did not intend it as ſuch; nor is his da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the leſs, becauſe I deſigned it not: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo under the Law, Reſtitution and Sacrifice was to be made in caſe of <hi>Treſpaſſes of Ignorance</hi> againſt <hi>man,</hi> as well as againſt <hi>God. If a Soul ſwear, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing with his lips to do evil, or to do good</hi> [we muſt ſupply (as is apparent by the ſcope of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text) <hi>in matters appertaining to his Neighbour] whatſoever it is that the man ſhall pronounce with an Oath, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth it, then ſhall he be guilty;</hi> that is, obliged to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Reſtitution for the Treſpaſs of his Ignorance, <hi>Levit.</hi> V. 4. That, I ſay, this Text is to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted of Common matters betwixt man and man, and not of the Holy or Devoted things, is evident by its Antitheſis to <hi>verſ.</hi> 15, 16, above touched. And further, the parallel place <hi>(Numb.</hi> V. 6, 7, 8.) which preſcribes expreſly the like amends, with addition of the <hi>fifth part to the principal,</hi> to be reſtored to him againſt whom the Treſpaſs was done, or in caſe of his being dead, to his next Kinſman, is an ample proof of the intent of the Law in this caſe. Acts, by which the Right and Property of God or our Neighbour is invaded or ſuffers, are really in the judgment of the Law of God, <hi>Treſpaſſes,</hi> though we did not intend a Treſpaſs, but were ignorant.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106283:9"/>
                  <p> The ſame muſt I ſay, Thirdly, of ſins againſt <hi>our own ſelves.</hi> If I fall into a ſin againſt my ſelf, and ſuch perhaps by which I really ſcandal others (that is, Embolden or encourage them to do the like) my Honeſt intention takes not off the Nature of Sin, nor Reality of the Scandal. We will inſtance in <hi>Drunkenneſs;</hi> we cannot well deny that Charity to many of them, who (in the language of the World) ſometimes <hi>play the good Fellows;</hi> but to think, they do not ordinarily meet, with deſigns to make Beaſts of one another, much leſs deliberately do they drink to intoxicate their own Heads, and forfeit their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: yet if they, beyond their intention, do either the one or the other, can we excuſe them from Drunkenneſs, or (according to their Quality) from having given <hi>ſcandal,</hi> becauſe we cannot conceive them to have been deſignedly drunk? <hi>Geneſ.</hi> XI. 21, <hi>&amp;c. Noah</hi>'s <hi>caſe</hi> was a ſingular one (far I mean from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any of the ordinary circumſtances of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive drinking) yet who will acquit it either from <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Scandal?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the whole then, Sin is Sin, notwithſtanding our Ignorance or Honeſt intentions.</p>
                  <p>But for fuller and more ſatisfactory proof hereof, I will ſet down, <hi>what Particulars</hi> are neceſſary to make an <hi>Action</hi> truly and Chriſtianly <hi>Good</hi> or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable: and if, when I have ſo done, it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that Honeſty of Intention is but <hi>One</hi> of the Points requiſite to the conſtituting any Action ſuch, I will then demand, It ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be acknowledged, that mens Honeſt intentions do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> juſtifie their engaging or proceeding in a bad C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe: For otherwiſe, where many conditions are required, one ſhould be all, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106283:10"/> is, more than One. And the due ſtating this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (beſides the Evidence which it will give to the Propoſition in hand) will further ſatisfie an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant doubt, which may ariſe upon the whole proof, thus: If my upright and Honeſt heart be not enough to juſtifie me in my engag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ments, or in the courſe that I take, What then further am I to look after, that I may throughly approve my ſelf to God and Man? This caſe many a Conſcientious perſon would be apt to put, when the Truth contended for were demonſtrated beyond all doubt: and therefore I ſhall truſt none will judge me extravagant, if I make the Reſolution hereof a ſecond Proof of the Obſervation I made.</p>
                  <p>Now in Anſwer hereto, I ſay, Firſt, That any Action may be truly good or warrantable, there is requiſite an <hi>Intrinſecal Rectitude,</hi> or Lawfulneſs, in the Nature of the thing. I take <hi>Rectitude</hi> here in a very large ſenſe, ſo as to exclude only all Obliquity or ſwerving from the Precept. Now ſuch <hi>Rectitude</hi> I affirm neceſſary; and indeed the Matter needs not (for it ſcarce admits) any proof, it approving it ſelf to our very Reaſon. Who can conceive, that what the Eternal Laws of God have made unlawful, any created or derivative Power can hallow or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize? Nothing hinders, but in a Moral ſenſe we may apply hereto that of the Royal Preacher, <hi>Conſider the work of God: Who can make that ſtraight which he hath made crooked?</hi> Eccleſ. VII. 13. And ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude there is (1.) In all points which are matter of Command, and made our <hi>Duties</hi> by the Law of God or Nature. (2.) In all points of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> or ſuch matters, which, being no wiſe forbidden unto us, are left to our diſcretion or prudential choice.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106283:10"/> And divers ſuch Caſes there are in humane life, (whatever ſome men pretend to the contrary) in which, what part ſoever we take we ſin not. To perſons under certain circumſtances, ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, even touching ſo weighty a concern as <hi>Marriage,</hi> Let them <hi>do what they will,</hi> marry or marry not, in either <hi>they ſin not,</hi> 1 Cor. VII. 36. Again in caſe of diſtinction of Meats, under ſuch and ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, <hi>Meat commendeth us not to God: For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if we eat, are we the better, or if we eat not, are we the worſe,</hi> 1 Cor. VIII. 8. Of one of theſe two ſorts muſt the thing to be done be, in caſe the Action be good or warrantable.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Though <hi>Honeſt intention</hi> do not juſtifie an evil Act or Cauſe, yet can no Act or cauſe, in which any man is engaged, be truly juſt without <hi>ſuch intention:</hi> And great care ought to be uſed herein, for that men are apt to flatter themſelves, and think better both of themſelves and their Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than truly they deſerve. It is requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we conſider, Honeſt intention may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be ſuch only <hi>Confuſedly</hi> and in the General (in which caſe it is much akin to the nature of <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Righteouſneſs)</hi> when meerly we propound no Evil to our ſelves: Such ſeems the Honeſt intention of theſe <hi>Two hundred men</hi> in the Text: now this kind is too inform and immature to wear the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Virtuous, Praiſe-worthy,</hi> or <hi>truly good;</hi> much leſs will it make our Actions ſuch. Intention truly good muſt be more <hi>diſtinct,</hi> particular and poſitive. And to that purpoſe it is neceſſary.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we be fully ſatisfied of the Right and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, both of our Cauſe and particular Actions which we go about.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106283:11"/> 2. That we engage in them with a deſign to pleaſe God, or to attain ſome conſiderable good, in the getting or enjoying of which good we have no ſuſpicion at all we ſhall diſpleaſe him. If it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with us, <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith,</hi> that is, from a Conſcience fully ſatisfied, touc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or lawfulneſs of the means uſed, or ends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; whatſoever, I ſay, is not thus of Faith, <hi>is Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It will therefore become every man, in matters of moment, not to truſt too much an <hi>Extemporary good intention,</hi> as I may ſo call it; but to examine all, and to be careful, that, as there is no evil in his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo there be due and particular good.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I muſt add, To conſtitute any <hi>Action</hi> juſt or warrantable, is requiſite the Integrity, at leaſt harmleſsneſs of the <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> as of <hi>Perſon, Place, Time, Manner,</hi> and the like: For, not only may that be <hi>lawful</hi> to <hi>one</hi> man, but alſo in great ſtrictneſs his <hi>Duty,</hi> which in <hi>another</hi> would be groſs <hi>Sin.</hi> To take an inſtance familiar at ſuch ſeaſons as this; namely the Executing, nay even the implead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and arraigning Malefactors. To give evidence againſt them, to accuſe and charge them, is the <hi>Duty</hi> of Witneſſes and of particular Officers: but in other Perſons, that is in the generality of the People preſent, who know nothing or little of their caſes, or are not by their place called to intermeddle, it would be <hi>ſin</hi> and an Exceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng their Calling; at beſt, all would judge it abominable impertinence. Again, To execute them when condemned, at leaſt to ſee they be executed, is the duty of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and ſuch Legal Officers: but if a Private perſon, or other by Law not authorized, ſhould preſently, upon their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106283:11"/> having received Sentence, kill them in the place he could next come at them, I know not how he could acquit himſelf of <hi>Blood-guiltineſs.</hi> And then, even thoſe very Officers to whom it belongs, are bound, not only by Law, but Conſcience, to obſerve, as near as may be done, <hi>Manner, Place, Time,</hi> and like Circumſtances: Otherwiſe the very Execution of what they think <hi>Juſtice,</hi> may prove <hi>unjuſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But more particularly to our preſent Buſineſs. As to the <hi>Manner</hi> of Doing ſuch things which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are Good or Lawful, there are two conſiderable Points, which the frequency perhaps of Good mens miſcarriages makes neceſſary to be preſſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">1. That all <hi>Duties</hi> be performed <hi>without Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and vain glory. Though the Matter of fact be moſt Obligatory, or of the Divineſt and moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent nature in the World; yet if the Affectation of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, or of the popular Eye and Vogue, interpoſe in its performance, it unhallows the Action, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us of the Reward. This our Lord teacheth as to <hi>Alms</hi> and <hi>Liberality; Matth.</hi> VI. 2. As to <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>Devotion, ver.</hi> 5. As to <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ver.</hi> 16. And by parity of reaſon, 'tis true of any other (otherwiſe) good works.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That <hi>Liberties</hi> (or things free) be ever uſed <hi>without ſcandal.</hi> By <hi>Scandal</hi> I mean, (with the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture generally) <hi>the Drawing or Encouraging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do what they are not in Conſcience convinced they may do:</hi> Which notion we ſhall do well to take notice of, as well for the ſatisfying and confirming our Conſciences againſt unreaſonable ſcruples and fears, as for the guiding our Practice. For this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106283:12"/> admitted to be the nature of Scandal, it is not then every one, which is capable of <hi>adminiſtring matter of Scandal</hi> by the uſe of his Liberty; but only ſuch Perſonages, by whoſe examples others are apt to frame their lives. Nor again is it every one that is apt to be <hi>ſcandalized,</hi> or <hi>receive ſcandal,</hi> but only the <hi>Weak;</hi> People who underſtand not duly the rule of life, or are not able to diſtinguiſh betwixt <hi>Duty, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Sin.</hi> But if it ſo come to paſs, that any of us, being perſons of reputed prudence and piety, and ſo of authority and conſiderable remark in the world, uſe ſuch freedom in words or deeds before unskilful Judges of things, that they clearly are drawn in, or likely to be drawn in, to do what they doubt lawful, or believe unlawful, be the matter of fact on our ſides never ſo juſt or innocent, and our hearts never ſo ſincere therein, yet we, by becoming thus a ſtumbling-block to others, are not only ſinners againſt them, but alſo againſt their Lord and ours, Chriſt himſelf. For, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> VIII. 12. <hi>When ye ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Brethren, and wound their weak Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ye ſin againſt Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the whole then, that any Action be good and warrantable, we ſee it is neceſſary, That the <hi>Matter</hi> be <hi>Right or Lawful,</hi> That our <hi>Intention</hi> be truly <hi>Honeſt</hi> (and both theſe points to us diſtinctly known to be ſo) That, laſtly, in our management, ſuch <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity</hi> or Harmleſneſs of <hi>Circumſtances</hi> do concur, as that by, or in none of them we violate any Law of God: And particularly, <hi>Duties</hi> muſt be performed <hi>without Oſtentation, Liberties</hi> uſed <hi>without Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106283:12"/>
                  <p> And now to ſum up our Evidence: If good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion change not the Nature of things, but Impiety be impiety ſtill, injuſtice, Injuſtice ſtill, and ſo as to all Acts of Uncharitableneſs, Intemperance, Impurity, and whatſoever is of like nature, none of them all are ſanctified by a good intent (however real, not pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed); If to conſtitute any Cauſe or Action there be diverſe other Material points requiſite, beſides the ſincerity of our Intentions, any one of which points failing, the Cauſe or Action good, according to the nature of the failure, partakes of true and proper guilt (and all theſe things are abundantly proved) then is it evident that no mans good intention will warrant or juſtifie either his engaging or proceeding in a bad cauſe. Nay, if we will be juſt to our own Senſe and Reaſon, it is further, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> and beyond what we in the beginning propounded, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſible from what has been evinced, That good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions will not warrant mens ingaging and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even in a good Cauſe it ſelf under any undue Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
                  <p>It remains now, that I bring all home to bear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deſign I laid down in the beginning, and that I preſs upon all ſorts practice ſuitable to the Truths I have aſſerted. I ſhall only have time for a double <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. And the firſt of them ſhall be, <hi>That we</hi> all of us again and again <hi>conſider every Cauſe</hi> which tempts our eſpouſal, <hi>before we engage</hi> our ſelves; or, if already, without due conſideration, engaged, <hi>before we further proceed</hi> therein. It is not enough that our Intentions in the General be good: We have heard, they may be generally good, when they want maturity of prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106283:13"/> thought and conſideration to make them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly ſuch. Beſides there are other points, of great moment, to be looked after: I will not be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in recapitulations, I will only put the Caſe in ſhort to all our Conſciences. We are haply moſt of us zealous in our ways, and for our own Party. But have we, to full reſolution and ſatisfaction of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, weighed the preſent ſtate and <hi>intereſt of the Common Chriſtianity?</hi> Have we ſtated the <hi>Cauſes,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we mutually <hi>Separate?</hi> Are they ſuch which we judge in good earneſt will bear us out? And then, do we withdraw from one another no farther, nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or maintain any greater diſtance, than theſe Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will warrant? Finally, in the whole have we no by and ſiniſter ends, no deſign but ſincerely of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſuch which we dare carry to, and own before God's Tribunal? Happy were it for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, would our Diviſions endure this Teſt, or had Chriſtian men (generally) conſidered, or would yet conſider theſe things as they ought. But alas! even in Religion it ſelf, the far greateſt part <hi>walk at</hi> a meer <hi>peradventure:</hi> At leaſt, they are carried along with that Current into which their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, Condition, or <hi>Genius</hi> happens to caſt them. And being once engaged <hi>(Veſtigia nulla retrorſum)</hi> almoſt as few return from their reſpective Zealotry, as from the Grave. They rather <hi>ruſh on like the Horſe into the Battle;</hi> and the Similitude holds alſo, farther than it were to be wiſht, they are rid too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, even to their own deſtruction. My Brethren, if we have any of us been unhappy in raſh and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Diviſions, or in addicting our ſelves to any ſo divided Parties, yet let us not perpetuate, and, as far as in us lies, eterniſe our own and the Churches
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106283:13"/> miſeries. If either our Reaſon, or our Chriſtianity, or our own or the Common ſafety be ſignificant to us, <hi>Let us gird up the loins of our mind, and be ſober:</hi> Let us recollect and ſummon together our conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive powers, and endeavour to judge like Men and Chriſtians, Where we are, and how we ſtand. And if upon the whole, all be clear, and Conſcience ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied, yet let us remember, we <hi>owe</hi> ſomewhat <hi>to the World;</hi> and the leaſt, that can be, will be, by all honeſt means to endeavour <hi>its quiet.</hi> And verily he is unworthy of his own quiet, at leaſt will not long enjoy it, who is not content a little to deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his own fancies, for others and the Publick ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>To bring this Exhortation a little nearer to our preſent Circumſtances and Condition. Let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, we here are not <hi>Law-givers,</hi> nor are therefore to conſider what is <hi>our own will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> what <hi>we</hi> would have <hi>Enacted,</hi> nay, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps what is in our judgment <hi>fit</hi> to be injoyned, but what <hi>actually</hi> is already <hi>injoyned,</hi> and what it is <hi>lawful</hi> for us <hi>to obey.</hi> As to thoſe of us, who have obeyed the Laws, we deſire only thus much charity from Diſſenters (which we will ſurely repay, <hi>good meaſure, preſſed down, ſhaken together, and running over)</hi> we deſire, I ſay, only thus much charity, that we may not all of us be thought to have acted blindfold, or upon corrupt inducements. There is a multitude of us can, in the fear of God, profeſs we have again and again conſidered the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and according to our duty, as we believe, we have been, and are <hi>obedient, not only for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake. Conſcience</hi> we can ſay, not meerly <hi>our own, but others,</hi> of whom we are,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106283:14"/> and muſt be tender. And we doubt not but in this our obedience <hi>we pleaſe God,</hi> and are not <hi>unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> unto <hi>Men.</hi> We hope further, we are able to approve our ſelves to the Great Judge of all in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral fore-mentioned Particulars; at leaſt according to that equitable allowance, which our gracious God, through Jeſus Chriſt, gives to humane infirmities, and which the beſt of us all muſt crave, even in our beſt Actions. Now as to <hi>thoſe who withdraw</hi> from us: We call not into queſtion the <hi>ſincerity of their intentions,</hi> we neither are, nor deſire to be Judges thereof; We profeſs we generally judge the beſt, and where we cannot ſo judge, we ſuſpend our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But we deſire them to reſume and reiterate the conſideration of the <hi>Rectitude of their Cauſe:</hi> For we muſt acknowledge and avow, we neither could ſee, nor have been ſhewen, any warrant, which makes it <hi>lawful</hi> to any, much leſs their <hi>duty,</hi> as many pretend, to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from that <hi>Church,</hi> which neither urges nor receives any <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> but what muſt be confeſſed pure; which <hi>worſhips</hi> God by no <hi>Office</hi> more or leſs than what is of his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and the <hi>forms</hi> thereof <hi>not diſſonant</hi> to his word; whoſe <hi>Government,</hi> if the ſenſe of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in all Ages (till within this hundred and few more years, and of the Generality of it ſtill) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Holy Scriptures, may be heard, is truly <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical;</hi> and in fine, whoſe <hi>Diſcipline</hi> (though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in ſome things to truckle under the iniquity of times) ſuffers few or none to be ſo bad as they would, and encourages all to be as good as they can. If it be lawful to ſeparate from ſuch a Church, where ſhall we find that, from which we may not ſeparate? And where then will be an end of Diviſions? In the Church
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106283:14"/> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> where were ſundry greater Diſorders and Corruptions tolerated, than can be pretended amongſt us (that we know of) the Apoſtle does not tolerate, but ſeverely reprove their Diviſions, and both cenſure the Authors of them, as Perſons <hi>to be avoided,</hi> and the Abettors, as <hi>Carnal.</hi> Then, laſtly, as to the Management of this departure, we paſſionately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech, and in the Lord conjure, all, who are guilty of withdrawing, that they will conſider whether the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> either of making or maintaining it, be <hi>warrantable,</hi> or indeed well excuſable, Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and briefly: Suppoſe things ſtood ſo, that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration were their <hi>Duty;</hi> yet is <hi>Theirs</hi> without <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation,</hi> as all Duties ought to be? Do not they publickly value themſelves thereupon, and deſpiſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Are not they (in their own Language) The <hi>Saints,</hi> and the reſt of the Nation Thoſe who are <hi>without,</hi> the People of the World, not to take up more odious Names? Again, admit <hi>Separation</hi> from us were <hi>lawful,</hi> yet is <hi>theirs</hi> without <hi>ſcandal?</hi> Without ſcandal to the <hi>weak of their own Church,</hi> without ſcandal to the <hi>weak of Ours?</hi> Without ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or ſcandal even to <hi>Jews?</hi> Without ſcandal to men of <hi>all Religions,</hi> or ſcandal to men of <hi>None?</hi> The good God be merciful unto us, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Chriſtian men from Partiality and Self-flattery.—But I muſt Contract.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. My Second Exhortation ſhall be, That being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in Conſcience touching the Right or Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our own engaging, in all points of our Cauſe, or, as ſome had rather ſpeak, touching the Excellency and Superlativeneſs of the way we are in, we would not ſpoil a good Cauſe by our ill Management. That
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106283:15"/> the Religious amongſt us are Divided at preſent, there is none who ſees not; Nor, that all the Petty Diviſions are reducible to theſe three Grand ones, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Regular Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Non-Conforming Proteſtants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Cauſe or way of the <hi>Firſt,</hi> I do declare, I judge, no Power on Earth, no nor (with all reverence be it ſpoken) of Heaven it ſelf, can make juſt: For, <hi>God cannot Ly,</hi> that is, contradict himſelf. The Doctrine they teach, profeſs, and (if we will credit them) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, is againſt expreſs Scripture, the Analogy of Faith, and the Conſent of the Ancient (and true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) Catholick Church: And indeed, in divers Points alſo againſt Senſe and Reaſon, the common Principles of Mankind. And too much of their Morals is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>The Cauſe or Way of the <hi>Second</hi> is juſt, if any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven. I need not ſpeak my mind again: I do not ſay, there is nothing amongſt us defective; nor that there is nothing which may be amended; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that there is no miſmenagement, or no evil People amongſt us. I do not believe there is, or will be ever, ſuch a Church on Earth: That accuſation, to the end of the world, will juſtly ly againſt the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Church; <hi>I have a few things againſt thee: Revel.</hi> II. 4. 14, 20. But I muſt avow, I know not that Church, which would take the <hi>Mote out of our Eye,</hi> that has not <hi>a Beam in her own.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Cauſe of the <hi>Third</hi> muſt be acknowledg'd by all indifferent and conſiderative men, at leaſt <hi>doubtful:</hi> For he is void of reaſon who ſhall deny, that diſputes with the lighteſt Probabilities are manag'd againſt it; and ſuch which with the moſt rational perſons turn the Scales. Poſſibly, to ſome of them who have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106283:15"/> it, it may not ſeem doubtful: But whatever my Charity may induce me to think it in any of them, were I my ſelf a mainteiner of it, I could not judge it in <hi>my ſelf</hi> any thing leſs, than <hi>Formal</hi> as well as <hi>Material Schiſm.</hi> But for the preſent we'll not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute the Point: Admit it to be <hi>lawful;</hi> I only move, that it be not <hi>miſmanaged,</hi> that Good men would not proſecute a lawful Cauſe in an unlawful manner, or by undue means, and ſo intangle themſelves and Cauſe in Injuſtice and Iniquity.</p>
                  <p>Having then concluded the Cauſe of the <hi>Regular Proteſtants,</hi> good and excellent; and for the preſent admitted (though not granted) that of the <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> to be lawful; there is chiefly a double miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menagement, which I muſt tax at preſent (and that on both ſides, for I would not be partial) and which the Exhortation in hand proceeds againſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The former of which is, <hi>Overcharging</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This, beſides that it renders us guilty of ſin, and makes ſtill our matters worſe, does further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us Both to our Common Enemies, and create to them ſweet Sport, and to our ſelves Scorn and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. The <hi>Nonconformiſts charge</hi> us moſt unjuſtly with <hi>Popery:</hi> Give me leave to beſeech theſe our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, that they will conſider what they ſay. If we had no Conſcience (which they would be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, ſhould they conclude of us) if it were all one to us, in point of Faith, what Religion were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht or went up, yet except they will alſo think us mand, and that we have renounced our worldly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, together with our Conſciences, they cannot think we are any Friends to Popery, or would make
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106283:16"/> any <hi>Advances</hi> towards it. Can they perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves we are ſo ſottiſh, or our Memories ſo ſhort, as that we have forgotten the <hi>Marian days?</hi> Do not we know, that if ever Popery get up again, we of the Miniſtry, and eſpecially thoſe of us who are in the higheſt Order, muſt firſt go to Stake? As to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they may ſcape: <hi>Theſe Sheep, what have they done?</hi> But their <hi>hands will</hi> ſurely <hi>be upon the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds.</hi> Or if we ſhould by flight, or any other baſe way, ſave our lives, (which as the world goes, we could ſcarce expect) if we ſhould, as <hi>Job</hi> expreſſes it, <note place="margin">Job XIX. 20.</note> come off <hi>with the skin of our Teeth,</hi> yet, is that ſuch a mercy or boon, which any can judge men in our preſent conditions fond of? Are our Families, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, our Honours, our Preferments nothing to us? (Sometimes theſe men think and ſay, we love the World well enough) Is there any <hi>Vicar, Parſon,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the Kingdom, that ſees not, or knows not, of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of his Pariſh, or the <hi>Titular</hi> of his See in preſent being? Do we not daily behold them walk the Streets, or know their Confinements? Are we ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their <hi>Claims,</hi> or that they look upon us on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and themſelves the true <hi>Proprietours,</hi> and that they now have a long time looked for the bleſſed hour? You cry out of us, I ſay, ſometimes that we are worldly, carnal men, that we only mind the <hi>Fleece,</hi> not the <hi>Flock:</hi> If we do even that, we cannot be Popiſhly affected: There is nothing ſo deſtructive of our worldly intereſt as Popery; That has already left no Beneſices or Livings vacant for us, and if it prevails will ſoon not leave us Air to breath. For ſhame then, interpret ſome mens Actions otherwiſe than you do: and if in all humane probability they act againſt their own Secular intereſt, in the things which they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106283:16"/> cannot but ſee, and do ſee as well as you, impute not thoſe actions to Popiſh affection, but good Conſcience. They dare not <hi>do evil that good may come,</hi> or be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, for their own preſervation. Thus as to one Party.</p>
                  <p>Now I will not deny but ſome of our men are quit with theſe falſe Accuſers, and pay them home in their own Coyn. (God forgive both). Hence ſo many bitter Invectives inſtead of Sermons; ſo much raking into old, forgiven, and it were to be wiſht, forgotten Crimes; charging the Villanies of the <hi>Abſaloms</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Individual of thoſe who <hi>went in the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of their heart, and knew not any thing:</hi> Hence, in common Diſcourſe, ſo many upbraidings of men with thoſe which were the ſins of their ignorance, youth and education, rather than of the men; ſuch care to ſtigmatize ſome perſons with the miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, which they have long ago repented of, and, if occaſion ſhould ſerve, would expiate with their lives; ſuch aggravating ſome Peoples innocent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and drawing thoſe Concluſions from them, which the poor men abhor, but never intended; with a world of like practices, familiar amongſt all Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans. Certainly, my Brethren, theſe things are very iniquitous: If my brother has <hi>repented</hi> of a <hi>ſin,</hi> God has taken it away from him; and the <hi>meaning</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had, was never <hi>his:</hi> I may not therefore impute either ſuch <hi>ſin,</hi> or ſuch <hi>meaning</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> or upbraid him therewith. We would think they gave us more than our due, who ſhould deal thus with us: Let us therefore our ſelves unlearn ſuch vile and pitiful Arts. I confeſs 'tis much another caſe, where men retain their ſins ſtill, and will not, without ſuch remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106283:17"/> be brought to acknowledgment or ſenſe of them: But even herein alſo care is to be had, and much pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence uſed: for we may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> injurious to our Cauſe by too much expoſing our Adverſary; An unintereſſed ſtander by will call ſuch diſcourſes <hi>Recriminations,</hi> not <hi>Defences;</hi> and will ſay the Caſe needs them, becauſe the Advocate uſes them. And as to the Perſons or Parties concerned; this kind of treatment can only tend to mutual exaſperation, upon which no good, becauſe no divine bleſſing, can be expected. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will be juſt to our ſelves, or our own beloved Cauſe, let us, on both ſides, forbear immoderate Charges, as being infallibly derogatory to whatſoever there is of true Juſtice either in our Cauſe or Defences thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Men may ſpoil a good Cauſe by too much <hi>Stiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Tenaciouſneſs</hi> of their own Senſe, and by this means keeping open ſuch Breaches, which might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily be cloſed. There is ſuch a thing, in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udgment, as <hi>Being righteous overmuch, and making our ſelves over-wiſe, (Eccleſ.</hi> VII. 16.) by which he ſuggeſts there, men may <hi>deſtroy themſelves.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> become <hi>deſolate,</hi> even to the admiration and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Beholders; or elſe ſtand ſingle and by themſelves, as the Marks of Common fury. If con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Parties may be ever guilty of this Evil, it is certainly in ſuch caſes wherein the Differences betwixt them being but ſmall, neither will recede the leaſt from their own Sentiments; or (which is with ſuch the ſame (for their own <hi>apprehenſions</hi> are too often herein made the meaſures) from their own <hi>Right;</hi> (as if nothing could be more Righteous than each of their Cauſes, nothing more infallible than each of their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106283:17"/> Judgments). And if ever men may expect ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of iſſue, it is when ſuch Differences are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuated upon ſuch mutual heights. Wherefore, <hi>A ſectâ infallibili libera Eccleſiam tuam Domine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I confeſs there are ſome who publiſh ſuch Principles and Poſitions of late, as infer <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in the Church not</hi> to be <hi>neceſſary:</hi> Theſe make the breach irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and therefore are not to be heard. There's an <hi>Argument</hi> now for <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> amongſt us in this Kingdom (I ſpeak to thoſe who call themſelves <hi>Proteſtants)</hi> which muſt be heard, and is uncontrolable: We muſt <hi>unite, or be deſtroy'd.</hi> At all times <hi>Chriſtian duty</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us thereto, now <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Self-preſervation.</hi> Two or more parties may ballance One, when any ſingle Other cannot. I ſpeak plain enough. Now if we muſt Unite, the only queſtion will be, Upon <hi>what terms?</hi> Muſt we of the eſtabliſht Church come over to you who Diſſent, or You come over unto us? We declare we cannot, without Schiſm: but are ready to ſacrifice all we can otherwiſe to the Publick Peace and Safety. And this Pretence is real: You, who diſſent, are very far from being all of a piece: Beſides thoſe Elder and leſs Anomalous Factions of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> there are <hi>Antinomians, Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Anabaptiſts, Quakers,</hi> and Sects which know not what they are, nor we what to call. All the world muſt allow there are Schiſms and much worſe, as far as worſe can be, amongſt ſuch an Heterogeneous Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as this. Should we yield to any one of theſe, we were yet as far from gaining the reſt, as we are now from uniting all.</p>
                  <p>Take thoſe two, which I called the <hi>Elder Parties</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106283:18"/> of the Diſſenters, How impoſſible a thing is it for them to agree what will ſatisfie them! They had a numerous <hi>Aſſembly</hi> gathered together of themſelves moſtly, which ſate many years. Did they agree then upon any common terms of Union betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Or are they agreed ſince? Let any produce the <hi>Accommodation</hi> if they can: and if not, let it be confeſt that there is Schiſm amongſt even theſe.</p>
                  <p>Again, take either of the Parties ſingle: Let them ſhew us, what Chriſtian Church upon the face of the Earth owns them, as they are broken off from the Eſtabliſht Church of <hi>England</hi> (and as indeed they broke down its Order, Form of Worſhip, Diſcipline and whole Frame, to their Power) Let them ſhew us, I ſay, <hi>what Proteſtant Church owns them,</hi> as ſuch, for a Church, or (as ſuch) holds Communion with them. If one of the Parties ſhould anſwer, The <hi>Kirk of Scotland;</hi> the Reply is obvious: The Eſtabliſht Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> was the ſame, in effect, with that of <hi>England,</hi> and fell by the ſame hands: And as to what the Anſwerers mean by the <hi>Kirk,</hi> 'twas only a Member of the <hi>Pars rea,</hi> a very guilty part of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or of the accuſed Body. It is well known, there is extant an <hi>Harmony</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of all the Reformed Churches throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſhew the World their Chriſtian Agreement and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In that <hi>Collection</hi> are extant with univerſal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, <hi>two Confeſſions of the Church of</hi> England, as by Law it then ſtood, and, bleſſed be God, now ſtands eſtabliſht: two, I ſay, becauſe different in Form, but of the ſame Subſtance, and very near of the ſame date. We can ſome of us remember the time, when the forementioned <hi>Aſſembly</hi> compiled alſo a <hi>Confeſſion</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106283:18"/> 
                     <hi>of Faith,</hi> and a good <hi>Latiniſt</hi> excellently tranſlated it, and in that form it was ſent abroad with a deſire and deſign to have it inſerted in the then new Edition of the <hi>Harmony of Confeſſions.</hi> But the Foreign Churches ſtood conſtant to the Two old ones, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the new. Judge hence what Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> they own, and whether they hold Communion with that People as a Church, whoſe Confeſſion they would not admit. They well ſaw the Admiſſion of it had deſtroyed the <hi>Harmony,</hi> that is, as well rendred the Collection contradictious in it ſelf, as brought too juſt an imputation of Schiſm upon the Reformation.</p>
                  <p>Further, in a word, What ſecurity can there be from partaking in <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and indeed, as it may happen, <hi>Hereſie</hi> too, in the Communion of that Church, the Form and Order of whoſe Worſhip and Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sacraments is not certainly known, nay, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their very Conſtitution, is no where twice the ſame; all being left to the gifts and diſcretion of the Miniſter, who is declared unfit for his Office if he need (and conſequently will uſe) a conſtant Form? What man can ſay, with any other than an Implicite Faith, and therefore what Church will ever declare, that they hold Communion, or agree in Worſhip, with ſuch a People? Herein this Generation of men has departed even from all the Foreign Presbyterian Churches themſelves, who all have their certain Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Forms of Publick Worſhip.</p>
                  <p>It were tedious to purſue more Particulars; give me leave to ſum up what has bee ſaid on this Head. Can it be expected (and much leſs demanded) by men of reaſon, that we ſhould relinquiſh and renounce a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106283:19"/> which has made us famous amongſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Reformed Churches, and has paſt their Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation from the beginning, to unite with men who are at a greater diſtance from one another (if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <hi>at least the</hi> ſeveral Sects) than perhaps we are from them all; the very ſobereſt Party of all whom (as they would be thought) if we would go about to agree to, we ſhall not find (as far as I can ſee) one Proteſtant Church would recommend them to our Fellowſhip by having firſt owned them as a Church, or having held Communion with them; nay, we are not ſure, that we can in Conſcience hold Communion with them; that is, joyn in, and conſent to, their Worſhip one hour our ſelves? Can this, I ſay, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected or demanded from us? It cannot ſurely. Some <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> may be on our hand <hi>abated</hi> or <hi>relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> (and had been doubtleſs long ago, if Men of eager and inflexible Spirits had not hindred): but the main Conſtitution we may not recede from. What moſt of the Diſſenters would be at (No Liturgy, no Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, no Uniformity, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> may not be, cannot be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Schiſm.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore again to take up my Exhortation: Let us reſolve upon yielding ſpirits; Let us move towards one another, in order to meeting. We of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Church do not ſay there is nothing amongſt us, which may be amended. Again, we do not ſay there is nothing among you which is to be approved. My Exhortation to you here only is, That as far as your Cauſe has any thing good in it, you would not blaſt that good, and the hopes of its taking, by an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal ſtiffneſs; and while you inſiſt on things, which are queſtionable, and (in the judgment of moſt others
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106283:19"/> but your ſelves) not ſit to be granted, keep open the breach to our Common Deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>The only ſteps, by which we can mutually move to Peace, I, with all ſubmiſſion, conceive to be theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we would all ſeriouſly, betwixt God and our own Conſciences, ſeverally, ſtudy Self-denial, (one of the great Leſſons our Lord taught us) and that with a peculiar eye and regard to Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. One man perhaps muſt deny himſelf of a certain kind of Popularity and Vulgar eſteem: Another, of an Idioſyncraſy, or particular humour, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that not ſo much natural as contracted: A third of ſomewhat elſe. All, of whatſoever good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us is leſs valuable than Common Union.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the ſobereſt of the Diſſenters would Catego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically and ſincerely publiſh, what of the Eſtabliſht Order they can agree to. 3. That they would actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally do, and teach their Followers to do, what they in Conſcience judge lawful. If theſe Points might be obtained, certainly in a very ſhort time a Conſultation of things would be reſumed: And then, let thoſe be blamed, who would not hear and do Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>But if theſe, and ſuch Diſcourſes as theſe, may not be heard, if we of the Church muſt only be Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated ſtill, as the great Enemies to a Publick Peace, and no means will take for the ſweetning and allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heights of thoſe Spirits we have to deal with, we can all of us only expect the fruit of Contention, and that is, <hi>Confuſion, and every Evil Work;</hi> one <note place="margin">James III. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> part of which will be, as already intimated, our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ruin. And let it be conſidered beforehand, when we ſhall have again ruin'd our ſelves by our own
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106283:20"/> hands, how poor a mitigation of mutual miſery it will be, to excuſe our ſelves with our <hi>Ignorance and Good meaning:</hi> Of which, when God comes to judge, the former perhaps will be found Stubborneſs, Heedleſneſs or Pride; and the later, not what its name imports, but ſomewhat, which we miſtook for it, called in true and proper ſpeaking, <hi>Self-flattery,</hi> or too good a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of our own Deceitful hearts, and ways.</p>
                  <p>To prevent then this miſery, if it be the will of God, Let us all <hi>Search and Try</hi> our <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Hearts,</hi> and be content to ſee our ſelves genuinly what we are, and to judge of our ways according to Truth and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs. And becauſe our own Scrutinies may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, Let that Appeal and Prayer of <hi>Davids</hi> dwell in all our hearts and lips. <hi>Pſalm</hi> CXXXIX. 23, 24. <hi>Search me, O God, and know my heart; Try me and know my thoughts: And ſee if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlaſting.</hi> Let us inculcate ſuch Petitions as theſe, and beat them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts at the Throne of Grace, till, being brought under the Power of them, we become content to be led into the ways of Charity, Peace and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yea, though they ſhould be found far different from thoſe which we have traverſt before with the greateſt Affection and Delight.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The good God pour into all our hearts ſuch Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sincerity and Honeſt Temper (the true Fruit of the Holy Spirit) through his Son Jeſus Chriſt; To whom, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:106283:20"/>
                  <p>THE CRY OF HOLINESS FOR PEACE.</p>
                  <p>A SERMON on Sunday, in time of the Aſſiſes there.</p>
                  <p>By the ſame Author.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1682.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:106283:21"/>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106283:21"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>The Text. HEBR. XII. 14.</bibl>
                     <q>Follow Peace with all Men, and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were eaſie from ſo pregnant a Paſſage of Holy Scripture, as this read, to ſuggeſt great variety of particular Subjects, each of which would adminiſter matter for much a larger Diſcourſe than I may be allowed at preſent.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Spirit in laying out our Chriſtian Duties conſiders us, either as ſingle perſons; and ſo the ſum of all that concerns us is <hi>Holineſs:</hi> Or elſe as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of ſome Society, more or leſs Publick; and ſo our main Duty is <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of both theſe the moſt zealous Endeavours and Practice we ſee ſtrictly injoyned in the Text. <hi>Follow Peace,</hi> that is, Purſue it with all urgency, yea, though it fly from you: And this in the greateſt extent, <hi>With all men.</hi> Then as to <hi>Holineſs,</hi> this is not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned with equal Emphaſis, but the purſuit thereof
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106283:22"/> inforced with the moſt moving Conſideration; <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> immediately relates to <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) that is, <hi>without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> That (at preſent) incomprehenſible fruition of the Supream and Infinite Good, which ſhall at once tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſatisfie all the powers of the Humane Soul, ſhall be vouchſaf'd to none but the Holy man.</p>
                  <p>I will not hold you in ſuſpenſe, but immediately fix on theſe <hi>two,</hi> as conſidered <hi>injoyn'd in conjunction.</hi> And whereas ſuch joint injunction of them may be conceived to have different reſpects, I ſhall not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conſider much their Connexion, as the Later may be thought the Condition or Qualification of our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of the former, thus; <hi>Follow Peace with all men and Holineſs;</hi> that is, <hi>ſo far ſeek</hi> and maintain <hi>peace with all,</hi> as <hi>Holineſs</hi> will <hi>permit</hi> (a ſenſe not to be neglected): But as the Former is a means to, or a <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſine qua non</hi> of the Later, thus; <hi>Follow peace and holineſs;</hi> that is, Follow Peace as it is a means unto Holineſs, and without which Holineſs will be very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly, if at all attained.</p>
                  <p>A little more diſtinctly yet. <hi>Peace</hi> according to the different Society, to which it relates, may be either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical. The ſtudy and purſuit of both is undoubtedly our duty, deſignedly comprehended in the Text, and conducive to Holineſs; and the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both to be reckoned as one of the greateſt Bleſſings. The one of them, Peace in the State (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God and the Conduct of our gracious Soveraign) we have had much of, and ſtill have, notwithſtanding all our Fears and Murmurings; which God cure and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give: The other, Peace in the Church, we neither have had, now a long time, no not ſince our Soveraigns bleſſed Reſtauration, nor have at preſent ſo much of,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106283:22"/> as we might, were we not on all ſides much wanting to our ſelves. And this is that, which I deſign now to preſs; and to preſs under this conſideration, as it connects with Holineſs in the preſent injunction of both, as it tends unto Holineſs, and as certainly we ſhould have much more of Holineſs, than is now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to be ſeen amongſt us, had we more of Peace and Holineſs in the Church.</p>
                  <p>My Brethren, there are many amongſt us pretend a great deal of Zeal for Holineſs; nothing is more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in their mouths, and I wiſh there lay nothing cloſer to all our hearts, than Reformation and the need of it. I cenſure none, but only ſhall at preſent endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to demonſtrate, that the moſt likely and proper way to a Publick Reformation is Eccleſiaſtical Peace and Union, and that thoſe who with all their might purſue not this, are, ſo far forth as they are negligent of it, or averſe to it, real Enemies to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and true Holineſs, whatever their pretences otherwiſe may be.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Peace in general</hi> we mean ſuch a Conjunction of mens Minds and Manners, that one man is not in any thing deſignedly troubleſome to another, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther favours every others advantages. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing applyed <hi>particularly</hi> to Cauſes and Matters Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, will amount to no leſs, than ſuch an Union of Judgment and Affections as engages Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to maintain Fellowſhip and Communion in all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Divine Worſhip, and Matters pertaining to the Glory of God. In whatever Church this is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in that proportionably is wanting Peace.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Holineſs</hi> we underſtand an Habitual Separation (or being ſeparate) from all Vice and Vitious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and a like Devotedneſs of Heart and Life
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106283:23"/> to God, according to the Rule of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Now I ſay, the firſt much conduces to the ſecond; Publick Peace in the Church to real Holineſs, and whatever practices are at preſent contrary to Peace amongſt us, are proportionably deſtructive of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>The main Evidence I ſhall give ſhall be to ſet forth the pernicious Effects of Faction; and let none ſuſpect I will in the leaſt be bitter, or invective, herein: I promiſe to ſpeak the <hi>words of meekneſs and ſoberneſs,</hi> as well as <hi>of truth.</hi> I ſhall then preſent to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the Effects of Faction or Church-diviſion: Firſt, upon the State. Secondly, upon the Church. And Thirdly, upon the ſpirits of Private men. And if all theſe are found moſt fatal to Holineſs, I ſhall hope it will be concluded there is no following Holineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Purſuing Peace.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I begin with the ſad effects of Church-diviſion upon the States and Kingdoms, within which ſuch divided Churches lye: And theſe are generally no better (worſe they cannot well be) than Civil Wars, and all the ſad Conſquences thereof; which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the moſt horrid Complications of all Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties imaginable; or, in the Language of St. <hi>James, (Chap.</hi> III. 16.) <hi>Confuſion and Every evil work.</hi> That Civil Wars are the Common Effects of Diviſions and Factions in the Church, eſpecially where ſuch Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are continued, and have had age, or time enough to ferment, as I may ſo ſpeak, the yet too freſh bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounds of theſe three Nations ſpeak more plainly than perhaps we would all be willing to hear. The point is tender, and therefore I forbear further to touch it. That Profaneneſs, Irreligion and Vices of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106283:23"/> all ſorts are the general effects of Wars, both while they rage, and too long after ſome compoſure of things, the Experience o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all Ages and People witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, as well as our own. There are thoſe perhaps that will tell us, It cannot be otherwiſe; 'Tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it ſhould not be ſo: Neceſſity compels, not only Private Perſons, but Publick Bodies, to foul Practices. When there was a General <hi>after Gods own heart, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that was in debt,</hi> (and had no mind to be juſt) <hi>Every one that was diſcontent,</hi> (the fruit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly of mens own Vices and Debaucheries, at leaſt of their Imprudence, Pride or Refractorineſs) <hi>and Every one that was in diſtreſs, gathered themſelves unto him, and he became Captain over them,</hi> 1 Sam. XXII. 2. And 'tis ſure enough, by the ſequel of the Hiſtory, there were worſe than ſuch in the greateſt Commands of his Army. <hi>The Sons of</hi> Zerviah <hi>were too hard for</hi> the good King, they were <hi>Evil-doers,</hi> privy murtherers, implacable, they ſhed the bloud of <hi>war in peace;</hi> yet durſt not he then animadvert upon them; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> III. 39. and, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> II. 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now to ſet up a Refuge for ſuch men as theſe in any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Wars do, what ſad influence muſt it have upon the Manners of the Nation?</p>
                  <p>To ſpeak ſomething cloſer to our own Country, and the late unhappy, ever to be lamented Troubles; and that in the Language of thoſe who will not be thought Railers, or <hi>Falſe Accuſers of the Brethren:</hi> The Aſſembly in their Petition to the Parliament, <hi>Jul.</hi> 19. 1644. have, amongſt others, this Prayer; <hi>That ſome ſevere courſe might be taken againſt Fornication, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and Inceſt, which</hi> (as they complain, to uſe their own terms) <hi>do</hi> (that is, then did) <hi>greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound; eſpecially of late, by reaſon of Impunity.</hi> (It
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106283:24"/> ſeems then, thoſe Odious things, the Biſhops Courts, while ſtanding, do ſome good: Fornication, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Inceſt do not ordinarily paſs with Impunity under them; which they ſoon obtain'd, when this Check was taken off.) And not only in this ſingle kind, but in moſt other Exorbitancies, was the Caſe no better. Particularly, at preſent; Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs are juſtly complained of to be reigning Sins, as well as Carnality: Now, I ſay it, and will at any time prove it, Hell it ſelf can ſcarce deviſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, or vent groſſer Prophaneneſs, Leudneſs, and Blaſphemy, than may be ſhewn juſtified, defended and cryed up, under the Notion of Perfection, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe printed Pamphlets betwixt the years 49 and 56. Nay, in the very year 1660, the greateſt part of the <hi>London Miniſters</hi> publiſhed <hi>A Seaſonable Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as they call it, complaining of the great Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs broken looſe amongſt us, wherein they ſet forth, as one dreadful Inſtance, That <hi>ſome, as they are cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>informed, are grown to that heighth of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, as to worſhip the Devil himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In a word, I could ſay much more, which would prove that then Impiety broke in like a Torrent upon us, when the Wars broke out. But I conceive all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men, of what perſwaſion ſoever, had rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs this ſad Truth, and lament it too, than hear it more largely proved. Wherefore I ſay, it follows hence, as from one general head of proof, that they are Enemies to Holineſs, who perpetuate at preſent our Church-diviſions, or (which is much the ſame) who do not their utmoſt towards a Publick Union.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let us in the next place conſider the Effect of Schiſms and Factions upon the Church, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106283:24"/> of things therein; and that Conſideration will conclude the ſame.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be conceived, at leaſt expected, I ſhould reckon up, or indeed that one man's head ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the general Inſtances or Kinds of Miſchie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s under this Head: It ſhall therefore ſuffice, that I preſent ſuch, which I judge moſt obnoxious amongſt our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then I ſay, Although Diviſions and Schiſms ſhould not, through the reſtraining hand of God, prove ſo direful to the Kingdom, yet are they in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>allibly a Plague unto the Church, and by being deſtructive un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its Diſcipline, make havock of Holineſs and publick Good manners. Diſcipline is the great expedient Chriſt has left his Church, both for the keeping out, and <hi>Purging out,</hi> all the <hi>Old Leaven of Naughtineſs and Wickedneſs,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> V. 7, 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whatſoever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bereaves the Church of this, lets in a floud of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs upon her. And is it not evident to any that has but half an eye, that Diviſions at preſent both take off the Efficacy, and hinder the Exerciſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline amongſt us? I know there are ſome who cry out, We have no ſuch thing as Diſcipline in our Church; we have only a Shadow and Skeleton of it. There is at preſent, it muſt be confeſt, ſomething of truth in the Accuſation. We have indeed too little of the Primitive and Apoſtolical Diſcipline: But we appeal to God and Men where the fault lies.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We complain our preſent Diviſions take off the Edge of our Spiritual Weapons. There are ſome, and thoſe Leading men too in their party, that deny any ſuch thing as a National Church, and much more
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106283:25"/> any Catholick Church in the ſenſe that Article of our Creed has ever been believed by all Chriſtians from the beginning. What ſhould men, acted by ſuch Principles, care for our Excommunicating them upon any Scandals they ſhould be found guilty of? They own no ſuch Church as we are, and as all Chriſtian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges have ever believed. Again, there are others, who have renounced their Baptiſm for another thing they call ſo; Others that laugh at all Baptiſm, as well as Sacraments, in general: Suppoſe any of theſe ſorts become obnoxious to Church-cenſures for their Immoralities, as too often they do; we cenſure them, and tell our Chriſtian people they ought to look upon them as <hi>Heathens and Publicans.</hi> What now ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies this? They have before caſt off the Badge of their Chriſtianity, and ſcorn it, and us for eſteeming it. They are already as Common, and as far without the Pale, as we can ſet them. I have no pleaſure to urge theſe things further.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We ſay moreover, beſides this, that the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions take off for the main, the Efficacy of ſuch Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline as we have; they have alſo hindred all along, as well the ſetting up, as the Exerciſe of that Primitive Diſcipline, which our Church long ago deſired, and intended. Thus we read in the Preface o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Office called a Commination. <hi>Brethren, in the Primitive Church there was a Godly Diſcipline, that at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Lent, ſuch perſons as were notorious Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, were put to open Pennance, and puniſht in this World, that their Souls might be ſaved in the Day of the Lord; and that others, admoniſhed by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, might be afraid to offend. In ſtead whereof, until the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſtored again, which</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106283:25"/> 
                     <hi>thing is much to be wiſhed, it is thought fit, &amp;c.</hi> And our Complaint is juſt, not only in the point there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, but in divers others. And this is evident: for, not to ſpeak of the enforced prudential conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances or omiſſions of Diſcipline in ſome particular inſtances, and at ſome times, in the Regular Church, even the very ſeparated Congregations themſelves (thoſe of them at leaſt that have any thing of Form or Government amongſt them, and are not purely Anarchical) too often feel the pinches of that Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and Evil we complain of. There are ſo many pretended Churches for the Ejected to flee to, that proceed againſt them, and you looſe them for ever. You looſe them, I ſay, not ſo much from your own Party, as from the profeſſion and practice of all that looks like Sobriety. They run into irregular Paſſions, and out of meer oppoſition to thoſe who have cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, addict themſelves to ſuch Societies, which are famous for the moſt contrary extremes to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Profeſſion. Thus many times, God knows, what was deſigned, by Chriſt in the Inſtitution, and by the Church in the Exerciſe, for a remedy, proves to ſuch diſtempered Souls a deadly Poiſon, or in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>a Stone of ſtumbling, and Rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> In ſtead of bringing the Delinquents to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for one ſin, you drive them into a courſe and ſtate of many more. This, the firſt Effect then of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions upon the Church, that they ruin Diſcipline, and have introduced all the want and impotency of it under which the Church of God at preſent labours, ſhews ſufficiently that they who are Friends to Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are none to Holineſs.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106283:26"/>
                  <p> Secondly, Another miſchievous effect of Diviſions upon the Church, is, the drawing off and diverting the Labours of the Miniſtry, from preſſing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating Holineſs, to the maintaining Opinions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, uſeleſs or troubleſome Speculations, and in a word, the croſs Intereſts of Parties. A ſad thing it is, that in a manner the very Fountains of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at leaſt the Streams, which flow thence, and which the thirſty Multitude flock to for refreſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould be invenom'd, or elſe turn'd aſide out of their due Courſe: but it is a Truth, of which every day gives us freſh and lamentable experience. I do not deny, but there are faults in this regard on both ſides, and as long as ſome men hold on their Humours, and other men are men, 'tis ſcarce poſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe. Holineſs indeed is, on all hands, confeſt the great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Mankind in this World; and ſo the great Errand and Univerſal Text of all Preachers: But how many of thoſe, who pretend the moſt for Holineſs, in their popular Sermons, at leaſt in thoſe Diſcourſes which they now-a-days publiſh (and we can judge on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the reſt we ſee not, by thoſe we have to view) how many, I ſay, of theſe, generally ſpend their pains in inveighing againſt ſome irregularities or hardſhips they apprehend in the Laws, in magnifying (perhaps beyond truth) their Parties ſufferings, in heightning or gratifying their Followers diſlikes of the Eſtabliſht Worſhip, and ſo exaſperating them againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of the Nation, as well People, Miniſtry as Magiſtracy? The late Writings of theſe men would tempt one to a ſeverer Character of their preaching, which I forbear: and only add, that then there are few on our ſide, that can perſwade themſelves they ought not to open their Mouths in their own Defence.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106283:26"/> Hence too often, when we ought to be approving our ſelves to every mans Conſcience in the ſight of God, by bringing them to the ſenſe of thoſe ſins, in which they live and wallow ſecurely, and convincing them of the indiſpenſable Neceſſity of a new life, ſhewing and teaching them the way and means thereto, and ſo to Pardon and Heaven, we ſpend good hours, or too great a part of them, in inveighing againſt Perſons or Parties, not one of which hears us; in reflecting on old Crimes and Villanies in which perhaps few men now living are concern'd; or elſe in the bandying ſome Controverſie at preſent in repute, touching which poſſibly there are more Arguments or Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on both ſides, than our ſelves, or all the men in the World can anſwer. By this means Chriſt is not preached, but Contention.</p>
                  <q>Heu! quantum potuit terrae pelagique parari, &amp;c.</q>
                  <p>How many Souls might have been won over to Peace and Holineſs, and ſo to God, by thoſe thouſands of Sermons, which having been ſpent only in peeviſh heats, and fanning the flames of Diſcord, have only raiſed the Fire, now almoſt beyond hopes of being quenched in this Generation! Now the Miniſtry of the Word being the great proviſion made by God to <hi>open mens eyes, and to turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> if this be otherwiſe imployed, if this the ſovereign means of Sanctification be perverted or diverted, what Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage muſt Holineſs needs ſuſtain?</p>
                  <p>But I muſt not lay all the fault, in this reſpect, upon the Miniſtry alone; the People have their ſhare
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106283:27"/> in the guilt. That, which the Apoſtle meant by <hi>ſound Doctrine, wholſome Words,</hi> and the like Expreſſions, namely the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">That this w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t. <hi>Paul</hi>'s No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> by what he calls <hi>ſound Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ine,</hi> or <hi>ſound Speech,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] See 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> I. 10. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp; Tit.</hi> II. 2, 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim IV. 2, 3.</note> and preſſing plain and neceſſary Chriſtian Duties, or Sacred Morals, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our people now nauſeate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and vilify thoſe, who moſt inſiſt on; having <hi>itching ears,</hi> and too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten freakiſh heads and proud hearts. Thoſe who live in abominable Uncharitableneſs, Hypocriſy, contempt of their Chriſtian Brethren (and of their Chriſtian Governours too) nay in groſs Uncleanneſs, Lewdneſs, and Riot, ſhall puff at an honeſt Practical Diſcourſe, and go away diſdainfully with an, <hi>I knew as much as this before.</hi> By this means many worthy Miniſters being diſcouraged from what they would treat of, think it but a prudential Expedient for the keeping their Congregations together, to comply with their Palates, and entertain them with ſuch Subjects, which the Preachers own inclination or natural choice would not have fixed on. But how much, Holineſs ſuffers by all this, how few are <hi>caught by this guile,</hi> and on the contrary, how many are only hardned in their former Vices, and neſtled up in their lofty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of their own Judgments, the ſober World too plainly ſee and (perhaps fruitleſly) lament. The good God, who only can, remedy this evil!</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I muſt not conceal a third Miſchief which our Diviſions bring on the Church, and that is a ſad number of inſufficient Pretenders and Intruders to the Miniſtry. Amongſt too many of the Factious, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can but boldly pretend to Gifts (and we know what pittiful reproaches of the Spirit of God ſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106283:27"/> men are uſed to call ſo) falls on exerciſing; and if after ſome practice, he gain a few ignorant Admirers, theſe ſhall be his Followers (otherwiſe perhaps ſtyled his Converts) and he may ſet up (eſpecially, if ſuch his Adherents chooſe him for their Paſtour) he may ſet up, I ſay, by the very Principles of divers of them, without any other Ordination, for a Miniſter of the Goſpel. This is up and down the Country a great Evil. But I am very far from ſaying, all the Miniſters amongſt the Diſſenters are ſuch: There are divers of them of Learning and good Conſcience, and poſſibly ſome of Legitimate Ordination. However, even theſe, in the Point in hand, we fear will find themſelves to have acted prejudicially to the Intereſt of Holineſs: not only by conniving at, and joyning with ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Intruders into this Holy Office, but alſo in not doing what they profeſs they can, and what would have ſufficed them, and by this means in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their places to be filled ſometimes with men much leſs ſerviceable to the Intereſt of Holineſs than themſelves, who unhappily occaſion many weak peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples following ſuch Intruders, and whoſe Admiſſion, as the Laws and Conſtitution of things ſtand, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church cannot now hinder. God be bleſſed there are few, that I know, or no Inſtances of this caſe hereabouts, but too many elſewhere in our <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Whoſe is the fault, God will judge.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this Point; Corruptions in Religion, whether in Doctrine or Manners, can never prevail much without corruption of the Holy Order. <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoam</hi> could not effect the Alienation of the people from the Temple and true Worſhip of God, meerly by his ſetting up his Golden Calves at <hi>Bethel,</hi> till he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106283:28"/> had made of the <hi>Vileſt</hi> ſort of people <hi>Prieſts, which were not of the ſons of</hi> Levi, perſons no wiſe qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their Office of Prieſthood by Education or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> XII. 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> XIII. 33. Let thoſe, who have been guilty of doing, occaſioning, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to, the like evil, look to it, and lay it home to their hearts and Conſciences. The generality of ſuch inſufficients is a conſequent of our Diviſions, and hereby Holineſs has ſuffered, and will ſuffer till ſuch practice can be remedied; which will never be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted till Union and Regularity may take place and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate. Thus as to the Effects of Diviſions upon the Church, deſtructive to Holineſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third Head propoſed now only remains, <hi>viz.</hi> the Conſideration of the Effects of Faction pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to Holineſs on the ſpirits of private Chriſtians; and theſe, I ſay, it ſtrangely vitiates.</p>
                  <p>I have already ſtated what I conceive genuinly meant by Holineſs: and according to the Account given in it ſignifies, in a word, an Habitual Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Chriſtian Graces and Virtues. Now let us look through the whole three Families or Tribes of Chriſtian Duties, towards <hi>God, Men, and Our ſelves,</hi> and ſee how miſerably peoples practice is corrupted under each Head by our Diviſions.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. I begin with Godlineſs: but muſt admoniſh here, as before, none may expect I ſhould touch on all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; Time would fail: Some enumeration of Points more obnoxious may ſuffice.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The greateſt corruption or adulteration of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Godlineſs in the world is, the miſplacing it: I mean, mens taking up and holding to ſomewhat in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106283:28"/> ſtead of it, which perhaps in their, and ſome others judgment, has ſome appearance and likeneſs of it, or remote pretence to it, but is very far from being it. And if men ſhall not only do this themſelves, but teach others ſo to do, and vent this falſe Godlineſs, they are more dreadfully guilty of corrupting Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſtroying Holineſs: according as he who ſhould diſperſe as much falſe Money as he could, were more a Criminal in adulterating the Kings Coin, and abuſing the Nation, than he who fondly ſhould pleaſe himſelf with the luſtre of ſome few baſe pieces in his own private Cabinet. Now I complain that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of the Church have brought men to place Godlineſs in points moſt diſtant from its nature, nay, ſome moſt contrary to it: and not only to practice ſo themſelves, but to teach accordingly. I ſhall aſſign only for the preſent a double inſtance.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Some men mainly place Godlineſs in being of ſuch or ſuch a Church; that is, in other terms, in being of this or that Sect or Party. And the perſons guilty herein are not meerly ſome weaker and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary people (which yet ſome account the greateſt part of Mankind) but divers of a far different Grain; at leaſt as their Diſcourſe and Converſation in other things beſpeaks them. How plauſibly, amongſt men of tolerable judgment, does the following Plea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed? Out of the True Church there is no Salvation. And the True Church can be but one (For there is <hi>One Body as one Spirit, Epheſ.</hi> IV. 4. And we <hi>Believe One Catholick and Apoſtolick Church,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Creed) It therefore concerns a man in the firſt place, in the Choice and Entrance upon his Religion, to look hereto, that he joyn himſelf to the true
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106283:29"/> Church. How few ſee the Snare which is here laid, or are wary enough to extricate their perplexed minds by diſtinguiſhing, that though the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church be but <hi>One,</hi> yet <hi>Particular</hi> Churches may be, and muſt be <hi>Many;</hi> and of thoſe many, God forbid but we ſhould think ſeveral to be true ones, that is, true Members of the one Catholick Church? And 'tis moſt likely, ſhe's the worſt, which ingroſſes to her ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (at leaſt would ingroſs) the Title of <hi>The True and Catholick.</hi> In the mean while, what a ſtir has this Queſtion made in Divided Chriſtendom, <hi>Which is the true Church?</hi> What are the <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters</hi> of it? How many private Conferences, publick Sermons, voluminous Treatiſes taken up on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject? And when men have, from theſe Signs or Characters agreeing to ſuch or ſuch a Church, in ſome tolerable meaſure ſatisfied themſelves to their own apprehenſion, and concluded ſuch or ſuch A True Church, to which therefore they forthwith addict themſelves, is not this generally the next concluſion, that the ſame is The True Church; and preſently this the final Reſult, that Themſelves and all in the <hi>Ark</hi> are ſafe by being in it? Who ſees not that this wile, deſtructive flattery and deluſion, derives its Original from our Diviſions? Every divided Party look upon themſelves as the Godlier (and conſequently <hi>quo id hoc,</hi> the Holier) by how much the purer Worſhip they conceive their Church to have: and that they take for certain, The <hi>truer</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> the Purer its Worſhip, its Sacraments, its Communion; and in fine, the ſurer its Members. So that with the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude this paſſeth current, Get into the true Church, and as to Religion you are ſafe: for you are ſure of True Sacraments, a ſaving Miniſtry, the beſt ſort of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106283:29"/> Worſhip, and what not? Ah, my Brethren! Theſe however in themſelves golden Pipes, and ſacred Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances of Grace, to thoſe who uſe them aright, are yet, in themſelves, and as the World goes, <hi>Faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; Parabiles ritus,</hi> a Godlineſs eaſie to be had, and which may prove as deſtructive as eaſie to be come by, when the outward injoyment hereof is the great matter of our Acquieſcence.</p>
                  <p>But to examine this Cheat a little more narrowly as well for the more effectual delivery of men from it, as the clearing the Point in hand, That Diviſions have brought men to place Godlineſs in matters moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to its nature.</p>
                  <p>Admit I place true Religion, and ſo Godlineſs (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much) in being of this or that Church; I ſay, the Church I am of is either a True one or a Falſe one; one that holds to, or one that has broken off from Catholick Unity. If the later, I am then in a Schiſm by being of it. And then by placing Godlineſs in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Church, what do I do but place it in Schiſm? An hopeful ſort of Godlineſs indeed! And if the former, if the Church, in adhereing whereto I reckon my ſelf Godly, be a true one, that is, a ſincere Member of the true Catholick Church, I am never a whit the godlier by my miſtake in over-valuing the Communion of the Church. For 'tis great odds, as the ſtream of mens ſpirits runs, but that my Zeal for ſuch dearly beloved Church, tranſport me into ſuch admiration of it, that, either I ſhall confine Salvation to it, and inſiſt ſo far on the neceſſity of Communion with it, as to forget Catholick Charity; by which means again I am fallen into Schiſm, though of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106283:30"/> ſort from that before mentioned (and ſtill pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Godlineſs in being of this Church thus ſtrictly, I place Godlineſs in Schiſm): Or elſe reſt in the meer injoyment of thoſe advantages and preeminencies I apprehend by it, running a round of external Duties and Obſervances, but little or not at all concerning my ſelf, as to a real changed heart and renewed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and then, the Godlineſs, with which I pleaſe my ſelf, lies only in ſome Formalities and Church Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which come naturally under what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſtyles <hi>a Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and which he ſays a man may have, and <hi>deny its Power;</hi> that is, be void of <hi>Holineſs, without which no man can ſee the Lord.</hi> And is not this as pernicious a miſtake? Alas, alas my Brethren! 'Tis not the Communion of Saints can ſave men, though it be both our Duty and Intereſt to maintain it. A man may be damned in the pureſt Church on Earth for a Carnal worldly heart, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly unholy life, however our Diviſions may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude us into contrary Fanſies.</p>
                  <p>This kind of men we have ſpoken of are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Zealots</hi> (of one ſide or t'other) But there are ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort which are <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> indifferent generally to all Religions and Churches in particular. Some Religion perhaps they think 'tis fit there ſhould be, for the better managing the people: and if in their judgment they do proceed to any Specialties, poſſibly they will tell you, 'tis expedient there ſhould be ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religions, that every man may find one, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion whereof will ſuit his Humour (A policy, not unlike unto which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has now a long time uſed in inventing and maintaining ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders) Now as they before-mentioned place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:106283:30"/> Religion (and ſo Godlineſs, or our Duty to God) in being of what they apprehend to be Gods true Church, ſo theſe</p>
                  <p>Secondly, place it in ſeeming to be of ſuch or ſuch a Church or Party; for in reality, and as far as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Religion, they neither believe nor own any ſuch thing, nor conſequently any Church at all. The other perhaps addicted themſelves to Factions and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties out of Conſcience (though haply erroneous) and in the ſincerity of their hearts: theſe out of humour or intereſt, ſeem to do ſo for the preſent, and when either humour or intereſt vary, then farewel ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed Party or Religion. And now let us put the Queſtion in plain Engliſh (and as plainly anſwer it) What do theſe men place Godlineſs in? Verily in an Atheiſtical humourſome Hypocriſy. And is it not true that our Diviſions foſter and confirm theſe Wretches Atheiſtical vein? They ſeem to themſelves rationally defenſible in disbelieving all Religion, and our ſeveral Churches Teſtimonies thereof, becauſe the Witneſſes are not agreed amongſt themſelves.</p>
                  <p>In a word, and to conclude this particular of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing Godlineſs, or deceiving our ſelves as to its whole nature. It is ſure, Godlineſs primarily conſiſts in a ſerious Belief of the Being and Nature of God, and in an intire Reſignation to him; whence moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and ſweetly ſlow all its inward and outward acts. But we have above made it evident, Diviſions have brought Chriſtendom to that paſs, that ſome men place Godlineſs in ſuch Practices which reſolve into Schiſm, others in Formalities and Providential Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, others in Atheiſtical and Humour ſome Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie (and not a few are there of each of theſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106283:31"/> ſorts): Now what can be more contrary to real God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs than all theſe? By what we have ſaid therefore of the miſplacing of Godlineſs, it appears Diviſions ſo vitiate the ſpirits of private men, as to deſtroy real Godlineſs, that is, (the firſt part of Holineſs) in them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though the Dammage Godlineſs muſt ſuſtain in miſplacing wholly its nature, is the greateſt we can imagine, yet certainly it ſuffers not a little by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Heterogeneous additions, and on the other hand by detraction of ſome of its Integral Parts, or Offices. And is it not evident, that ſince the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church has been thus rent in pieces by Diviſions, each Party, as if in their own defence, and in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their proceedings, has made it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſtand by themſelves, and purſuant hereto moſt have been running further and further from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the ſtrangeſt Extreams? Which diſtance muſt be confeſt moſt chiefly viſible in Articles of Faith and Offices of Divine Worſhip. Both theſe, on ſome hands, have been wiſely multiplyed, on others as prodigiouſly, and not without the moſt dreadful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, diminiſhed and retrenched. From the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of Articles of Faith amongſt the Papiſts, Believing, with the Multitude, is become only a blind Obedience and Reſolution of ſubmiſſion to the Church. From the like multiplication of Divine Ordinances, the Publick Worſhip with them is moſtly Pageantry and Ceremony, and Private Devotion little elſe but ſome Lip-labour, Bodily Exerciſe, or ſmall Money-matter. Amongſt thoſe who call themſelves Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, there are a People who have run into contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heights, and after denying ſome Articles of Faith,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106283:31"/> and laying aſide others as uſeleſs, have rejected all poſitive worſhip of God, all Prayers, Sacraments, yea even the Miniſtry of the Word, as belonging only to a lower State and Oeconomy than that they are in. I do not ſay but theſe mens Opinions fairly enough derive from ſome old Romiſh Fanaticiſm: however, the men themſelves at preſent pretend the greateſt contrariety to <hi>Rome.</hi> Far be it from me totally to excuſe all middle and interjacent Parties: but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by all theſe Diviſions (in Faith and Worſhip) Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs ſuffers much amongſt us, in things appertaining to God.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. So does it in things appertaining to Men. Though all the Individuals of each Party were Righteous, and ought no Debt of <hi>ſtrict Juſtice</hi> to one another (ſo that this part of our Duty to men were no whit at all infringed by our Diviſions, the contrary to which is yet moſt notoriouſly apparent) notwithſtanding there is one Debt, which in St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s language, we muſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) always be paying, yet always owing; namely, Charity and Loving one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <hi>This Debt alone,</hi> of all others, ſays he, <hi>knows no end.</hi> But how much this part of Holineſs ſuffers by our Factions, is unconceivable, as well as inexpreſſible. How few of any Party maintain ſo much as Charitable hopes of one another, much leſs ſuch Judgment as they would have exerciſed towards themſelves? And hence in every common affair of Life, what abominable Male-conſtruction of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Actions, yea even of Intentions and Thoughts? As if men, rather than not be Uncharitable to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, were reſolved violently to invade the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the Almighty, and to become <hi>Judges of</hi>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106283:32"/> 
                     <hi>Hearts.</hi> Nay, happy were it with Humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, if the Uncharitableneſs of Factions ſtuck here; What Detraction, Contempt, Scorn and Reproaches do the Parties mutually proceed to? What Ill-will, Envy, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (rejoycing in one anothers Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, as well as Sins and Miſcarriages) every where abounds? Yet further, What contrivances of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs upon one another? What unmerciful Intrigues, Plots and Labours to expoſe one another? No ill Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I had almoſt ſaid no Diabolical Arts of Trapan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Circumventing, falſe Accuſing ſpared. Good God! what more contrary to Holineſs? It too plainly appears hence, our Diviſions have trampled upon Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as well as Charity.</p>
                  <p>But there is one particular ſort of Injuſtice (the genuin, though curſed Off-ſpring of Church-Faction) which I muſt not ſilently paſs over, and that eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is againſt Governours; (though herein the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge undoubtedly will alſo one day Pronounce, <hi>They have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me that I ſhould not reign over them.)</hi> How little do the Commands of Authority ſignifie with many men? Is it not too generally with ſome grown a Maxim? That which was in it ſelf indifferent, and lawful to be done before it was Commanded by Law, being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, may not be ſubmitted to; ſuch Command being an Invaſion of the Liberty Chriſt has left us. A Principle deſtructive to all Peace and Government, even to the very Root of both; and indeed highly <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian;</hi> as being truly but an old ſtrain of ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Judaiſm (which proved too fatal both to that peoples ſouls and ſtate) To admit no <hi>Chriſt</hi> but what ſhould ſet them above <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But I muſt not expa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106283:32"/> on this, leſt I ſeem to ſome to forget a promiſe I made in the beginning.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. It remains now only to ſet forth the Effects of Diviſion upon Holineſs as that comprehends the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to a mans ſelf. And of this nature, as well on one ſide as the other, are the High conceits of our ſelves, of our own Judgments, Gifts, Graces, and general Attainments; The ſtrange Confidence we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain of that ſingular favour God has for us and our Party; whence commonly proceed marvellous <hi>Capric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio's,</hi> Self-flatteries, boaſting of and ſetting up our ſelves (at leaſt reſentments that it is fit others ſhould ſet us) as the Patterns and Meaſures of Holineſs or Reformation. This has ever been the temper of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſince there were Parties, and ſince Sects entred into the Church. When the old Jewiſh Church was in a manner only Bipartite, or divided but into two great Sects of Phariſees and Sadduces, how did the one value themſelves above the other? The Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Character of them anſwered exactly, <hi>Iſai.</hi> LXV. 5. In their hearts, at leaſt, they ſaid to thoſe who were not of themſelves, <hi>Stand by thy ſelf, come not near to me, for I am holyer than thou.</hi> And however this is ordinarily charged as the fault of one ſort of men amongſt us, I fear there is no Party at all but has too many Members of ſuch arrogant vein.</p>
                  <p>I do not ſay the Evils taxed under this Head are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſins againſt a Man's ſelf; They are alſo certainly contrary to Charity, whoſe Property it is, <hi>not to vaunt it ſelf, not to be puffed up, not to behave it ſelf unſeemly</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XIII. 4, 5.) and ſo againſt our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; They are contrary to Humility, and that holy awe and reverence we owe to God, and ſo alſo ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106283:33"/> him: But ſtill, Practices thus complicately ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful muſt needs be the more oppoſite to Holineſs; and proportionably, ſuch muſt needs be, whatſoever intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces them into the Chriſtian World, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church Diviſions.</p>
                  <p>In ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m then, to conclude our proof. It is apparent, let us pretend what we will for Holineſs and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet if we either privately foment and lengthen out the Diviſions of the Church, or labour not all in us lies to compoſe and reconcile them, we keep alive thoſe Coals whence we can expect no other than the diſmal flames of a Civil War (a ſtate of things, which above all others depraves National manners, inſomuch that the uſual Tenour of Sobriety is not commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in an Age or two after) We ruin the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church, the great Curb and Cure of Vice amongſt Chriſtian men, provided by Chriſt; We for the main pervert or divert the ordinary means of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, the Miniſtry of the Word; We ſet open a door for blind Leaders of the blind; We, beſides, otherwiſe contribute much to the vitiating the private ſpirits of men, by introducing (by our ſelves or others) unnatural kinds, offices, and inſtances of Godlineſs, by the like retrenching genuine Godlineſs, by perpetua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſarily uncharitableneſs, unmercifulneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and eſpecially Diſobedience to Government, and finally, by cheriſhing the Seeds of Spiritual Pride, Oſtentation, Preſumption, and whatever is contrary to that Meekneſs, Sweetneſs and Comlineſs of Mind which conſtitutes the Chriſtian temper: By all which means, and poſſibly many other unſeen ones, we in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al truth ſubvert and deſtroy, what we profeſs moſt Zealous Endeavours for, namely Holineſs and a through Reformation.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:106283:33"/>
                  <p> Give me leave now, in a word, to reſume the Text, and purſue it, as an Exhortation, in the ſenſe, and with the Deſign I have propounded; <hi>Follow Peace with all men, and Holineſs.</hi> Let us ſtudy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Union of the Church, the accord and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſerious Chriſtians, as the moſt effectual mean of a compleat Reformation. Were the good men of the ſeveral Perſwaſions, or the Generality of them, of one piece, of one Communion, Profaneneſs, Vice and Looſeneſs would not find amongſt us where to take Refuge. Men would be compell'd to amend in their own defence, and for meer ſhelter in the Church, the reproach of an Outlier would be ſo into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable.</p>
                  <p>I muſt profeſs with all ſincerity, I cannot, in my poor inſight into the ſtate of our Diſſentions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of any poſſibility of an Union of all honeſt mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men of the different Perſwaſions amongſt us, that call themſelves Proteſtants, but by the coming in of ſuch ſeveral Diſſenters into the Eſtabliſht Church. The Approaches perhaps muſt be Gradual; and the Methods of effecting them I will confeſs beyond my Comprehenſion: Only I will adventure to ſay, I am apt to think <hi>the ſweeter the better.</hi> Yet though I dare not pretend to ſhew how all may be done, I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to apprehend the thing, as ſome do, not ſeaſible. Are we not on all hands ſenſible that the things, which keep us aſunder, are far from being of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as are the Reformation of the ſcandalous Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the Edification of the Pious? Why then may we not hope, but by ſuch mutual advances one towards another, which the aforeſaid ſenſe of things is apt to beget, we may in ſome time meet? And why
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106283:34"/> ſhould we hope it, and not honeſtly with all our might and skill endeavour it? We ſee the abominable Vanity and Self-flattery in pretending to a Zeal for Holineſs, when we are Lukewarm to Peace, and adherents to Faction. Let us be ready to ſacrifice ſomewhat to peace, if it be only to approve our ſelves not to be Hypocrites in our Pretences to Holineſs or Saintſhip. I ſpeak this to men of all Parties, and particularly to all conſiderable of our own Church. I take it to be a greater fault in Conformiſts to be ſtiff and averſe to Union than in any other ſort, inaſmuch as the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples we profeſs are more truly Catholick and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than thoſe of any others I know. Let all therefore be prevailed with, to unite their Endeavours and whatſoever they have of intereſt, to promote ſo great a bleſſing. Have we any power over our own ſpirits, any influence upon others, any intereſt at the Throne of Grace, let all be imployed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let us never ceaſe by Conſideration and Prayers, night and day, enforcing upon our ſelves all the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to, and Counſels of Peace and Union, which we can contrive or collect; let us not ceaſe, I ſay, to enforce them, till we feel our hearts really brought under the power of them, and are able to approve our Conſciences to God, that he, who knows all in us, knows we are from the bottom of our hearts ſtudious of Peace, and will do all we can in our places to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs it: Eſpecially, that we will in all meet things deny our ſelves, and recede from whatever on our parts may be ſpared, which really hinders it. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, my Brethren, Peace could not be far off, could all particular men, eſpecially thoſe of note and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er on all ſides, go before God, and appeal to him, as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106283:34"/> the Searcher of all hearts, that they are ſincerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, to the utmoſt of their might, to purſue Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bring their own and their Brethrens ſpirits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. We may many of us pretend to this, but it is to be feared, ſuch pretence is but a Copy of our Countenance: It has been ingenuouſly confeſt, even by ſome Conſciencious men who diſſent, that if our Hearts were not further from Peace than our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or our Pens, it would ſoon be effected. Let us put it home to our ſelves, Why ſhould it be ſo? Nay how can it be ſo, without abominable Hypocriſie? Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt bring our hearts to the temper perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or farewel our Saintſhip: We are but vile Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to what we are not, and in truth Self-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and falſe to God and the World.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let us imploy all the Intereſt we hold in others, whether in any Grandees and powerful Patrons that we have, or in Familiars and Friends, Followers and Diſciples, with any and all, with whom we can hope our entreaties, power, or any kind of importunity can prevail, let us be dealing effectually, that they would in their places joyn their Endeavours, and work together to the ſweetning and uniting the minds of good men. Let us not reſt, till we have made them (what we are ſuppoſed to have made our ſelves) reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, cordial, and zealous in this bleſſed Deſign.</p>
                  <p>But more eſpecially, if any of us, impartially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting before God upon our paſt Life and Actions, find we have influenced any towards the preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, Let us remember their Schiſm is ours, their Uncharitableneſs ours, all they do to defend or diſperſe their dividing Principles is ſtill an Accumulation of our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106283:35"/> Guilt. Let therefore no poor ſhamefacedneſs, or baſe tenderneſs of our own Repute and Eſteem, with-hold us one day from acknowledging our Errour, and from recalling and regaining ſuch into the Unity of the Church, whom unhappily (though poſſibly with a good meaning) we drew from thence. And let us do this inſtantly, by the firſt opportunity we can lay hold on; <hi>to day, while it is called to day.</hi> God knows, how little time there may be left us for ſuch work: And it would be, we will eaſily believe, as fruitleſs an attempt, as dreadful inhancement of our Woe, ſhould we come one day to be at <hi>Our Father</hi> Abraham, <hi>ſend</hi> Lazarus <hi>unto my Brethren, that they come not into this place of Torment,</hi> the reward as well as original of Schiſm and Contention.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, That no ſtone may be left unturn'd in ſo heavenly an Engagement, let us all try our Intereſts with the <hi>God of Peace,</hi> and ply his Mercy-ſeat with our Supplications and Tears night and day, that he would pity his Church here, rending and tearing out her own Vitals with her own hands. Let us pray that if there be in our hearts any latent, and to us unſeen Seeds of Diſcord, God would open our eyes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to winnow them out of our ſelves and the World; that he will on all hands remove Errour, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy and ſelf-will; and that he will pardon them too, to the end our paſt guilt may not blaſt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and ſucceſs of our Repentance. Let us at leaſt thus far obey the Injunction in the Text of <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Peace,</hi> as with pure and fervent hearts to <hi>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> if we have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means of effecting it. This is an Endeavour out of none of our Orb or Power. And would the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106283:35"/> World (at home I mean) take up this ſpirit, and conſpire in this practice, God would certainly ſoon accompliſh, what man looks upon as impoſſible, The Union of Proteſtants: <hi>For with him nothing is impoſſible.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the God who <hi>maketh men to be of one mind in an houſe,</hi> ſend down the Spirit of Peace and Union into his Church, which is the Houſe of him the Living and True God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To whom, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>The End.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:106283:36"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:106283:36"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>HAving iuſt now read over theſe Two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons which I have tranſcribed ſince I preached, I am not a little thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the belief of an Obſervation I have long ago made (or taken up I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay whether) That a man may with leſs danger of expoſing himſelf preach many Sermons than print one: Thoſe Defects and Crudities, which the ſpeed and (with ſome more happy perſons) the Grace of Pronunciation covers, are eaſily perceived by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture attention of the Peruſer. That this will be the Fate of divers Paſſages in theſe foregoing Diſcourſes, I am ſenſible enough, and perhaps ſee the Particulars: But the Deſign I purſue in them is ſo neceſſary to be promoted by more Advocates than it has in good earneſt, that I could not prevail with my ſelf, through any fear of Cenſures, to ſuppreſs my poor, however cordial, endeavours therein. Nor did I think it fit in the Copy for the Preſs, to make any ſuch Supplies or Changes, as in themſelves I might think but requiſite, leſt it ſhould be objected by any, I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not what I print. Wherefore I am content that all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106283:37"/> paſs in the form it is. I will only admoniſh, that the ſame Arguments, which I have uſed in the Second Sermon to prove our preſent Diviſions deſtructive to Holineſs, will alſo prove that other part (which I have too lightly touch't) That the Union we perſwade, would certainly produce more Holineſs or Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick Manners, than any other Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent we can eaſily imagine: Only I had not time to apply them diſtinctly to both parts; and to thoſe, who will read this, 'tis amply enough to have ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus much.</p>
            <p>There may poſſibly occur divers Paſſages in both Sermons, which ſame may ſay want Truth; nay, the Contradictions to which I have read in print not many days ago: I can only ſay, I ſpoke them not with a deſign of contradiction; and I both did, and ſtill do judge them real Truths. For inſtance, <hi>(Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 22.) I ſay, <hi>We</hi> [Conformiſts] <hi>doubt not but in this our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience we pleaſe God, and are not unſerviceable unto men.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> on the contrary, in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the Non-conformiſts Miniſtry (which Book I ſhall much cite in what follows) applies to us, more than once, as I remember, that paſſage of the Apoſtle touching the unbelieving Jews, (1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> II. 15.) <hi>That we pleaſe not God, and are contrary to all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag 235. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>men.</hi> I believe in my Conſcience he is miſtaken, and that what I ſaid is true. Nay further I will tell him, and all the World, and God is my Witneſs herein, I at firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed with a deſign to ſerve God; and I bleſs my God, I do both ſerve him, with a pure Conſcience, in the way of Conformity, and have the comfort and joy thereof in my own breſt daily; nor do I trouble my ſelf, or can I help it, if prejudicate men are of another mind.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106283:37"/> Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 30. of the ſame Sermon, I ſaid, <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians and Independents could not agree among themſelves;</hi> no not, <hi>when they had an Aſſembly packt moſtly of themſelves.</hi> Yet many have lately magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their Agreement, and ſome have told us, that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> was <hi>almost all of Epiſcopal conformable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxt.</hi> Apol. N. C. p. 90, 204. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>men.</hi> Were it worth the labour, I could prove the truth of what I ſaid; nay, I could prove much more. Firſt, as to their great concord, I ſay they were ſo far from agreeing then, that they are not agreed yet: For whereas ſome could come in to our Church, upon ſuch terms as they are pleaſed to inſinuate under the name of a <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> (namely the Moderate Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians) They of the Congregational way <hi>cannot, according to their Judgments, allow of our Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bill for Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation. pag. penult.</note> 
               <hi>Churches, nor a Book of Liturgy; but do chooſe to worſhip God in the way of their Gathered or Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Congregations,</hi> and ſo need an <hi>Indulgence.</hi> Then as to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s demand, Were not almoſt all the <hi>Weſtminſter-Aſſembly</hi> Epiſcopal Conformable men when they came thither? I could ſay, No, not in <hi>their hearts,</hi> as appear'd by <hi>their fruits:</hi> (Thoſe four of five that were, had no comfort to be amongſt them.) Hear part of the Preamble of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, by which this conformable Aſſembly was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Whereas it has been declared and reſolved by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jun. 12. 1643. Scob. Coll p. 42.</note> 
               <hi>the Lords and Commons aſsembled in Parliament, that the preſent Church Government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Officers, depending upon the Hierarchy, is juſtly offenſive and burthenſome to the Kingdom, a great impediment to Reformation and growth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and very prejudicial to the State and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:106283:38"/> 
               <hi>of this Kingdom; and that therefore they are reſolved that the ſame ſhall be taken away; and that ſuch a Government ſhall be ſettled in the Church, as may be agreeable to God's Holy Word,</hi> [Epiſcopacy then in theſe mens judgments was not] <hi>and most apt to procure and preſerve the peace of the Church at home, and nearer agreement with the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What Epiſcopal men would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered this call, or theſe ends, any otherwiſe than by proteſting againſt them? Did theſe things tend to peace? I could and would give a further anſwer. I could tell him too, who it is, that through habitual prejudice, ſelf-flattery, and unhappy errour, is a <hi>falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of Hiſtory,</hi> and that <hi>in the very memory of them,</hi> in whoſe times theſe things were acted; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in fixing the <hi>war</hi> upon an <hi>Eraſtian party in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> (when all the World knows, a People ever known to be of more bloody Principles, and whom I will not name, for peace-ſake, both ſcattered and blew the Coals, whence aroſe thoſe Combuſtions:) but that, I ſay, I conceive, my Anſwer would no more conduce to peace, than his reminding the Nation of thoſe things, which at other times he would have forgotten: I would have ſet forth all this. In ſhort, he and all his Abettors muſt know, the Catalogues of that <hi>Parliament,</hi> of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> are in our hands; the Copies of their <hi>Speeches,</hi> the Journals of their <hi>Votes, Tranſactions, &amp;c.</hi> are all to be produced: and, to ſay nothing of the <hi>Covenanters,</hi> the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (both of Miniſtry and Laiety) named in the <hi>Form of Church Government</hi> (which the Aſſembly had been ſo long a hammering) <hi>to be uſed in the Church of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, all theſe mens names, qualities, principles, and procedure, are notorious in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106283:38"/> print. Such publick, and (as I may juſtly call them) Authentick Records, as theſe, muſt and will be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, when private perſons, whoſe intereſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs it is to tax others with their own faults, will ſcarce find belief. But I forget my ſelf: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I followed another; and ſad it is, when one who pretends for peace, in his very pleas for it leads us out of the way to it. I have done with this kind of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, when I have beſought my Reader not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count any thing ſaid in my Sermons falſe, becauſe ſome have been pleaſed to contradict and <hi>hector</hi> the Truth.</p>
            <p>I did not at firſt intend even thus much of Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for I propoſed not to my ſelf in this <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> to Apologize for my <hi>Sermons,</hi> nor to anſwer other mens Imputations on us and our Church; but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſuch Particulars in order to my <hi>Pacificatory deſign,</hi> as were leſs fit for a Sermon, and ſo ſtill to drive the ſame Nail further home. To this purpoſe therefore I ſhall take the boldneſs (which the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my intentions I hope may obtain pardon for) to obſerve to the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> where in ſome of their Writings, which I have ſeen, while they plead for peace, they openly blaſt it; and wherein otherwiſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their <hi>pleas,</hi> their own <hi>practices</hi> are evidently wanting to the deſign of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> And herein I deſire to be hear'd only with ſo much candour and calmneſs as I ſhall uſe.</p>
            <p>He that appears in the Front of the Diſſenters, for <hi>Peace,</hi> is Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> He ſays in his <hi>Epiſtle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory</hi> of his <hi>Apology for the Nonconformiſts Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry,</hi> he <hi>has been begging in vain theſe Twenty years for Peace and Concord, of the Order of the Biſhops;</hi> nay <hi>(pag.</hi> 1.) he <hi>has tried in vain too, what ſilence</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:106283:39"/> 
               <hi>in this kind would do:</hi> yet after all, <hi>before the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his gaſping hopes, he reſolved once more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt diſpair, and make another effort.</hi> It is really to be lamented that both his and other good mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to this purpoſe, have been no more ſucceſsful: but being we all, who either ſpeak or write on this Subject, ought not to be thought any other than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and in good earneſt, let us be content to conſider each of us in what Particular our endeavours are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient or peccant. The diſcovery of this may haply help us a little into <hi>the way of Peace.</hi> And let not Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> be diſpleaſed with me, if, being to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſome <hi>writings</hi> of his of this kind, I firſt, with intire good will, both to him and mankind, deliver freely my thoughts of <hi>him;</hi> I will aſſure him I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect one day to anſwer for all I ſay: and now let his and all mens Charity judge of my Veracity.</p>
            <p>I really believe him at the bottom a very good man, truly loving and fearing God, and paſſionately zealous for the Converſion, Edification, and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Souls: When ever he treats of the things that belong to another life, the ſenſe and concernment he has for them appears in his very language; <hi>Videtur ipſius oratio non in labiis naſci, ſed in pectore:</hi> Thoſe who are not ſtrangers to Holy Affections, muſt needs feel a kind of ſympathy, which, beyond all ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and above all other Arguments, will demonſtrate thus much to them: I will alſo add, that 'tis moſt ſure he is exceſſively ſtudious and laborious, and as great an Inſtance as many Ages will ſhew, what Induſtry and Parts may do, without the Aids of Regular and Academical Education: But I do not look upon him, any more than other mortal men, to be without his Infirmities; and of what nature his chiefly may be, a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106283:39"/> man may not improbably conjecture, from the mortified ſtate of his Body, and that Opinion, which he is ſaid to have aſſerted, that <hi>A man might live</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Morleys</hi> Letter, p. 13.</note> 
               <hi>without any Actual Sin:</hi> Sure it is, it has been his great unhappineſs, to have been long in the top of a Faction of his own making; which Faction, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heterogeneous (neither Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, <note place="margin">Apolog. p. 73.</note> Independent or Eraſtian, as himſelf ſeems to confeſs, but a Compoſition or Temper, I will not ſay, an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> of all) and beſides very Numerous, he has paſt too much without brotherly reproof; and perhaps is not now ſo capable of it: Moſt have cenſured him, too many perhaps expos'd him; others on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry admired and extoll'd him; few or none have dealt, together faithfully and candidly, with him or with his Writings: I have done ſo hitherto, and ſhall all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to my poor ability.</p>
            <p>But leſt any ſhould ſuſpect me, being a Perſon of different perſwaſion and intereſt from him (as may be conceived) to ſpeak out of prejudice, I will take the liberty, as he does ſome times, in his forementioned <hi>Apology,</hi> to tell him a ſtory or two: I had ſeen him but twice, once <hi>en paſsant,</hi> and another time in the Pulpit (nor did I ever ſee him ſince) when being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> School to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I waited on a good man, who had ſhewn me diverſe never to be forgotten kindneſſes, and eſpecially by whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry I had made ſome proficiency in Godlineſs, (though I muſt ſay, the grounds of it I had had elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) I waited, I ſay, on ſuch a reverend Perſon, to pay my thanks and take my leave; and at my parting, amongſt other very good <hi>advices,</hi> he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd me not to leave the Univerſity too ſoon, as the manner of thoſe, who went ripe thither, was: <hi>For</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:106283:40"/> 
               <hi>they,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that do ſo, are never able</hi> to wade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that depth of Learning, <hi>which they might eaſily have done; and beſides that, for want of having gone through the whole Circle of Arts and Sciences regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, they too often become opinionative, furious, unable to bear liberal conference or oppoſition, though it be by way only of Diſpute or Brotherly Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: As,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>we have now experience in a very godly, but ſtrangely fierce man, Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>by name, who though he will ſpeak very well, yet is not able to endure being gainſaid in any thing.</hi> (If the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be alive, and read this, I am ſure he will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge many of his own Expreſſions; and ſay, if I have erred from them, it is rather <hi>in partem faventiorem.)</hi> He added, <hi>There is a great deal of truth in that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of old</hi> Lilies <hi>uſing;</hi>
            </p>
            <l>Adde quòd, Ingenuas didiciſſe fideliter artes,</l>
            <l>Emollit mores nec ſinit eſſe feros:</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Had Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>been bred at Diſputations, or in the Schools, he would manage himſelf with more tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> This Gentleman, if alive, I am ſure is a <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt.</hi> This was all I had ever heard of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> till from <hi>Cambridge</hi> making ſome Excurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into my own Country, I there found him cried up as <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> of thoſe parts; and his Books flying there much abroad, I met with his <hi>Gildas Salvianus,</hi> which I read with great concernment, again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; in ſhort, ſuch was the impreſſion it made on me, that I ever after believed, whatever infirmities Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> might have, he was certainly a man moſt faithful in his Miniſtry. Coming down again in the Year 1658. as I remember, I met with his <hi>Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> and read a great part of it, much ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereat, and with great concernment pitying him,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106283:40"/> as to my apprehenſion, out of his Element; yet I can truly ſay, loving and reverencing him for that I had before read in him. From that time till 1663. I remember my ſelf to have heard or read little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of him: And then I was told by a Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, that at the <hi>Conference</hi> of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> being demanded what would ſatisfie him? ſhould reply, <hi>All or Nothing;</hi> or words to that effect. Up, on this, I reflected on what that Grave <hi>Divine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, told me, when I went to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity:</hi> And ſince that time I have only occaſionally, and as by accident they have faln into my hands, read any thing of his Works, till now this piece of his, which I am about to cenſure, came in my way: And from hence the World may eſtimate, how far I am acquainted with, or prejudiced againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly Peace is ſo amiable thing, that it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend any man to me who comes with offers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it; much more Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whom I have ſo long looked upon as a Conſcientious man: It is not eaſie to aſſign greater Advantages to the Perſon of a <hi>Peace-maker,</hi> than what flow from Mortification, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, Age, Experience, Holineſs and Zeal for Peace: Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to any one that knows ſo much as, and no more of him than, I do, would not ſeem, with the Multitude, to want any repute for theſe. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſaw this Book, inſcribed, <hi>The third Part of his Plea for Peace,</hi> I was very ſorry the other two had eſcaped me, and expected much from this: But, to my great grief, have found my ſelf only much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed. Now becauſe I know, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do much with his Followers towards <hi>Peace,</hi> and becauſe further, I am well aſſured he will be writing as long as he is able, I have reſolved to adventure the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106283:41"/> detecting how vaſtly, in what he has writ, at leaſt in what I have ſeen of his, on this Subject, he comes ſhort, perhaps errs, from his pretended Mark; to the end, that both he and his Partners, in their future at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, may take the better aim: For certainly were there never ſo much Humility, Meekneſs, Charity, and Patience in the World, were all our men of the moſt for bearing and moſt for giving Spirits imaginable, (which God knows is on all hands wanting) yet the way he takes is not the way to Peace.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I complain, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>manner of mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> his Plea, is mightily deficient, I may ſay culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: He muſt bear with me, if, as I promiſed, I am faithful to him; and tell him, he pleads for Peace in a moſt unpeaceable and provoking ſort: The <hi>Apology</hi> before-mentioned, (after the <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory</hi> (the deſign of which alſo ſeems to be, to inſinuate a kind of Schiſm, even amongſt our very Engliſh Biſhops) after that Epiſtle, I ſay, and a few of the initial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) ſwarms all along with the ſtrangeſt Suggeſtions, Accuſations, Aggravations, with the moſt biting Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms and Reproaches, which could well be ſtuff't in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo much Paper: I would not be miſtaken; I am not at all incenſed by them; only I really mourn before God, to ſee the Symptomes of ſuch a Spirit in ſuch a man: Good God! that men, in whom other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe appears ſo much of the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> ſhould thus expoſe it, themſelves, and their Chriſtian Brethren to the Laughter and Scorn of the Common Adverſaries, <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt faithfully, I am more concern'd for the credit of <hi>Religion</hi> in general, amidſt theſe bitter Aſperſions, than for any diſgrace, our Church, or her Friends can ſuffer from all charged on us: I am ſorry to ſay it, His
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106283:41"/> whole vein of Writing, in this Piece, betraies the want of that Singleneſs of Heart, that Candour, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Charity, Sweetneſs and Aequanimity, which not only the Deſign of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Union,</hi> but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eſſence and Conſtitution of a <hi>Chriſtian Spirit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably requires: God forbid, any ſhould take their Meaſures hence, of what temper Godly men are, and what is the language they uſe: It cannot be expected, but I ſhould give a few Inſtances to make good this Charge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, I cannot but confeſs, it is true, there were many more of the Diſſenters ſilenced, than we could have wiſht; and God grant there be not one day found much of <hi>their own fault</hi> herein (ſome Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have talked of a <hi>Combination</hi> or <hi>Pact</hi> amongſt themſelves, that except they might have their own will throughout, <hi>they would make the World know, what a breach they could make,</hi> and how conſiderable they were). But yet it is not fair to over-reckon, knowingly and in ordinary courſe, two hundred in the Sum, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>others</hi> do, <hi>[pag.</hi> 155. 210. and in the very Title Page, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> thereby to ſwel the accompt to the greater <hi>Odium,</hi> by complaining roundly Two thouſand. This I muſt conclude to be done knowingly, for ſometimes he only ſays One thouſand eight hundred; as <hi>pag.</hi> 151. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Where the Execution has been ſo vaſtly milder than the Law, where ſo much Mercy and Connivance has been ſhewn, that I am confident, there is not the moſt rigorous Biſhop in the three Kingdoms, but could give many more Inſtances of his Clemency and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, than the Law will juſtifie, there not only never to acknowledge this kindneſs, but to be oftner than the Sheets occur in his Book (I will juſtifie the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt)
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106283:42"/> ſometimes twice or thrice in a Page, <note n="*" place="margin">He is not content to do this in Engliſh ſo oft, but in Latin too. <hi>In Praefat. Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Chriſtian. Theolog.</hi>
               </note> incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating or upbraiding to us their <hi>Impriſonments,</hi> ſeems to have ſome other Deſign than <hi>Supplicating for Peace:</hi> Such ingeminated and undue Accuſations of thoſe whom we Petition, are ſtrange Arguments from Petitioners.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſame muſt I ſay much more of the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the World, The Biſhops and Church-men are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to promote, or would be glad of thoſe Severities to be executed upon them, which their Souls abhor to think of, and which the pretended Sufferers, by no Laws, nor ſo much as by the inclination of the Law-makers (as far as ever yet could appear) were at all in danger of. Thus <hi>pag.</hi> 197. <hi>Blood was never yet of a light Digeſtion.</hi> [I pray God it have not been to ſome.] <hi>Nebuchadnezzars Furnace devoured the Executioners, &amp;c.</hi> Who would not think from hence, That the Laws had made <hi>Nonconformity</hi> as Capital, as what was called <hi>Hereſy</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days? Or that the Statute <hi>De Haeretico Comburendo</hi> were by the Biſhops reinforc't, which contrarily has been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repeal'd. Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 200. <hi>And you muſt conſider alſo, that if Blood and Deſtruction be the means you truſt to, you muſt ſet up a Shambles or Trade of Butchery, and make it the Profeſſion of your Lives.</hi> Pag. 202. <hi>And then the whole Country will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, how many worſe men you leave alive, which will encreaſe the Odium.</hi> I am confident Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does not believe any of us are guilty of ſuch Inclinations, and therefore whether he acts like a Chriſtian, in ſuch ſuggeſtions as theſe, let him ask himſelf: Yet he goes on, again and again, in the ſame ſtrain, <hi>Pag.</hi> 203. <hi>But eſpecially forget not that the number of Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts in</hi> England, <hi>is ſo great, that it will weary</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:106283:42"/> 
               <hi>the Hangman to diſpatch them; or Executioners will ſcarce be found: For what if you hang a Thouſand, or Eighteen hundred Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi> Pag. 209. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, Hanging or Baniſhing Hundreds or Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands will not do your Buſineſs, but make it worſe.—And if you baniſh or kill all that are againſt you, Land will be very cheap, and Houſes cheaper; and others will call that Solitude, which you call Concord, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, Peace, &amp;c.</hi> I am weary of tranſcribing ſuch Language, and ſorry to find men, who would take it very ill not to be thought Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious, againſt their Conſciences to impute that to their Brethren, which themſelves do not believe they would ever attempt, nay, which they abhor in the leaſt to deſire: Good Lord forgive!</p>
            <p n="4">4. I muſt needs look upon his <hi>aggravating</hi> his own and the Diſſenters ſufferings, beyond truth, I am ſure beyond Probabilities, to have proceeded from the ſame want of temper. <hi>Pag.</hi> 142. He tells us, <hi>Some of the ejected Miniſters</hi> are ſo reduced, and find ſo little ſuccour, that they <hi>live upon brown bread and water.</hi> I will only, in Anſwer hereunto make, and I do hereby make, a ſolemn and ſerious Invitation of all thoſe Proteſtant Miniſters in my Dioceſe, nay, of all of them in the whole Province, who are thus low, I invite them, I ſay, hereby to my Table every day in the year; They ſhall freely eat as I do, and Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in God's Name. But it is yet an higher ſtrain which we have, <hi>pag.</hi> 153. <hi>Some have died through the effects of want.</hi> I have heard ſo indeed of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of our own Churches Clergy, ejected in the days of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> and I have reaſon, from ſome I knew. to believe it: But Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> muſt pardon me, if I tell him, I am very ſure there is more Liberality and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106283:43"/> Charity amongſt the Brethren, than that any ſuch things could come to paſs; except men were reſolved wilfully to conceal their own Conditions, and throw themſelves away in ſome diſcontented Humour: But this I take only for a <hi>Figure</hi> which he uſes, beyond the Rule in Oratory, <hi>&amp; uſque ad nauſeam.</hi> We have it again, <hi>pag.</hi> 210. Having told us after his uſe of the <hi>Two thouſand ſilenced Miniſters of late,</hi> he adds to that Sum, <hi>and the many that have died in and by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,</hi> (which we are told of again, <hi>pag.</hi> 180.) as if, beſides that vaſt number ſilenced, there were many others that fared much worſe. We muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs all theſe things are new to us, never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays well, upon a like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite Accuſation <hi>(pag.</hi> 145.) <hi>All proof</hi> (in ſuch caſes) <hi>muſt be of individuals;</hi> ſo, till ſuch proof be brought, he muſt excuſe our Faith, as we are content herein to excuſe his Charity. Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 194. <hi>We will be thankful to be under no ſeverer uſage than Colliers and Bargemen and Seamen, than begging Rogues and Vagabonds have.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Ficta voluptatis cauſâ ſint proxima veris.</q>
            <p n="5">5. Of the ſame nature are his <hi>Altitudes</hi> touching the Conformity by Law required. <hi>Pag.</hi> 189. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, That we have not miſtaken a word in all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e three Books, &amp;c.</hi> [We will ſuppoſe by the three Books he means the <hi>Liturgy, Canons,</hi> and <hi>Homilies:</hi> but what by the, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which we pretend to be infallible as he inſinuates, we know not; unleſs it be a litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Art to make ignorant People furmiſe more than he durſt affirm.] <hi>Or elſe you ſhall not preach the Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Salvation, nor labour to ſave Peoples Souls, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſwade them to think on another life.</hi> Yes, in <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vate</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:106283:43"/> as much of this as you pleaſe; or not to above <hi>five</hi> at a time, that are not of the <hi>Family.</hi> The ſame in ſenſe we have again, <hi>pag.</hi> 219. <hi>We cannot ſubſcribe that your three Books are inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llible to a word, &amp;c.</hi> I doubt not but Mr. <hi>Baxer</hi> knows a man may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, with good Conſcience, to that, which he does not know infallibly to be true: There are many things, which both he and I verily believe, yet we are not infallibly ſure we are not miſtaken: If I have a fair and clear perſwaſion or ſatisfaction grounded hereon, That, though there be Arguments on the contrary ſide, yet they are ſuch which I judge honeſtly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but on the ſide I take, the Arguments are far the ſtronger, and not ſatisfactorily anſwerable as I ſee; I ſay, I may <hi>ſubſcribe,</hi> with very good Conſcience, that I receive ſuch Doctrine, <hi>Lubens &amp; ex animo</hi> (for I do ſo) though perhaps I receive it not as of ſtrictneſs neceſſary to Salvation, or as an Article of Faith: But neither is that aſſent required in the Subſcription: We ſubſcribe only with a deſign of Peace and Union: The very Articles are intitled, <hi>Articles agreed upon—for the avoiding of diverſities of Opinions.</hi> I could tell Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that ſomewhere in this his Book, if my memory miſtake not, he ſays he durſt not reject ſuch an one, who ſhould not ſubſcribe he believed every Book of the Old Teſtament (as perhaps a Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or the Book of <hi>Canticles)</hi> or ſome other like piece, to be infallibly Canonical: yet I doubt not but he ſubſcribed, and can in Conſcience ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the <hi>ſixth</hi> amongſt the 39 <hi>Articles.</hi> Nay, <hi>pag.</hi> 167. <hi>The Nonconformiſts offer to ſubſcribe</hi> (I fear with ſome exception) <hi>the ſame Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as the Conformiſts do in the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles and the Book of Homilies.</hi> Yet neither do the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106283:44"/> Conformiſts, nor Nonconformiſts, believe every word in thoſe Books to be infallible; but they judge them a <hi>wholſome mean of Peace,</hi> and by their ſubſcription are bound not to teach contrary: What needed then thoſe terms, <hi>ſubſcribe, we have not miſtaken a word,</hi> (Did any one ever ſay ſo?) that theſe three Books <hi>are infallible to a word, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe heights ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conciliate hatred, and the reputation of cruelty to us, and ſo to blaſt Peace.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I will only ask Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, whether he thinks, that imputing to men groſs ignorance of their Office, unbelief of Religion, obdurateneſs beyond Examples, and the like, are apt terms to gain mens hearts, and unite us and them? Yet all theſe, and worſe than theſe, as far as worſe can be, we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly from his hand. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. He accuſes the <hi>Clergy at the Savoy,</hi> that is, thoſe Biſhops, Doctors and diverſe the Learnedeſt men in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms (perhaps in <hi>Europe)</hi> with whom he there trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, of having <hi>ſpoiled the work at that ſeaſon, for want of skill.</hi> But this is Modeſty in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> yet. <hi>Pag.</hi> 89. <hi>Alas! that</hi> England <hi>muſt ſuffer ſo much, while the Biſhops are learning to rule and do their Office, yea, learning what weaker perſons (i. e.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>lin.</hi> 15.) <hi>eaſily perceive. Alas! that ſo many thouſand ſouls must pay ſo dear for a few mens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</hi> Pag. 195. <hi>I ſhall give you reaſons that will make you know it, if you have but the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of ordinary men.</hi> This as to the ignorance and ſottiſhneſs, yea even of thoſe of our Party, who are ableſt, ſuch, I ſay, as were thoſe at the <hi>Savoy:</hi> Poor Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Morley,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gunning,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp;c.</hi> that had not the <hi>underſtanding of Ordinary men.</hi> Then as to our Atheiſtical, Irreligious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106283:44"/> 
               <hi>pag.</hi> 190. <hi>O! what a plague it is to the Church and World, to have Miniſters, that when they read of the neceſſity of Knowledge, Holineſs and Salvation, do neither believe Chriſt, nor themſelve!</hi> Laſtly, as to Obdurateneſs, <hi>pag.</hi> 235. <hi>Neither the Wars, nor laſting Plagues, nor dreadful Flames which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, move you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to ſee ſo great and grievous ſins.—</hi>No nor <hi>the inſtances of the Obduration of</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and the Phariſees, with the Conſequents, make you afraid, leſt wrath ſhould come upon you to the uttermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. It would be indeed endleſs, to ſet down thoſe ſeveral Paſſages he has, which (in humane appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) could have no other deſign than to expoſe our Church and Clergy: To this purpoſe, the corrupt Manners, not unjuſtly taxed in the Romiſh Clergy, both by Ancient and more Modern Cenſors of them, are carefully ſummed up, and a charitable ſuggeſtion made, that our Lives are <hi>the Commentary with which they are to be read,</hi> pag. 172, 173, 174, 175. And becauſe many Readers haply underſtand not Latin, the ſame or worſe Characters of us are ſcattered and inſinuated up and down throughout the Book in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. <hi>Pag.</hi> 50. <hi>According to this rule, which we diſſent from, all the World ſhould be ſuffered to be hanged and damned for ever, rather than a Conformiſt ſhould loſe a game at Cheſs, or a cup of Sack, or abate a Ceremony.</hi> And again, at the bottom of the ſame Page; <hi>Were I of this opinion, I ſhould not stick to make merchandiſe of Souls, and to ſell an hundred for a Benefice, and twenty thouſand for a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, nor to give over preaching, &amp;c.</hi> Then as to our Labours, and what we do in diſcharge of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, hear how vile all that is, as well as our Lives
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106283:45"/> and Hearts. <hi>Pag.</hi> 203. <hi>If theſe Preachers,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Nonconformiſts, <hi>would have talked a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle half-ſenſe</hi> (as they do often, and print it too) <hi>and have read a cold Oration, and lived like thoſe that have little ſenſe of God and Heaven, and would ſave men by a charm of words and ſhews, without ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Godlineſs and Chriſtianity, they might have had Maintenance, and as much Honour as ſuch men as theſe can put upon them. But judicious, ſerious, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty godlineſs is intolerable to all the fleſhly Tribe, whoſe Mind neither is nor can be ſubject to the Law of God, to which their intereſt and diſpoſition hath an Enmity.</hi> I again will return nothing hereto, but only ask whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things tend to Peace? Nay, do they not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently infer, That no Peace ought to be with us? For if <hi>Holineſs</hi> be the Condition and Meaſure of <hi>Peace;</hi> with ſuch men, as he makes us, what Peace can genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Chriſtians enter or maintain? Or finally, is this agreeable to his own Principles expreſſed, <hi>pag.</hi> 8? That we ought not <hi>to vilifie our Brethren, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them as Odious and Intolerable, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look that of Chriſt which is amiable in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. But as to ſome of our particular Perſons, we would have borne more ſilently ſuch Calumnies (though there are enough of us, that could never play a Game at Cheſs in our lives (the doing of which, in ſeaſon, notwithſtanding, we take not to be a ſin) nor ever made merchandiſe of Souls, nor have left off preaching, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> we would have borne this, I ſay, without complaint, were he not pleaſed to deal as unkindly, to ſay no worſe, with the very Conſtitution it ſelf. It is ſmall, perhaps, that he ſays our <hi>Articles,</hi> to which we require ſubſcription, are <hi>not intelligible, or have contrary meanings to fit</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:106283:45"/> 
               <hi>the uſe of every Subſcriber,</hi> pag. 122. (of which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation perhaps I may ſpeak anon.) Yet that is not ſo eaſily to be paſſed by, that in order to the fixing <hi>Looſeneſs</hi> upon our Principles and Cauſe (to uſe his terms) <hi>i. e.</hi> in plain Engliſh, on our Laws and Church, he accuſes the Laws and Practice of the Church of looſneſs, in ſeven Particulars; and of thoſe ſeven Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions he brings, five are notoriouſly falſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he knew it or no, I will not ſay; <hi>viz.</hi> 1, 3, 4, 5, 7: The Second is impertinent (for it pronouncing only touching <hi>baptizing Infants dying before actual ſin,</hi> can be no incouragement to looſneſs of life; and the damning of Children for the Vices of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Parents, is a Doctrine which I believe Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would be loath to be put upon to make good) and the Sixth is an uncertain Inference of his own from the words of the Liturgy taken <hi>in nequiorem ſenſum:</hi> Too tedious would it be to ſpeak ſeverally to each: In ſhort, to them all I ſay; No perſon, by the preſent Law of the Church, is to be <hi>Confirmed</hi> till he <hi>understand</hi> in ſome good meaſure, as well as be able to <hi>repeat</hi> the words of the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> being <hi>preſented</hi> (and therefore <hi>approved)</hi> as ſuch, <hi>by the Miniſter:</hi> This is plain enough from the <hi>Rubricks,</hi> and from the Preface to the <hi>Office of Confirmation.</hi> Next, No perſon is to <hi>Communicate</hi> till <hi>Confirm'd,</hi> or, in caſe of neceſſity, be <hi>deſirous</hi> of Confirmation, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof in probability imports an Underſtanding and ſome ſenſe of Religion; at leaſt, herein the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is Judge, and the Admiſſion of ſuch will be the fault of the Miniſter, not of the Law: <hi>Ignorance</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is <hi>provided</hi> againſt (eſpecially if groſs) by the Order of <hi>Confirmation.</hi> And as to <hi>Scandal,</hi> the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> is ſevere enough: The Miniſter (alone) is not
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106283:46"/> only to ſuſpend the ſcandalous perſon from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but to ſignifie it within fourteen days to the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> that ſuch ſcandalous Members of the Church may be proceeded againſt according to her Laws. Further, the Miniſter is to admit no Child to Baptiſm without God fathers and Godmothers; nor any to undertake that truſt, but ſuch who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Communion. Now what Communicants, that is (it is to be hoped) what underſtanding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, ſerious perſons, will become Sureties and Sponſors for the Chriſtian breeding up of the Children of Atheiſts, Infidels and Scorners <hi>of Religion, Chriſt, and the Holy Scripture,</hi> except they be well aſſured the Children ſhall be under their power, as to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their Education, that is to ſay, retrived out of the hands of ſuch wicked Parents, to be bred in a Chriſtian ſort? And if any ſuch perſons will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Godfathers and Godmothers to ſuch Children, and will ſo promiſe, why ſuch Child may not be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and that without any detriment to ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I muſt profeſs I ſee no reaſon: To inſiſt on the Faith of the Parents, may, I confeſs, do ſome Parents good (though he who will not be vertuous for the ſake of his own Soul, will ſcarce become ſuch for his Childs): but the want of Parents Faith, ought not with the Church to prejudice, in this caſe, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch Parents.</p>
            <p>But a more manifeſt prevarication ſcarce can be, than what he delivers as to the <hi>Viſitation of the ſick.</hi> Pag. 167. <hi>When they are ſick,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if they will but ſay they repent, and deſire it, they muſt be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in abſolute terms; though they give the Miniſter no ſatisfaction that they are truly Penitent, and have lived till then, a moſt ungodly life, and perhaps by</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:106283:46"/> 
               <hi>curſing, ſwearing and railing at an holy Life on their Sick-bed.</hi> It is plain by the Office of the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Sick, that much in that Particular is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the diſcretion of the Miniſter: <hi>Then ſhall the Miniſter exhort the ſick perſon, after this form, or other like,</hi> ſays the Rubrick: He is not then tied up, but may vary; and I ſcarce ever knew, but, in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary practice, we do ſo. Again, <hi>Then ſhall the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter examine whether he repent him truly of his ſins, and be in Charity with all the World; exhorting him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>forgiveneſs, ſatisfaction</hi> to men for wrongs done, <hi>diſpoſal of his goods, Charity</hi> to the Poor, all which, ſays the Rubrick, may be done, <hi>before the Miniſter begin his Prayer, as he ſhall ſée cauſe.</hi> And for all this there is no form at all preſcribed: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently then, it being left to the Miniſters prudence, he he may put what Interrogatories, and make as narrow a ſearch, as he ſhall think fir, and he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired plainly to <hi>judge,</hi> becauſe to <hi>exhort and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> as there appears cauſe. Now it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, theſe Exhortations and Admonitions may, and moſt frequently do, take up divers Viſits: However, all this being ſuppoſed to be done, <hi>Then</hi> (and not till then) <hi>Here ſhall the ſick perſon be moved to make a ſpecial Confeſſion of his ſins, if he féel his Conſcience burdened with any weighty matter. After which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the Prieſt ſhall abſolve him (if he humbly and heartily deſire it) after this ſort. Rubr.</hi> Where, to be ſhort, I only deſire two things may be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That after all this, the Miniſter is not command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to abſolve him <hi>[They muſt be abſolved,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> is then falſe.] but if he ſee fit to abſolve him, he is to <hi>abſove him after this ſort.</hi> It is very well known,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106283:47"/> divers of us have refuſed, and daily do, to abſolve ſuch perſons, touching whoſe Penitence we are not ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe words, <hi>if he humbly and heartily deſire it,</hi> do import the diſcovery of ſuch a ſenſe of ſin to to the Confeſſour (at leaſt ſuppoſe him in Conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence judge) as may well be conceived to bear him out in giving Abſolution; certainly, they do exclude <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Swearing, and railing at an holy Life at that time.</hi> Which things being ſo apparently thus, it would almoſt tempt a man in charity to think, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> writes againſt the <hi>Laturgy,</hi> without having du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read or conſidered it; otherwiſe he would not ſo falſly accuſe it, or traduce our Church for it. His laſt imputation is but little better than this which we have now diſpatched; Namely, that the <hi>Diſcipline of the Church is managed by one Lay Chancell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and his Court, with ſome ſmall Aſſiſtance.</hi> The <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons</hi> (of which in moſt Dioceſes there are divers, in that of <hi>Exon,</hi> from whence I came, four) through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi> generally have their Courts; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they Lay-men, nor for the moſt part do they Act mainly by Lay-Officials; and their Courts in many places are weekly: Beſides theſe, in Every <hi>Deauery (i. e.</hi> ten Pariſhes, or thereabouts) there are <hi>Archypresbyters</hi> or <hi>Deans Rural,</hi> whoſe Duty and Oath binds them to enquire into the Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well of the Clergy, as of the People, within their Precincts. So that if Miniſters and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens will but do their Duty, the Proviſion of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline is ſufficient (in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s language) for the <hi>keeping clean the Church.</hi> I will be ſtill ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to him, as to believe, he is not verſt in our Exerciſe of Diſcipline; but I could alſo have wiſh't,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106283:47"/> that he had no more cenſured it: Only I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Particular by appealing to his own Senſe, and the ſenſe of Mankind, if ſuch undue and prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Charges, as theſe, be <hi>the way to peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. And now I am ſpeaking of Prevarication, his reckoning <hi>Hooper, Latimer,</hi> and <hi>Cranmer, pag.</hi> 228. amongſt the Nonconformiſts, to conciliate thence credit to their Cauſe, and detract from us, is a kind of Art, which Ingenuity, and much more Chriſtian Veracity, would bluſh to own: I will allude in this regard to the words of the <hi>great Apostle,</hi> I wiſh not only Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> but all the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſuch as they, excepting their Bonds and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>10ly, and Laſtly, (For, I will not run the number up to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s beloved number of 20, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, though I might) There appears to me in him a great Inconſtancy to himſelf; and that not only in ſmaller points and lapſes of memory or attention (as may ſeem that, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. <hi>I never came near them,</hi> [that is, the People of <hi>Kidderminſter] nor, except very rarely, ſent them one line;</hi> yet within five lines after, <hi>I ſent them,</hi> ſays he, <hi>all the Books which I wrote;)</hi> but even in his Reſolutions and Matters of great moment, is there with him <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay?</hi> Sometimes he ſeems againſt all <hi>Subſcribing,</hi> as <hi>pag.</hi> 60, 113, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At another time, he is for Subſcribing to the Doctrine of the Church in the 39 Articles and Books of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>(pag.</hi> 12, 167, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and other terms of Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs. Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 128. The 39 <hi>Articles are a wholſome Doctrine;</hi> yet <hi>pag.</hi> 122. <hi>They are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, they have contrary meanings to fit the uſe of every Subſcriber; they are hot to one, and cold to the other.</hi> [By the way, ſometimes it is no fault in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106283:48"/> the Books to be ſubſcribed, that they are ſo worded as to allow men to abound in their own ſenſe: And we are ſure our Articles are in this no more guilty, than moſt Confeſſions, which have been penn'd for Concord, as the <hi>Augustan</hi> it ſelf, witneſs therein the Article and Clauſe touching the Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Sacrament. In ſum, when a Propoſition evidently admits of two or three ſenſes, and each of them is known, famous, and held by divers Doctors of the ſame Church, and that Church framing a Rule or Mean of Concord for her Sons, ſhall in that Rule ſet a Propoſition which takes in the ſeveral Opinions of theſe Doctors, in ſuch ſort, as to tye them up, as far as is neceſſary, and to leave them otherwiſe at their liberty, is this Propoſition juſtly to be called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible, or have Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and the Diſſenters any cauſe, if they will be conſtant to themſelves, to ſay 'tis Unreaſonable? For my own part, I wiſh ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, for their ſakes, ſome more of the Articles, and perhaps Rubricks too, were penned with ampler Latitude.] But to the Point again: That is a very unkind inconſtancy (unkind not only to us, but to the Deſign of Peace) that ſo often in <hi>pag.</hi> 16, 17, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ſays, <hi>They take it to be their Duty, in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Miniſtry, to take heed of any thing that tendeth to the Diviſion of the peoples minds, or the hinderance of the lawful publick Miniſtry, or to their juſt Diſcouragement;—</hi>Again, <hi>to take heed leſt any diſhonour, or murmuring againſt their Rulers, ariſe or be cheriſhed by reaſon of their ſufferings;—</hi>or, <hi>to ſubvert or perplex the hearers by aggravating the faults of others, or other mens worſhipping of God or breeding in them diſtaſt of the Publick Worſhip:</hi> (for all which Expreſſions I could not but inwardly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106283:48"/> thank and love him.) And again, that after he had ſaid, <hi>pag.</hi> 143. <hi>We take Conformity to be ſo far from indifferent, that we forbear to tell the World the greatneſs of the ſin, leſt men cannot bear it, and lest it ſhould diſaffect the People to the Miniſtry of the Conformiſts;</hi> That, I ſay, after all this ſo fairly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and promiſed, he ſhould ſpend three or four whole Pages continuedly (beſides what he does inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſt) in a moſt unjuſt aggravating what he calls the ſinfulneſs of Conformity, ſtyling <hi>Conformity,</hi> in their ſenſe and eſtimation of it, <hi>Aggravate Perjury, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Lying, Rebellious Profeſſion of Diſobedience to God, owning great and publick ſins, corrupting holy Worſhip,</hi> and to all theſe (when his wearied in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention ſupplied him with no more hateful terms of variation) adding after his manner, an <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 219. Again, ſays he on the ſame Subject, <hi>The ſins we fear being guilty of</hi> (namely by Conformity) <hi>are as great as almoſt any we ſhall ever preach againſt.—We fear we ſhall do much to make our hearers infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, impenitent, and utterly debauch't.</hi> Pag. 220. Yet higher: <hi>The ſins which we fear</hi> (ſtill by this dreadful Bugbear, Conformity) <hi>being of the greateſt ſort Hell ſuggeſteth, Perjury and owning the Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The very ſame ſtrain, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt word, he has again, pag. 218 and 219. and I know not indeed how often.</note> 
               <hi>of thouſands, and doing what is equipollent to the preaching Impenitence, and ſaying, Repent not, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a publick Miniſterial Profeſſion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation and Church Corruption, and of our Reſolution never to obey God in doing any Duty of ours in order to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> (pag. 221.) <hi>Offering God lying Perjury, &amp;c. for a Sacrifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ſo blaſpheming him;</hi> pag. 222. If Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> have theſe fears, certainly he would have done very well to have kept his word, and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born telling the world of them,</hi> except he would
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106283:49"/> have all the Conformable Miniſtry ſilenced (which would be fivefold the objected 2000) or which is worſe, except he deſigned by this publication of his fears not only <hi>the hinderance,</hi> but the blaſting for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>their Miniſtry, both Publick and Private.</hi> O the ſtrange Partiality and Irreſolution that is in Man! To <hi>lead, draw,</hi> or <hi>encourage thouſands into Arms</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soveraign, contrary to a man's own, and all their Oaths of Allegiance, as well as contrary to the Laws of God and Man, when ſome men <hi>ſearch their hearts</hi> they cannot find to be Perjury, nor own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perjury: Nay, <hi>they cannot ſee in ſo doing they were miſtaken in the Cauſe, nor dare repent of it, nor forbear doing the ſame, if it were to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in the ſame ſtate of things:</hi> nay, they <hi>cannot be convinced</hi> by others <hi>that they ſinned in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> (Holy Commonw. pag. 486.) Yet to Subſcribe and declare, That it is not lawful, upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King, or that an unlawful Oath cannot bind men to unlawful Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is <hi>Perjury,</hi> ſome of the groſſeſt that <hi>Hell ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth.</hi> I temper my ſelf. Good Lord deliver mens Conſciences from theſe deluſive Snares, and make us conſtant to thee and our ſelves! Without even this latter, as well as former, no poſſibility of Peace. I break off my Inſtances here, not for want of many more, but becauſe I promiſed ſo; and becauſe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I have ſaid enough to demonſtrate to Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and all the World, what I am content to call the <hi>firſt Defect</hi> in his <hi>Writings for Peace;</hi> they want, as I may call it, the Stamp or Character of Peace, they ſeem not writ with a Peaceable Temper.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:106283:49"/>
            <p> The ſecond Defect I ſhall tax, in his Writings on this Subject, is in part grounded on the former; and it is, <hi>want</hi> of that <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> even with good men, which he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght eaſily conciliate, at leaſt might have eaſily conciliated to his Writings, would he avoid, or had he avoided, what he muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be as real blemiſhes, as perhaps any can be aſſigned: If he would put leſs Gall in his Ink, if he would write with more Gentleneſs, Softneſs, Compliance and Yielding, as far as in Conſcience he can, his Books would take and perſwade a thouſand times more. It is a Rule which he himſelf preſſes, and which I remember my ſelf firſt to have read in his <hi>Gildas Silvianus</hi> four and twenty years ago, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige &amp; dic quod voles:</hi> I do not prevaricate, if I ſay, 'tis not the tenth part of our men, which are Readers, that will read his Books on theſe Subjects, by reaſon of theſe his Severities: His Fierceneſs blaſts the good he might do. But <hi>this</hi> I have ſaid enough of already, as alſo of his <hi>inconſtancy to himſelf.</hi> There are two other Points, which, out of the Faithfulneſs I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, I muſt not paſs unobſerved; And the firſt of them is (to give it the fitteſt name) The <hi>never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging an Errour,</hi> eſpecially, where it cannot well be, but he muſt be convinc't of it: I have read ſomewhere, that when <hi>Luther</hi> lay on his Death-bed (or towards his end) he confeſt to <hi>Melancthon,</hi> that he had writ too violently, and more than to him then ſeemed truth, in the Controverſie of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and the Preſence of <hi>Chriſt's Body</hi> therein. <hi>Melancthon</hi> perſwaded him to ſomething of a <hi>Retractation; No,</hi> ſays <hi>Luther, ſhould I retract any thing I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the Papiſts will ſay I retracted all, and ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I have written may be credited:</hi> I cannot tell
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106283:50"/> whether Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> may not have ſomething of this vein; but I think his Caſe and <hi>Luther</hi>'s widely diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. In a word, it would redound to his immortal credit, would he publickly revoke and recant thoſe things, which, in his Conſcience, he judges he has writ amiſs in <hi>juſtification of the late Wars,</hi> and the <hi>alterations of Government</hi> that inſued thereon: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Paſſages of this nature I could tranſcribe out of Notes from that unhappy and miſcalled Book, his <hi>Holy Commonwealth:</hi> But there is more collected and copied out of it in the biſhop o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Worcester</hi>'s Letter, and ſome other ſharper Pieces againſt him, than I could wiſh for his ſake were extant. I remember my ſelf to have read about the year 1663. in ſome <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> or <hi>Epiſtle</hi> before his <hi>Call to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted,</hi> that he himſelf takes notice of this prejudice lying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and his Writings, (the Book I have not by me) and that he there profeſſes to this purpoſe, <hi>That, did he either know of any Seditious or Treaſonable Matters which he had any where delivered or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or would any ſhew him of ſuch, he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately retract them.</hi> He and I, and all the World, except men of evil Principles, or no Principles, muſt ſay, There is a great deal of Miſchievous and Sed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticks (not to call a <hi>Spade a Spade)</hi> in the Book mentioned: Nor will I be ſo unkind to him, I ſay, as that any more of it ſhall be by me recorded againſt him. But I intreat him not to reſent it as written out of ill will, if I tell him, many do (I aſſure him I do not) believe he is of the ſame Principles ſtill, becauſe he is ſo far from having retracted, or made ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Scandal of that Book (as far as is generally known) that in the Paſſage above-cited, even after all theſe things were pardoned by the King, he ſays,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106283:50"/> 
               <hi>If he had writ any ſuch thing, he would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted:</hi> which ſeems to the World an Argument, he did not look upon that Book, which yet goes under his name, as containing in it any Treaſonable or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Matter: To which, that I may be ſtill faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I muſt add; That his going about to maintain ſuch Paradoxes, as ſome before taxed, touching the beginning of the <hi>War, &amp;c.</hi> confirm mens jealouſies, and encreaſe their admiration and prejudice in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: He would not have us to rub on theſe ſores; let him be prevail'd with, not to tempt ſuch thereto, by ſtrange defiances, who perhaps want temper to reſiſt ſo daring Provocations.</p>
            <p>Another real Blemiſh (to uſe again my former terms) and which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſuch, if he acknowledges any Blemiſhes inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his Works, is, his aſſuming ſo much unto himſelf, and looking, if not upon all men as below him, yet upon all, that will not learn of him, as <hi>young, raw, unskilful,</hi> without <hi>experience,</hi> ſometimes too without <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>ſenſe of ſpiritual things.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I have divers times pitied him, when I have read the Contempt he has in ordinary courſe expreſt of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, who have ſtudied, if not quite as long, yet, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Opinion and Suffrage of the Learned World, more legitimately, and to much better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than himſelf: Such a perſon I take the Authour of the <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> to be, if I miſtake not (as I think I do not) the man; whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully has nam'd the <hi>Debate Maker</hi> (we know what kind of men, that term in one ſenſe, belongs to) but is a man known above twenty years ago, to have had more Learning of all ſorts, than it appears to me Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has of any; and who has given the World
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106283:51"/> proof of no leſs Piety and Integrity; yet what a Child and Novice does Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> make of him, <hi>pag.</hi> 116. However; this we will eaſily excuſe, as a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure only upon a ſingle Adverſary. That I do not know how to Apologize for, which according to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (for I have not my ſelf ſeen the Bock) he has in his <hi>Firſt Part of the Plea for Peace, (p.</hi> 172. <hi>N.</hi> 12.) animadverting upon the firſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> after the Office of Publick Baptiſm, touching the Salvation of Baptized Infants, who dye before Actual Sin; <hi>When,</hi> ſays he, <hi>young unſtudied men have in this Point attained to an undoubted certainty which their wiſer Seniors cannot attain, it behoveth them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of the truth of their Inſpiration or ſpecial Indowments, either by a proportionable excellency above us in other things, or by ſome Miracles or Teſtimonies from Heaven.</hi> It is not eaſie <hi>for young unſtudied men</hi> to get into the <hi>Houſe of Convocation</hi> (by whom this Rubrick was approved, if not framed) but that the <hi>Repreſentative Body of the Engliſh Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> (a ſmall part whereof have, before Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s time, been look't upon and pronounced <hi>the Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World)</hi> ſhould by a ſingle perſon, whoſe own * Education was very defective, be ſtyled ſuch, <note place="margin">Apolog. pag. 58, 59.</note> and himſelf too plainly enough profeſs himſelf as mongſt their <hi>Wiſer Seniors,</hi> beſpeaks ſuch a Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which I will not give a name to. Other Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, which are pertinent to this place alſo, I have had occaſion otherwiſe to mention out of his <hi>Third Part</hi> already.<hi>—Nec bis repetita place bunt:</hi> Yet perhaps there is one following, exceeds all: <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodus Theologiae Chriſtianae,</hi> 1. <hi>Naturae rerum,</hi> 2. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae Scripturae,</hi> 3. <hi>Praxi Congrua, conformis adapta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Plerumque (corrigenda tamen &amp; perſicienda)</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:106283:51"/> 
               <hi>Non</hi> 1. <hi>Ignavis, feſtinantibus, delaſſatis.</hi> 2. <hi>Stolidis, Indocilibus, Sectariis (ex homine &amp; fuco judicantibus.)</hi> 3. <hi>Superbis, mundanis, malignis: Ergo, non pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, Sed Juventutis Academicae &amp; Paſtorum junio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum parti,</hi> 1 <hi>Studioſae, ſedulae, indefeſsae.</hi> 2. <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioſae, Docili, veritatem &amp; ordinem ſitienti.</hi> 3. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili, Candidae, Deo devotae. Quippe ad</hi> 1. <hi>Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis indagationem, cuſtodiam, propagationem.</hi> 2. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitatis Cultum, incrementum, Liudem.</hi> 3. <hi>Eccleſiae ſalutem, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cem, Decus. Supra omnes natae, diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, conſecratae: Dicata per Richardum Baxterum Philotheologum.</hi> (And after follows a Sentence out of <hi>Cicer. pro Roſcio,</hi> almoſt as humbly affixt) When I firſt read this Title in the Term-Catalogues, I thought it ſome Character or Summary of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Book, which the Stationer had procured, there inſerted to recommend the Book to better Sale: but having ſince got the Book, I find it is the Genuin Title given it by the Authour himſelf, and as much his own, for ought appears, as the reſt of the Book; and, in truth, it has the peculiar ſignature of his way of writing. Does he, or any man in the World, think it is a fit invitation or preparatory to a man to read a Book with patience, and without prejudice, that the Book in its front, indirectly and ſlily, calls him <hi>Slothful, raſh, fooliſh, unteachable, proud, world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, malign, &amp;c.</hi> If not this affront, yet the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion of ſo voluminous and <hi>imboſs't</hi> a <hi>Title</hi> (as one phraſes ſuch) certainly will deter moſt Readers,</p>
            <q>Quid feret hic tanto dignum promiſſor hiatu?</q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a Rule, which, if he had <hi>had his School Books</hi> ſo much about him, as he would poſſeſs us, had done
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106283:52"/> him much more ſervice, than all the fetches in by the head and ſhoulders out of <hi>Juvenal (Third Part of Plea for Peace, pag.</hi> 199, 200, 201, 202, 203, 204, 206, 209.) with as much ornament as pertinence.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Purpureus latè qui ſplendeat unus &amp; alter</l>
               <l>Aſſuitur pannus.—Sed citharoedus</l>
               <l>Ridetur, chordâ qui ſemper oberrat eadem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to return from this Infection of repeating old ends, though never ſo appoſite; Could any thing eaſily be ſaid with more (appearance of) <hi>Arrogance,</hi> in the very Title Page too, than that his Book is <hi>above all others of the ſame Subject</hi> (I know not how otherwiſe to interpret his <hi>Supra omnes</hi> [viz. <hi>Methodus Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae Chriſtianae] &amp;c.)</hi> framed, diſpoſed and hallowed amongſt other ends to the <hi>Propagation and growth of Holineſs,</hi> to the <hi>Peace and Honour of the Church?</hi> I will now for ever joyn with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in acquitting him of a fault, which he ſaith <hi>he dares not be guilty of,</hi> ſtyled by himſelf <hi>Hypocritical Modeſty. (Third Part of Plea: pag.</hi> 247.)</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief Blots I have obſerved in Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Works, which render them ſo much unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Deſign of Peace: He writes ſo <hi>pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhly,</hi> ſo <hi>variouſly</hi> or inconſtantly to himſelf, ſo <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (as if wilfully blind, or not <hi>penitent)</hi> of his own guilt, and ſo <hi>arrogantly</hi> and <hi>diſdainfully,</hi> that many are diſcouraged from reading his Books, others only take thence further pet; though I faithfully promiſe to do neither.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Were his pacificatory Writings obnoxious by none of the afore-recited defects or inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet the Materials, in my poor judgment, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106283:52"/> defective, and (without very conſiderable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) never like to take. I no whit at all doubt but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was the main Authour of the <hi>Petition for Peace,</hi> and the <hi>Reformation of the Liturgy,</hi> ſaid to have been tender'd about the ſame time, and publiſht <hi>A. D.</hi> 1661. The ſtyle and whole tenor of them abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly beſpeaks ſo much to me: Now, if out of theſe, and his later Pieces, we view what he offers or propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes towards Union, it will appear to be ſuch as might tempt men to think, he treats like thoſe who never intend to come nearer to an agreement. 1. A Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy indeed he would poſſeſs us he is for; but when he comes to particularize, Not one Office, no, not one Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Old Liturgy (except the Lords Prayer) nor ſo much as the Ancient Face, Order and Structure thereof muſt be left. And it is obſerveable, what the Petition for Peace ſtyles Alterations and Additions to the Liturgy, when it comes to be preſented, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <hi>A Reformation of the Liturgy</hi> (and indeed bears proportion perfectly to the Reformation they made of the Church, which deſtroy'd its identity and viſibility) and is clearly and intirely a new Frame, and even that ſo propoſed, or deſigned, that it would have been little more than a Direction; this being generally the ſtyle of the Rubricks (if without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence I may ſo call them) [Prayer] <hi>to be performed in theſe, or the like words,</hi> pag. 25. <hi>Then ſhall the Miniſter uſe this or the like Prayer,</hi> pag. 51. In the very Office of Conſecration of the Elements in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, <hi>Let the Miniſter bleſs them in theſe, or the like words,</hi> pag. 52. <hi>Let the Miniſter pray thus, or to this ſenſe,</hi> pag. 56. <hi>and conclude with this or the like bleſſing,</hi> pag. 58. In the Burial of the Dead, <hi>pag.</hi> 72. <hi>His power ſhall be ſuited</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:106283:53"/> 
               <hi>to the occaſion:</hi> No Form of Prayer being there ſo much as directed. So too upon Days of Publick Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, Thankſgiving, Anniverſary Feſtivals, No form at all, <hi>pag.</hi> 73. Beſides ſo great variety of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in the Order of Conſecrating and Diſtributing the Elements, is permitted in this Draught to the Diſcretion of the Miniſter, as muſt neceſſarily have bred great d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſorder and diſcontent: In a word, ſo u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal innovation, and ſuch unlimited liberty, they could never expect would be admitted. This had been to confeſs the old Liturgy obnoxious beyond all reaſon and conſcience; and our ſelves guilty of all the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſchiefs which aroſe by the oppoſing it, and by the methods uſed for the aboliſhing it. I no whit doubt but divers parts of it (as elſewhere I conceive my ſelf to have manifeſtly proved) were in uſe even in the Apoſtles days, I mean, taken up from their mouths, as having been frequently, and in ordinary courſe uſed by them, and that they have been continued in the Church ever ſince: Now Prayers of ſuch Antiquity, ſuch Primitive ſimplicity and fervour, I may add of ſuch Purity too, were it not for no other reaſon, but ſome mens (perhaps unreaſonable) diſlikes to be thrown out: I could ſpeak much here touching their intrinſick real excellency and perfection, not only as to particulars, but as to the main body: And I find ſomething, as to this Point, confeſt ingenuouſly by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, <hi>Third Part of Plea,</hi> pag. 9. <hi>Having,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>peruſed all the Forreign and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Liturgies extant in the</hi> Bibliotheca Patrum, <hi>I doubt not but our own is incomparably better than any that is there.</hi> Yet, <hi>pag.</hi> 219. he complains of <hi>ſuch failings in it,</hi> that it is <hi>a Worſhip which we (i. e.</hi> he and his Nonconforming Brethren) <hi>cannot in Faith be aſſured God accepteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:106283:53"/>
            <p> That there was never any thing purely of Humane Compoſure, but had ſome failing or defects in it, we readily acknowledge: neither did our Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver require (whatſoever he in the Page laſt cited, and other of his Party ſcrupulouſly pretend) ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to any of her Books (no not to the Correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Tranſlation of the Bible it ſelf) which was to be taken in any other ſenſe. This is a common Temper underſtood in all ſuch Subſcriptions: But that our Liturgy has more failings or faults in it, than either their Extemporary Conceptions, or the ſtated Forms, which they preſented, I muſt crave their pardon if I peremptorily deny: I have, not undiligently, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe Forms of theirs with our own; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the daily uſe of our own for many years (according to that wholſome Rubrick to all in Holy Orders) which has naturalized them to my ſpirit, or whether by ſo frequent reading, hearing and minding them, I ſee more intimately into their Senſe and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſes, than I do into thoſe which I have read but twice or thrice, or for ſome ſuch reaſon, I know not, but this I profeſs, God bearing we witneſs, that it is the ſenſe of my ſoul, I can find nothing in theirs which comes ſo naturally near unto my heart, as our own Prayers do. What have they ſo humble, eaſie, comprehenſive and emphatical in every part, as our <hi>General Confeſſion, Almighty and moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> So Pathetical as well as comprehenſive alſo as our <hi>Litany?</hi> And to paſs over other parts, the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Service</hi> is in my poor ſenſe of Devotions, moſt incomparable: What could the Wit of Men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deviſe fitrer to introduce the Celebration of that Holy Ordinance, than the <hi>diſtinct Rehearſal</hi> of the <hi>Commandments,</hi> each Communicant, in the hearing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106283:54"/> of every Commandment, having occaſion given him to examine, or reflect upon his examinations of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, touching his ſins againſt that Commandment, and, betwixt God and his own heart, in his thoughts to confeſs them; and in concluſion, after every one with his own mouth to beg diſtinct pardon for the ſins, which occur to his mind againſt that Commandment, and for Grace, as diſtinctly, againſt ſuch and ſuch ſins for the future: And all this uſher'd in too with a Prayer, which would raiſe any Soul that were not ſenſleſs, as well to a ſtrict enquiry into his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>[Almighty God, to whom all hearts be open,</hi> &amp;c. 'tis in vain therefore to flatter our ſelves with an half-ſcrutiny or Confeſſion] as to the impartial cleanſing his Soul from all reſerves of ſin. And (waving other parts) to proceed to the Prayer for the State of <hi>Chriſts Church Militant,</hi> and the <hi>Commemoration</hi> of, and <hi>prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God</hi> for <hi>the Triumphant,</hi> or <hi>thoſe who are departed this life in his faith and fear;</hi> (without which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration it appears not that the Ancient Church did ever Communicate) To proceed, I ſay, to the <hi>General Confeſſion</hi> in behalf of all the Communicants, and that moſt comfortable <hi>Abſolution</hi> annext, and then to the <hi>Surſum Corda,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Gloria in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſis</hi> (which three laſt will certainly reach home, for Antiquity, to the Apoſtles days) what more Seraphick than theſe? And how mean is, what they would have ſubſtituted in the room hereof, at leaſt comparatively? Again, beſides the Materials of our Prayers, the very Form and Expreſſion is admirable, and infinitely above that they would have obtruded. It is not every kind of ſtyle, or Character of Speech, which is fit for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers; There is ſomething in this reſpect,
<q>Quod nequeo monſtrare, at ſentio tantùm,</q>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:106283:54"/> not ſo well expreſſible to all mens Apprehenſion, which makes thoſe Prayers of theirs more non-natural. More expreſly; ſuch Heterogenous Pieces, ſuch bold Narrative or telling God of divers Matters, ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptneſs of Tranſitions, ſuch confuſed ſynonymous Petitions, ſuch long-winded Continuations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Reſponds at all (which yet I have heard Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has declared his Approbation of) yea, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any obliging the People ſo much as to a <hi>Vocal A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> (the frequent uſe whereof, as it is very ancient, ſo muſt I commend as moſt ſerviceable to engage the Peoples hearts ever and anon afreſh in Prayer, and to keep them to the Publick Devotions) theſe, I ſay, and divers more very uncouth Incidents concurring in them, render them very unſavoury to us in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of our own; and as unmeet to be received, much more to be preſcribed. Wherefore I wonder not that their whole frame was rejected; but I muſt confeſs I do wonder at the Humourſomneſs of their Authours Devotion, who ever thought of rejecting all ours, or admitting theirs into equal Authority, ſo that it ſhould have been at the Miniſters choice which to have uſed? Would they have had us had two Liturgies, or to have received one which had little to recommend it but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Novelty, and to have laid aſide another, whoſe Antiquity, Simplicity, Purity and Perſection has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted Commendations from its very Adverſaries? Theſe things they could not expect would be agreed unto, nor may yet: wherefore ſuch Terms of Peace or Accommodation they ought not to think of. Thus as to what Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and ſome of his Brethren have propoſed touching the <hi>Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:106283:55"/>
            <p> 2. As to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>remonies, as far as I can ſee, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would have therein only ſuch a Reformation, which</p>
            <q>—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na litura poteſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Take all away, and the Quarrel is at an end, we are all one,</hi> pag. 218. Sometimes indeed he ſpeaks, as if he would have theſe left to all mens choice, ſo that they <hi>who have a mind of them, might uſe them,</hi> and they who have not, might let them alone; as <hi>pag.</hi> 60, 113. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this (eſpecially if extended to all) would be of far worſe Conſequence than the preſent Injunction can be juſtly charged with.</p>
            <p>3. Epiſcopacy he expreſſes ſometimes a content to ſubmit to; yet at other times, both brings ſuch Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt it, and makes ſuch Demands, as at once deſtroy the order, and all regard to be paid to it. <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation and Church Corruption</hi> are ordinary terms for it; <hi>pag.</hi> 218, 221, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (He has much <note n="*" place="margin">Church Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, p. 241. Deſtroying thouſand, of Churches. p. 243. &amp;c.</note> worſe, but I cannot ſtay to look them). And he demands, That <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Confirmation be granted of thoſe who have been ordained otherwiſe than by Biſhops, they being ſtill reſponſible for any perſonal Inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or Crime, and that Reordination, whether Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute or Hypothetical, be not made neceſſary to the Exerciſe of their</hi> (that is, ſuch mens) <hi>Miniſtry.</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Peace, pag. 2. Take away from the Biſhop this Peculiar, and farewel Epiſcopacy, St. <hi>Hierom</hi> himſelf being Judge. <hi>Quid enim facit, exceptâ Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatione, Epiſcopus, quod Presbyter non facit?</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Euagr. This for that reaſon was not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, becauſe inconſiſtent with retaining the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Beſides, that in the judgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of the generality of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch practice can never be admitted in our own Church (I profeſs I meddle
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106283:55"/> not with Forreigners) without Schiſin and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Scandal; even the Laity would be no leſs ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized at it, than the Clergy.</p>
            <p>4. Another ſtrange Demand or Propoſal of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, and divers of his Brethrens, is, that the <hi>Exerciſe of Diſcipline,</hi> even to <hi>to the putting each ſcandalous Offender to open Penance,</hi> and in caſe ſuch perſon ſubmit not after Admonitions, the <hi>Power of Excommunication</hi> ſhould be veſted in every ſingle Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Miniſter: <hi>provided</hi> indeed <hi>there be place for due Appeals to Superiour Powers.</hi> Reform. of Liturg. pag. 79, 80, 87, 88. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet is it not determined there, what Crimes they are which are ſcandalous, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tacitly ſuppoſed that all men know them, or that every Miniſter will judge aright. How far the very Parliament themſelves were from permitting this to the Parochial Presbyteries, and what Debates there were upon this ſingle Point, <hi>what ſhould be a ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſin,</hi> or a cauſe ſufficient to have men <hi>ſuſpended from the Lord's Supper,</hi> I liſt not to ſpeak at preſent: Yet then it was demanded only for the Paſtor and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip, now to the Paſtor ſingly: This Demand at once cuts off from the Biſhops the taking cognizance of any ſcandalous Offence <hi>in primâ inſtantiâ,</hi> as we ſpeak: Before their Power of Ordination had its wound, now their <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> Yet we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them Biſhops ſtill. However let it be conſider'd whether this Propoſal would have been ſwallowed, in caſe it had paſt the Biſhops, by either People or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: A few Eccleſiaſtical Courts in a Dioceſe, that is in ſome hundreds of Pariſhes, though all of them govern'd by Canons, which the Eccleſiaſtical Judge dare not ſwerve from, are now looked upon by a great many as a ſtrange burthen; Would then the People
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106283:56"/> ever ſubmit to, or our Lawgivers go about to Erect and Authorize, a ſeverer Tribunal, regulated chiefly by a ſingle perſons diſcretion in every Pariſh? What intolerable Confuſion, Strife or Oppreſſion muſt ariſe from hence? I can think of none that this project would be good for, unleſs the Officers in the Biſhops Courts; for they undoubtedly would have ſo much work by Appeals, that they would not be able to turn themſelves to it. If any ſay this laſt Head is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but rather an exorbitancy; I anſwer, as to the Diſcipline propounded, there is a defect of Laws and Canons: but, to give an anſwer once for all, which may ſerve too in other caſes, whether Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Propoſals in general are peccant in <hi>Defect</hi> or <hi>Exceſs</hi> of what is fit, I am not concern'd to be Critical: I modeſtly ſtyled them defects, and I am ſure they come much ſhort of being any likely Mean of Peace. Witneſs,</p>
            <p>5. That he divers times inſinuates more a great deal would be done by himſelf and brethren towards Conformity, were not <hi>Subſcriptions, Declarations, Swearing and Penalties impoſed:</hi> and ſo ſeems to deſire Conformity only might be injoyn'd, but none of theſe ſtipulations or obligations thereto required: Thus, <hi>Third Part of Plea.</hi> pag. 60. <hi>Let the</hi> Agenda <hi>of Religion remain only</hi> Agenda, <hi>and the doing of them ſerve the turn, and you would have much fewer Scruplers and Nonconformiſts.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe again (for he ſeems to think us very forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) <hi>pag.</hi> 113, 156. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Firſt, as to the point of bare Church-Conformity, there is only required <hi>Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Declaration.</hi> The Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy are of another conſideration, and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not excepted againſt, And the Oath of <hi>Canonical</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:106283:56"/> 
               <hi>Obedience</hi> (which binding expreſly only <hi>In licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> I wonder men make ſuch a clamour of) and the <hi>Oath against Simony</hi> are adminiſtred only to ſuch who are inſtituted into Livings: So that upon the whole a man would think the buſineſs of Swearing ſhould never hinder any Loyal Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct from Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, being that Swearing properly ſo called is not required to Conformity. And then, Secondly, as to <hi>Subſcribing</hi> and <hi>Declaring,</hi> thoſe who pretend, they more ſcruple theſe, than they do the performing the things they thereby engage to, would either without them perform thoſe things (that is, obſerve the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Ceremonies) conſtantly, or only when they ſaw fit, and as they pleaſed. If the Later, this would be much worſe than plain Nonconformity.</p>
            <q>—Magis ingenuè Peribomius.—</q>
            <p>If the former, when they ſhall have proved that it is much more to declare a thing lawful, and promiſe either to do it, or ſubmit to the Penalty for not doing it, than it is without any ſuch promiſe ordinarily to practice it; when, I ſay, they ſhall have proved this, by any conſent, they ſhall be accounted Conformiſts upon ſuch practice without any Subſcription or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Nay, further I dare engage, let any of them come into our Churches, put on the Surplice, read Prayers orderly, go up and Preach, they ſhall have leave ſo to do, though they never Subſcribe or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; and for their ſo doing they ſhall ſuffer no Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty: And till they will prove the one, or do the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt conceive Subſcribing and Declaring is reaſonable: For ſeeing they have to do theſe things, how ſhall we know they will do them, except they
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106283:57"/> tell us ſo beforehand, and that's Declaring; or elſe write ſo, and that's <hi>Subſcribing.</hi> This abatement therefore was not to be expected, and ſo not to be propoſed.</p>
            <p>6. I add hereto, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does not propound to do, what yet he ſays he can in Conſcience do, and what he judges lawful; no, neither does he or his Brethren ordinarily practice ſo much, as far as I can hear. 1. He very honeſtly tells us <hi>(pag.</hi> 8, 9.) he can Communicate <hi>with our Pariſh Churches in the Churches Prayers, and hear the Miniſters where he lives, if they be but tolerable in the Sacred Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> Nay, he is <hi>exceedingly moved againſt the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> as well by the <hi>Arguments of many of the famous old Nonconformiſts,</hi> as by <hi>four</hi> excellent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations</hi> he there ſubjoins. 2. It appears by what he diſcourſes at large from <hi>pag.</hi> 14. to 20. and <hi>pag.</hi> 139. <hi>ſub fin.</hi> 240. and in divers other places, that he does not at all judge it unlawful, but many times ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedient to forbear their preaching in the time of the Publick Prayers and Sermons of the Church, on Lords days: Whether theſe two be his and their practice, we leave it to themſelves, we hope it is; only I do not find he propounds to do this, as a Mean of Peace. 3. He ſays, <hi>he himſelf never ſcrupled Kneeling at the receiving the Lords Supper.</hi> pag. 155. 4. I have heard alſo that in his <hi>Five Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, pag.</hi> 409. he hath theſe words, (ſpeaking upon a Suppoſal that one certain habit were enjoyned Miniſters in their Miniſtration) <hi>The thing in it ſelf being therefore lawful, I would obey him [i. e.</hi> The Magiſtrate] <hi>and uſe that Garment if I could not be diſpenſed with; yea, though ſecondarily the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be to ſignifie Purity, and ſo it be made a Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:106283:57"/> 
               <hi>Sign, yet would I obey.</hi> Now it would appear hence, that he does not think the Surplice unlawful: Yet do I not expect, he ſhould propound either of theſe two laſt in general (whatever himſelf in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular might think good to do for reconciling himſelf to our Church) becauſe he intimates <hi>Better men than himſelf ſcruple them.</hi> However, this very matter I may juſtly mention as the</p>
            <p>Seventh and Laſt Defect I will take notice of, in his Propoſals, that we can build upon little or nothing in them, as Concluſive to the Body of the Diſſenters; Becauſe <hi>What are his thoughts to Two thouſand that are Abſent,</hi> or not conſulted: <hi>Third Part of Plea: pag.</hi> 195.</p>
            <p>I have thus dealt very faithfully with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and his Writings, as to the matter of Peace: and I hope he will approve himſelf ſo wiſe and good a man as not to take with the left, what is given him with the right hand; but if he think fit to write more on this Subject, that he will ſtudy rather the cloſing Wounds, than making or widening them: He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains himſelf, he has had but bad ſucceſs in ſolliciting the Cauſe of Peace: I will therefore adventure to take my leave of him, in recommending to him what I am of the mind he may do to much better purpoſe, and what, were I in his Circumſtances, I ſhould, if not judge my ſelf bound unto, yet accept as the beſt Works, with which I could cloſe my Labours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whereas he intimates <hi>(pag.</hi> 71.) that he has wrote above <hi>Seventy Books, wherein his Doctrine and Religion are viſible;</hi> were I their Author, leſt People ſhould take all that to be my Doctrine and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is viſible in them, I would immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106283:58"/> with what care I could run them over, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly retract (either under ſome general heads, or in particular, as the caſe and my leiſure would permit) whatever I ſhould judge had been ſaid amiſs or leſs ſound. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> well knows how great a mans Works, in the Uſual Editions, begin with his Books of <hi>Retractations</hi> and <hi>Confeſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Whereas it is apparent, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has been intangled miſerably in the Calamities of the times, and perhaps contracted thence ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as render it highly unexpedient for him, as he conceives, to ſpeak in his preſent Condition, as he would or might have done, if never ſo intangled; I would, were I as he, at leaſt in conceipt diſembaraſs my ſelf, and ſit down, and conſidering the preſent ſtate of the Church, what is impoſed, what are the pretences of thoſe who oppoſe, what a fair Gaim theſe oppoſitions put into the hands of the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; conſidering, I ſay, and comprehending, as near as I could, the whole, I would freely preſent to the World my calm and unintereſſed thoughts, and give a candid and impartial Account, what I could in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience do, and what in prudence I would do, were I to begin the World again, in order to the fair and ſucceſsful Exerciſe of any Miniſtry. I humbly beg his pardon, if I think, he never can do the Chriſtian Church and himſelf a greater Service than two ſuch Works of theſe would amount to: and ſo from my heart I commend him to the Grace of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now reflect on ſome others upon the ſame Subject: and I am ſorry that I can truly ſay, I have met with ſome, who taking up Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, out-going him, acting only like thoſe <hi>who caſt</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:106283:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>abroad Firebrands and Arrows and Death.</hi> I will not name them, nor their Books; for neither does it conduce to Peace: No more will I take notice of ſome Inſignificants, one of whom, in his Title Page, has inſerted <hi>Celeuſeuca</hi> as a Book of a Pacificatory Deſign (ſo is the Father of Lies a Peacemaker) It would ſeem that Author was as well verſt in the Contents of the Book he Commends, as in the import of its Title <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuſuca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am very weary of theſe People, and will therefore, that I may not be wanting to my Deſign, paſs over to ſuch who ſeem to me to run on the <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Extream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such are they that would have nothing at all yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on our ſide: And theſe, as far as I have met with, I may reduce to two ſorts (at leaſt their vein of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, let their Profeſſions be what they ſhall, ſuggeſts to me this diſtribution of them into) <hi>Politicians</hi> and <hi>Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Politicians look upon the Diſſenters as Eaſie to be brought in by other, ſurer, and (as they conceive) more Honourable means, than any Conceſſions from us. <hi>Their Leaders,</hi> ſay they, <hi>are but few, (about a Dozen perſons, who are ſick of their Separation, and ſtand in need of a plauſible pretence, under which to return</hi> to the Church: <hi>About an hundred men,</hi> ſay others; though ſurely all vilely out in their Accounts.) Their <hi>Followers</hi> contemptible, and moſt of them of that Body, which we call the <hi>Mobile:</hi> A little time, they ſuppoſe, will wear off theſe old ſtubborn head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and mean while a brisk and impartial Execution of Laws will fetch off moſt of the People, and hinder a new Growth or Succeſſion; and thus the Faction in leſs than an Age become extinct. But <hi>to gratifie the</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:106283:59"/> 
               <hi>Pride of a few men</hi> would be endleſs (for they would ſtill be at new Demands) and beſides very dangerous in encouraging for the preſent, and propagating for the future, the numerous Diſſenſions and their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts. Thus ſome; Others (though much the fewer, but perhaps the wiſer, yet I fear it will be no wiſdom to leave it to the Event to determine which part is wiſeſt) Others I ſay, bid us take no notice of them; go on quietly in our way; Oppoſition, by a kind of Antiperaſtiſis, embodies, ſtrengthens, and ſo multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies them. To ſuch purpoſes as theſe are the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of our men who pretend to an inſight into <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Divines ſeem to judge, they are to be diſputed and reaſoned out of their Diſſenſion: and I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, they have uſed ſuch variety and ſtrength of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as if the thing were thus to be done, in all probability, would not have failed of effecting it. But I know not whether I may ſay of the Arguments on both ſides, what <hi>Solomon</hi> does of all Events, <hi>There is nothing new under the Sun.</hi> The <hi>New Conformity,</hi> as ſome are pleaſed to ſtyle it (that is, The New Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, Declaration, Reordination, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> might perhaps, at its firſt Commencement, admit of ſome new Argument: But as to Conformity, as it ſtood by the old <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> the Queſtion has been ſo long agitated and ſifted ſo near, that at leaſt it is very hard to preſs any thing, which has not been ſaid before in one form or other; and by this time (that is, after near Twenty years debate) I may pretty ſafely ſay as much of the other; ſo far am I from being of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s mind, <hi>That, as the Presbyterians may ſay, their Cauſe was never yet publickly pleaded; ſo may thoſe on the other ſide, who</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:106283:59"/> 
               <hi>could have yielded to the Old Conformity, but cannot to the New.</hi> Third part, p. 6. A ſtrange kind of Pleaders theſe! who think they are never heard, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they have their will. Alas! how little of new was there in <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> it ſelf? And afterwards, when the <hi>Reaſons for Reformation</hi> came forth, what had they of moment, which had not been pleaded by their famous <hi>Cartwright,</hi> my <hi>Names-ſake,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> and others, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad Cramben,</hi> long before? The <hi>Argumenta ad homines,</hi> which, of all ſorts of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, are ſtill likelyeſt to be new, we ſee ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie now not at all with them; they will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the judgment or practice of their Anceſtors, no nor of their preſent Brethren; ſome of them not by their own at all times.</p>
            <p>So that I muſt profeſs I utterly deſpair of ever ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nonconformiſts diſputed into the Church; not through any Diffidence to our own Cauſe, or through any Inſufficiency or Suſpicion of our own Arguments, which, I ſay again, I can perceive no defect in, either, as to weight or number; but there is ſuch an incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tetter in the World as a <hi>Diſputandi pruritus,</hi> and a <hi>Non perſuadebis, etiamſi perſuaſeris.</hi> Nor have I any more hopes as to the ſucceſs of the Politick Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods. Theſe People have been tried long enough, and glory in that <hi>Motto,</hi> which one made the Title of a Pamphlet againſt them, <hi>Semper Iidem.</hi> Hear what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us, amongſt many other things to the ſame purpoſe, in that ſo oft cited Piece, <hi>pag.</hi> 195. <hi>Experience telleth you, and all the World, that you are miſtaken [viz.</hi> in thinking to reduce us by Violence] <hi>We read the ſame Books in the Priſon, if there we may have them, as out of it. And what abundance of Ministers within theſe Ten years have come out of</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:106283:60"/> 
               <hi>long impriſonment in the ſame mind as they went in, yea much confirmed? But whom can you name that came out convinced? How long have they ſuffer'd not only poverty and reproach, but that ſilencing which they account a greater evil?</hi> And again, pag. 196. <hi>In a word, I know, not only my ſelf, but ſo many of the Nonconformable Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>ſo well, that I utterly deſpair that ever ſilencing or impriſonment ſhould change their judgments.</hi> Much more he has to the ſame purpoſe, and what ſome would call more Reſolute Bravado's. Then, as to the Extinction of the Faction by the death of theſe Leaders, ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 203. <hi>They will chooſe to themſelves Teachers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors out of the best qualified of the People that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive</hi> (for as to our Orders, they value them not, they have a new Notion of Ordination, fitted for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; Ordination is nothing but a ſolemn Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Church, that ſuch a Perſon is qualified for the Miniſtry, and ſo called thereto by Jeſus Chriſt: nay, 'tis but a <hi>Confirmation and Complement of the Peoples choice,</hi> ſays <hi>Ames, De Conſcient. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>A publick approving a man as fit to be a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, A ſolemn allowance of his Call.</hi> J. H. p. 8. Mr. <note place="margin">Queſtion of Reordinat.</note> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf too is of the ſame mind, <hi>Diſput. pag.</hi> 147. ſo that the People, or their Elders, hereby may lawfully ordein) <hi>They will chooſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſuch, and will not lay down worſhipping God according to their Conſciences, though they were uſed for it as</hi> Daniel <hi>was, contrary to Law. And theſe new Paſtors per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will have leſs Moderation than the old: And thus you will be troubled with a ſucceſſion of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> But I could have furniſht Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and the World, with another Confutation of this vain hope of the Extinction of the Faction by the death of their
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106283:60"/> Leaders: We ſhall never want a new Succeſſion of them, and thoſe violent too to the purpoſe, out of the ſame Nurſeries whence divers of the Preachers in the Field Conventicles lately in <hi>Scotland</hi> came: Thoſe Seminaries have been long enough ſo well ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they can afford us at any time Sholes of Teachers, Presbyterian Paſtors, Independent Paſtors, Anabaptiſt Paſtors, Millenaries, Quaking Holders-forth (men or women, choice without doubt). Kind Neighbours they are, and will at any time, and at all times, as long as they can keep up, <hi>bring forth out of theſe their Treaſures,</hi> able Leaders to the Factions <hi>new and old,</hi> and Teachers full of Zeal too, for each to their own hearts content, as we have too long had woful Experience, however ſlow of belief we have been.</p>
            <p>But it will be returned upon me, To what end will it be then to ſeek to gain in to our ſelves the preſent Diſſenters? I anſwer; It is not to be thought that all of them will come in upon any terms whatſoever, but it may be hoped, the honeſt men will be pickt out of them, and ſtrengthen us by their Union; and the reſt of them will be diſcovered to be what they are; and no good men will p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty ſuch incorrigible perſons, if they fall under the laſh of ſevere Laws.</p>
            <p>Now to this purpoſe I muſt ſtill inſiſt upon the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient</hi> propounded, as the only probable one, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Mutual Conceſſions</hi> and <hi>Approaches:</hi> At the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> that Reverend and Great Man, Biſhop <hi>Morley,</hi> tells us, the Generality of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming <note place="margin">In his Letter p. 13.</note> Divines <hi>ſhewed themſelves unwilling to enter upon Diſpute, and ſeemed to like much better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way tending to an amicable and fair comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which was wholely fruſtrated by—</hi>a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106283:61"/> perſons <hi>furious eagerneſs to ingage in a Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This was it ſeems the ſenſe of both ſides at that time: Now if compliance be likelyeſt to do the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, let us Relax a little on both hands, in the fear of God, and fall upon it. Let us candidly conſult, what good Conſcience, what Prudence will bear towards an Accommodation.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo vain, as to take upon me to determine, nor ſcarcely ſo much as to point our, what is fit to be yielded: nor is there any thing of what is at preſent injoyned, which, I bleſs God, grates on me: There are ſome, who have told us, that had the <hi>Cathedral way</hi> of performing the daily Service been injoyned, as only the <hi>Parochial</hi> is, we had had many more Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts: I ſeriouſly and cordially, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profeſs, That though by reaſon of my Age, the Cathedral Service was very ſtrange to me at firſt, I never having known any ſuch way of Worſhip till his Majeſties happy Reſtauration, yet having immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereupon the advantage to underſtand it, and be converſant in it, I have ſince, a thouſand and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, worſhipped God therein <hi>with my Soul and all that is within me:</hi> I ſpeak this not out of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but in the fear of that God who knows my thoughts and heart, who ſhall judge me one day, and for his glory, and for the benefit of others who may be undeceived, or a little temperated in their Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, by this my ſo ſolemn Profeſſion and Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To condemn without trial, we ſay, is unjuſt, but it is too uſual; The holy Joy and Raviſhment of Soul, which are truly to be found in this way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when voice and heart together ſweetly aſcend to God on high, the tranſports of Divine Love, and longings for that bleſſed Eſtate, wherein ſome ſuch
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106283:61"/> employment of praiſing God, and ſinging to him will be at once the work and felicity of our Lives, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Senſual Life and Pleaſures, and the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph Faith conceives over all things here below; Theſe, I ſay, and the like emotions of Soul towards God and Heaven, are with me Arguments for our grave Cathedral Muſick, never to be forgotten, never to be confuted. While I write theſe thing, I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall out into my</p>
            <l>Awake up my glory, awake Lute and Harp; I <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 9, 10, 11, 12. Old Tranſlation.</note> myſelf will awake right early, &amp;c.</l>
            <l>Set up thy ſelf, O God, above the Heavens, and thy glory above all the Earth.</l>
            <p>Oh! that ſome of the Nonconformiſts did but hear that Anthymn ſweetly ſung: I am very confident there are no ſerious ſober men amongſt them, who would be long Nonconformiſts to ſuch duly regulate Muſick'; and that they are ſo now, I cannot but impute it to prejudice of Education, want of Experience and of Exerciſe herein, and the like. The very Order in theſe Aſſemblies, to ſerious unprejudiced men, is a goodly ſight, and a little image of Heaven.</p>
            <l>A fine aſpect in fit array, <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Herbert,</hi> pag. 102.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Neither too mean, nor yet too gay,</l>
            <l>Shews what is beſt.</l>
            <p>And, in the ſame Divine Poets language, as to the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick it ſelf, when a devout Mind ſtrikes in with it, 'tis to ſuch the</p>
            <l>Sweetest of ſweets,—<note place="margin">Pag. 57.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And knows the way to Heavens door.</l>
            <p>I do not deny but that there may be faults in ſome
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106283:62"/> peoples vanity, looſneſs, want of ſerious, heavenly minds: But are there not theſe kind of people under all ſorts of Worſhip whatſoever? And do we not both teach and endeavour the Reformation hereof? I will not here recapitulate, what I have writ <hi>elſewhere,</hi> touching the ſerviceableneſs of <hi>Quires,</hi> as well to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotion, as to the holy Education of ſuch for the Miniſtry, who from their Infancy, through their whole Age, may ſerve God zealouſly in divers ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; capacities. I will, therefore, only add, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is to be reduced, I can never think of conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the aboliſhing (what ſome poſſibly will call <hi>Conformity in Alt)</hi> I mean the <hi>Cathedral Service.</hi> Nor do I find that it is deſired by the ſobereſt of the Nonconformiſts themſelves; witneſs the following Paſſage. <hi>For the Ceremonies—I wiſh they might be left to the Conſciences and Prudence of Miniſters and People every where,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">So too, the Bill for Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation</note> 
               <hi>excepting the Cathedrals, to uſe them or forbear them, as they judge it moſt meet for one anothers Edification,</hi> ſays the Author of the <hi>Healing Paper, pag.</hi> 30. And I queſtion not but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Brethren had approved this, as well as moſt of his other Propoſals, becauſe they were deſign'd to <hi>Chalk out the way to the Parliament to open the Church door for ſober Nonconformiſts.</hi> Anno 1678. Ep. to the Reader.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding what I have ſaid of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency both of the <hi>Common Prayers</hi> themſelves, and of the <hi>Cathedral performances,</hi> I do not conceive the Alteration of an Expreſſion, or perhaps here and there, of a whole Prayer, or two, by Law, or the diſpenſing (ſtill by Law) with ſome Ceremony, <hi>in loco,</hi> for the ſake of ſome unſatisfied, but otherwiſe regular Chriſtians (who are not ſuppoſed of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106283:62"/> Body) I ſay, I do not conceive, ſuch Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Relaxation as this, would break the Harmony and Beauty of our Worſhip, or diſturb the Union and Peace of our Church: I will therefore freely publiſh my thoughts to be, That whether we conſider the nature of the thing it ſelf, or with regard to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Rule <hi>(Rom.</hi> 15. 1, 2.) <hi>Not to pleaſe our ſelves, but every one of us to pleaſe his Neighbour, for his good, to Edification:</hi> In either regard, I ſay, there are ſome <hi>Collects,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Rubricks</hi> too, which, with all duty and ſubmiſſion, I humbly conceive might be altered for the better. And further, That in ſome ſeaſons and in ſome private places, where Ceremonies want that Auguſtneſs which the advantage of Publick and great Congregations gives them (and in which kind of Aſſemblies they are chiefly requiſite) if the Obligation to a Ceremony or two were taken off, the Benefit which might hence redound to the Church would be very conſiderable, both in reſpect of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes and ſtrength thereby, as alſo perhaps in other Points. And I ſeem to my ſelf herein to follow the ſenſe and guidance of our Church; for even at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the Injunction of the Ceremonies does not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to me to extend it ſelf to all places and ſeaſons: As for inſtance; A Miniſter baptizes a Child in caſe of real Neceſſity in private, and he neither habits him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Surplice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor ſigns the Child with the ſign of the Croſs, and the Baptiſm is by the Rubrick declared <hi>Lawful</hi> and <hi>Sufficient:</hi> nor did the Miniſter offend in the Omiſſion of thoſe Ceremonies, becauſe no Law required them. In this particular then the Senſe and Spirit of our Church, touching the Places and Occaſions, which require Ceremonies, is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparent.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:106283:63"/>
            <p> There are alſo divers other Points, which, when once the Deſign of a fair and complaint Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be on foot, will be fit to be mentioned; and indeed will both of courſe offer themſelves, and be, I judge, as eaſily granted; ſuch are, the <hi>Liberty</hi> (which the Preface to the Second Book of Homilies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) of <hi>exchanging Apocryphal Leſſons</hi> for Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ones, any <hi>Amendment</hi> of ſuch <hi>defects</hi> as can be proved (for all that is ſaid cannot be proved) in the <hi>Calendar,</hi> The uſe of the moſt <hi>correct Tranſlation of the Pſalms,</hi> A better <hi>Metrical Verſion</hi> alſo, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome like matters; which, though we may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſmall, ſome Diſſenters do not.</p>
            <p>Without doubt, ſome ſuch Mitigations proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable might have been obtained, when that <hi>Way tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a fair and amicable compoſure</hi> ſpoken of by the Right Reverend Biſhop <hi>Morley,</hi> was not yet preclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: But now, as to the Diſſenters (who perhaps expected another Game than they have found) it may be truly lamented, to uſe <hi>Caeſars</hi> words in a like caſe, <hi>Accidiſſe his, quod plerumque hominibus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De Bell. Civil. Com. 1.</note> 
               <hi>nimiâ pertinaciâ atque arrogantiâ accidere ſolet, uti eò recurrant &amp; id cupidiſſimè petant, quod paulò ante contempſerint;</hi> nor is it at preſent (though poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they think, as they daily complain it is) in the Biſhops power to help them: <hi>Id poſsumus, quod jure poſſumus.</hi> They who know any thing of our Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, know the Biſhops are as much tyed, by the Laws, to the Obſervation of the Laws, as any Order of men whatſoever: And though ſome may ſay the Penalties upon us in this regard are ſmall or rarely inflicted; yet, what Penalties operate in others, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ought to do in us: And I ſee not how in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience we can diſpenſe, when the Law allows no
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106283:63"/> ſuch thing: for we know not the Miſchiefs, which may ariſe from ſuch our Laxneſs; and it would be a very unjuſtifiable preſumption, and beſides inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence with that mans ſelf, who pretends to obedience and ſubmiſſion to the Wiſdom of the Conſtitution, for him upon his ſingle judgment to over-rule the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of that Wiſdom, that is, the Laws of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In plain Engliſh, when every one bears his own burthen, the hardſhip or rigour of the Laws, if any there be, is to be laid firſt at their doors, who by their Combinations had made it neceſſary for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in its own defence, to break the knot; and then at theirs, who through refractorineſs, when they were asked what would ſatisfie them, replied and ſtood to it, <hi>All or Nothing</hi> (ſome men may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Language if they pleaſe). Nor are the Law-makers to be charged with ſeverity: Such ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved perſons, as I ſpeak to, can only thank them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they have one Member of their fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned choice; though perhaps many of them, whom they take for their Enemies, are ſorry for it, beſides themſelves; and yet, I ſay again, not able to help them. For Laws neither can nor may be altered, (and Liturgies varied) as oft as men could wiſh: then perchance Government, as well as Laws, would be of very ſhort life.</p>
            <p>Being then ſuch Alterations cannot be made in the Liturgy for the preſent, as might effect the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> we muſt turn our ſelves in the next place to think what can be done. And here, firſt, it offers it ſelf, that one main Branch of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and Declaration preſcribed in the Statue
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106283:64"/> for Uniformity, which ſtuck much with divers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Covenant, by the very Letter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Statute, ceaſes within half a year: I truſt this may give eaſe, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rhaps open the door to ſome. And whether the ſame inducements, which ſwayed the Wiſdom of the Nation to prefix ſuch term for the expiration of that Clauſe, might not be as forcible towards the taking off another clauſe or two, which are ſcrupled by ſome, (Poſſibly it is as neceſſary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſhould be forgotten as the Covenant) whether alſo the Old Oath of Allegiance might not be ſo worded or explained as to ſerve in the room, not only of this Declaration, but of another new Oath too, I ſhall not adventure to propoſe: But this I will ſay, that the Clauſe touching the Covenant ceaſing of it ſelf, as beforeſaid, I do not ſee what is left in this Declaration or Subſcription, (call it as you pleaſe) which he, who is reſolved faithfully to keep the Oath of Allegiance, according to its true intent, need at all to ſcruple, except only that Branch of <hi>Conforming to the Liturgy as it is now by Law e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht.</hi> Yet this Obſervation, though it remove a ſuggeſtion which might afterwards have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, leaves us nevertheleſs where we were, ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as ſome may account it) upon the Rock of Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Conformity to the Liturgy. This would ſeem now the only ſtop. For relief then herein, we muſt conſider whether there be no Mitigations or Lenitives to be found, without Repeal, or too diſhonourable Change of Laws, which we cannot expect.</p>
            <p>And I know no fitter Clue in the Entrance of this Labyrinth, than the examining what has been offer'd
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106283:64"/> hereto by any of the Diſſenters themſelves: for from them only, under God, we can tell what will pleaſe them. Amongſt all that have writ upon the Deſign of Accommodation, there is only one come to my Hand, that ſeems to me to offer any thing of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (more there may be whoſe Books reach not me here) I mean the Author of <hi>The Peaceable Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Conſcience.</hi> His Work ſpeaks him a man of Real Learning and Temper; and I wiſh his Brethren, who value themſelves above him, would learn of him. Now the ſum, as to the point in hand, which he propoſes, is; They <hi>cannot,</hi> he ſays, <hi>give their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to every thing contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Liturgy</hi> and Appendages, as the Statute requires; but they can <hi>conſent to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Book in the Conſtant Lords-day Service.</hi> And as to what <hi>Exceptions they have againſt ſome things in the By-offices, the Occaſional Service, the Rubrick, and otherwiſe, they who ſcruple the performance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſhall be ready to permit others to perform ſuch Offices to thoſe, who deſire them.</hi> I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally believe him ſincere in this, and that he would not diſſwade or diſcourage People from the uſe and love of the Regular Offices, but let them injoy their freedom, being content with his own, could he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it; though perhaps ſome will be apt to think, it would ſoon be otherwiſe generally, did this their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal take. But notwithſtanding this my Charity, I muſt confeſs, I do not judge what he propounds ſufficient to qualifie men, (otherwiſe meet) for a Parochial Charge. My meaning is, this is no ways a tolerable meaſure of Conformity: For all they are thus ſuppoſed to conſent to, (and conſequently to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106283:65"/> promiſe) being the uſe of the Conſtant Lords-days Service, they are not tyed (that I mention not yet occaſional Week day Prayers, Feſtival Services, even upon the Great Feſtivals, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> they are not tyed, I ſay, to, nor have we any Security they will obſerve; the very Forms of Adminiſtration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or of Baptiſm; and by this means we may have both Sacraments adminiſtred according to mens pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate pleaſure, which I think no one will judge ſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Either then they muſt offer more Conformity to the Liturgy, than this mentioned amounts to, or not expect (as it is deſired in the Bill for Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation) <hi>to be admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and injoy the uſe of their Miniſtry without Moleſtation.</hi> This is a great defect, which I could not but note in that Writers Propoſals, as much as I like him otherwiſe. I know indeed he is for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the 39 Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that is Conformity to Doctrine; I ſpeak now meerly of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rmity to the uſe of the Liturgy, and, I ſay, his Propoſals herein are very ſhort of the great Deſign, Union: For if we be not united in Sacraments, how equivocal is the Union we pretend to?</p>
            <p>I confeſs he has laid his Deſign with much more Modeſty, as to the Repeal and Change of Laws, than any I have ſeen: for an Explanatory Act (at leaſt what may be called fitly enough an Explanatory Act) of the Statute of Uniformity ſalves all: Let it but be allowed, by a favourable Interpretation from the Legiſlative Power, that ſuch a qualified or miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated (indeed in our eſteem a very partial) Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Liturgy, ſhall be judged ſufficient for ſome purpoſes, and then naturally enough the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106283:65"/> of Aſſent and Conſent may be alſo interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with proportion thereunto.</p>
            <p>But there is yet another Defect, which I muſt challenge in the <hi>Petition</hi> or <hi>Demand</hi> made upon ſuppoſal of ſuch Conformity allowed by Authority, and performed by the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſenters: They deſire here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that <hi>they may be admitted to any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Preferment.</hi> I ſay, here is one Limitation wanting to make it conſiſtent with what this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himſelf propounded before; and after that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, or two perhaps, to make it conſiſtent with Reaſon and Equity. He had above propounded, That the <hi>Ceremonies ſhould be left to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Prudence of Ministers and People every where, excepting Cathedrals:</hi> In theſe then, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Propoſals, a Plenary Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is to be obſerved inviolable: But in his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Poſtulatory part, he would have this new ſort of Conformiſts to be admitted, upon ſuch their Conformity, <hi>to any Eccleſiaſtical Preferment:</hi> To be conſiſtent with himſelf, he ought here to add, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in Cathedrals;</hi> otherwiſe, by this Explanato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Act deſigned, we ſhould have Members, (at leaſt might have them) in Cathedrals, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fully conform, and conſequently an Half-Conformity, or not that, would enſue there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p>Yet admit even this Limitation were put in, and then <hi>Any Eccleſiaſtical Preferment,</hi> will ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Any <hi>Rectory, Vicarage,</hi> or as we uſe to ſpeak, Any <hi>Cure of Souls:</hi> I ſay ſtill, as before
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106283:66"/> intimated, it is very unreaſonable and unfit there ſhould be any Incumbents, to whom the Charge of Souls is immediately, according to Law, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Biſhop, who ſhould not be bound to Adminiſter the Sacraments, to Bury the Dead, to Catechiſe the Youth according to the Church-Catechiſm (and prepare them thereby for Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) to obſerve and celebrate, according to Order, the Great Feſtivals, as of our Lord's Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, Circumciſion, Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which Offices are evidently here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted under the term of <hi>by-Offices.</hi> And the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs hereof will further appear, if we conſider, that there are divers Pariſhes, wherein no ſmall part are diſaffected to Conformity: Theſe ſhall ſtickle hard for ſuch Miniſters, which when they have got, they ſhall only by their Practice (and poſſibly Doctrine too) be confirmed in their diſaffection; and theſe ſhall become Nurſeries of Nonconformity, and a proviſion thus made for the propagating Male-content againſt the Church: Now however, we would be willing to allow all favour to ſuch who unhappily already do in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience diſſent, yet we can never agree to ſuch Methods, which will be ſure to perpetuate Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So that, except they throughly Conform, I think they ought not to deſire to be admitted to Parochial Cures, but only to Preach publickly as Aſſiſtants to ſuch Incumbents, who would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy or accept them, or where otherwiſe there were want: And even herein alſo methinks there is need of another Limitation, <hi>viz.</hi> that whereas ſuch Preachers are ſuppoſed by Law indulg'd, or
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106283:66"/> diſpenſt with, as to their own Scruples, they give good Caution never to Preach againſt ſuch Uſages of the Church, which they Scruple, or to which they Conform not.</p>
            <p>All then I can reaſonably ſay in this Caſe is, That if it could be obtained that the Subſcribing the Thirty nine Articles, the promiſing to read Orderly Morning or Evening Prayer reſpectively before Sermon, and receiving the Lord's Supper, at leaſt three times a year, according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our Church, might by Authority be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted a ſufficient Conformity to the Liturgy of the Church, to capacitate Perſons, otherwiſe fit and in Epiſcopal Orders, to preach publickly in ſuch and ſuch places (caution being firſt given to the Biſhop for the peaceableneſs of their Doctrine) I do not ſee but our Church doors will ſtand as open to the Nonconformiſts, as in Equity or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they can deſire; at leaſt as in ſafety the Church can allow. I muſt beg their pardon for ſaying no more (I cannot, with juſtice to my own ſenſe); and I ſhall ſcarce obtein pardon from ſome, for ſaying ſo much: but I thought it for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, to ſay what I have; to which Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good we are all of us in duty bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all we can, whatever diminution we ſuffer in ſome mens eſteem.</p>
            <p>I know it will be demanded of me, What need of letting theſe men in? Are there not Miniſters enow already, and more than are Honourably provided for? I anſwer, We ſhall have never the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106283:67"/> more for this Relaxation: Theſe men, in behalf of whom I have ſpoken, are in being already, and will preach ſome where or other; and 'tis better we had them in Publick than in Corners, that ſo the Church either had ſecurity for their peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able doctrine, which I verily believe we may have as to moſt of them, or opportunities to convict them of their Sedition. But I have other-gueſs Arguments than theſe, that move me:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To thoſe who ask, What need of more U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? I return, What need of Holineſs? What need of Godlineſs, Charity, Juſtice? Are theſe Chriſtian Duties, and is not Union and Peace as much ſo?</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am and muſt be in the mind, that the ſtrength of the Proteſtant Cauſe, both here at home and throughout Chriſtendom, lies in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Proteſtants; and the Glory, Purity and Power of Chriſtianity, in this World, ſtand or falls with Proteſtantiſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I muſt be ſo ingenuous as to acknowledge, That though perhaps the City, and divers parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Places, flouriſh with ſuch Preachers as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they had before, yet the way of Preaching in many parts of the Countrey, and in ſome no obſcure places too, might be much improved, and needs ſupply: And it can never be made out to the World, but it were better we had too many good Preachers, than too few.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:106283:67"/>
            <p> I could tell ſome men in their ear, They alſo have ſtrangely multiplied <hi>Curacies,</hi> which are too often vacant: The Lord forgive them, and redreſs this great Evil in his Church. If I thought not theſe Arguments ſufficient, I would add more, which occur plentifully; but my Poſtſcript is too much ſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n already.</p>
            <p>I am not unſenſible, how difficult it will be, to gain even this Point, which I have pleaded for, as ſmall as it ſeems to ſome: That it neither can, nor ought to be attempted, without the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power, I have ſaid often enough: And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the Diſſenters would do well by perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much Obedience to the Laws, as they can to encourage and invite Authority to ſavour them, by a Relaxation in what they cannot. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by way of Concluſion, make one Propoſal, which, above all yet done or ſaid, is the likelieſt means, in my opinion, to bring on an Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays (Part. 3. p. 8.) <hi>Where he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he came to the beginning of the Churches Prayers, when he could, and ſtaid to the end.</hi> And that peaceable worthy man above-commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (whom I know not, but whoſe name I found out, by comparing one Book with another) Mr. <hi>John Humphrey,</hi> the Author of both Pieces, touching <hi>Reordination,</hi> of the <hi>Healing Paper,</hi> and of the <hi>Peaceable Reſolution,</hi> &amp;c. ſeems to offer for himſelf, and divers of his Brethren, not only <hi>to uſe,</hi> but to <hi>ſubſcribe to the uſe of,</hi> the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as to <hi>the Ordinary Lords-day Service.</hi> It is plain then, that ſeveral of the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106283:68"/> Preachers, can in Conſcience uſe thus much of the Liturgy: yet I never heard, either that Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> when he preached publickly Occaſional Sermons (as he calls them, and to which, if I miſtake him not, he conceives his old Licence might authoriſe him ſtill) I ſay, I never heard, either he, or any other of his Brethren, did read any part of the Liturgy before any of their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: That they ſtill frequently preach, I no whit queſtion: Now my Propoſal is, That <hi>before all ſuch Sermons, at leaſt before their more Solemn Ones, on the Lord's days, they would reſpectively uſe the Morning and the Evening Prayer, which they thus acknowledge they could uſe, and ſubſcribe to the uſe of; and by their practice thus teach the People the lawfulneſs of ſo much Conformity.</hi> I ſhould not doubt but ſuch frequent, reverent and ſerious uſe of it, would ſoon recommend it to their Conſciences, and to the Conſciences of all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber perſons among them; and this practice would not only be an Argument, that they talk about Accommodation in good earneſt, but certainly prevail with the Biſhops to uſe their intereſt, and addreſs to his Majeſty in Parliament, for ſome ſuch Relaxation or <hi>Explanatory Act</hi> as is deſired. This would be ſomething of a coming nearer to us, and is but reaſonable in them, for that they expect we ſhould be moving towards them. But if they will ſtill totally hold off, and only tell us They can do thus and thus much, towards Peace, yet really do nothing, it is a very ſhrew'd ſing, either that there is not in them that Cordial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Union they pretend to, or that their <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:106283:68"/> is more the Act and Reſolution of their <hi>Will,</hi> than of their <hi>Conſcience;</hi> which if it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, they will for the future find leſs belief and fewer Favourers.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
